<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>Aeneid</title>
	<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
	<author n="Verg.">P. Vergilius Maro</author>
	<editor role="editor" n="Williams">Theodore C. Williams</editor>
<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
		<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
		<respStmt>
		<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
		<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
		<name>William Merrill</name>
		<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
		<name>David Smith</name>
		</respStmt>
<funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>about XXX57Kb</extent>
	<publicationStmt>
		<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
		<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
		<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
		<availability status="free">
    <p>This text may be freely distributed, subject to the following
    restrictions:</p>
    <list>
	<item>You credit Perseus, as follows, whenever you use the document:
	    <quote>Text provided by Perseus Digital Library, with funding from The National Endowment for the Humanities. Original version available for viewing and download at http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/.</quote>
	</item>
	<item>You leave this availability statement intact.</item>
	<item>You use it for non-commercial purposes only.</item>
	<item>You offer Perseus any modifications you make.</item>
    </list>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc default="NO">
	<biblStruct default="NO">
	  <monogr>
	    <author>Vergil</author>
	    <title>Aeneid</title>
	    <respStmt>
	      <name>Theodore C. Williams</name>
	      <resp>trans.</resp>
	    </respStmt>
	    <imprint>
	      <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
	      <publisher>Houghton Mifflin Co.</publisher>
	      <date>1910</date>
	    </imprint>
	  </monogr>
	</biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      
      <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
      <state unit="book" />
      <state n="chunk" unit="card" />
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage default="NO">
	<language id="en">English
      </language></langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>11/96</date>
	<respStmt><name>WM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Scan, proofread, tag public domain text.</item></change>
      <change><date>12/19/96</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: verg.a.w_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.2  2010-07-02 16:42:49  student
fixed place tags - zr

Revision 1.1  2009/12/09 18:06:47  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.5  2009/01/12 22:23:43  rsingh04
commented out extra chunking scheme

Revision 1.4  2006/02/10 20:50:31  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.3  2005/11/21 20:02:26  lcerrato
changed two suspected typos book 10 line 505; cuch to such; Ioud to loud
no source found, not confirmed

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 16:34:36  packel
removed stray item tags

	Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 15:06:48  packel
	Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2004/04/02 19:47:43  mimno
added line 1 cards

Revision 1.7  2003/07/01 22:18:58  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.6  2002/01/15 19:49:02  amahoney
ocr error -- UIysses for Ulysses

Revision 1.5  2001/03/14 19:17:27  lcerrato
changed typo Glaucus, to Glaucus'

Revision 1.4  2000/03/04 20:35:30  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.3  1999/08/12 17:24:51  dasmith
Changed line tags to handle verse translation.

Revision 1.2  1999/08/04 23:27:56  textgod
Turned line milestones into cards.

Revision 1.1  1997/09/24 20:16:59  textgod
Changed names and redid headers.

</item></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

<text><body>
<div1 type="Book" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card" />
<l n="tr">Arms and the man I sing, who first made way,</l>
<l n="tr">predestined exile, from the Trojan shore</l>
<l n="tr">to <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, the blest Lavinian strand.</l>
<l n="tr">Smitten of storms he was on land and sea</l>
<l n="tr">by violence of Heaven, to satisfy</l>
<l n="tr">stern Juno's sleepless wrath; and much in war</l>
<l n="tr">he suffered, seeking at the last to found </l>
<l n="tr">the city, and bring o'er his fathers' gods</l>
<l n="tr">to safe abode in <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName>; whence arose</l>
<l n="tr">the Latin race, old Alba's reverend lords,</l>
<l n="tr">and from her hills wide-walled, imperial <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="8" unit="card" />O Muse, the causes tell! What sacrilege,</l>
<l n="tr">or vengeful sorrow, moved the heavenly Queen</l>
<l n="tr">to thrust on dangers dark and endless toil</l>
<l n="tr">a man whose largest honor in men's eyes</l>
<l n="tr">was serving Heaven? Can gods such anger feel?</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="12" unit="card" />In ages gone an ancient city stood—</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, a Tyrian seat, which from afar</l>
<l n="tr">made front on <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> and on the mouths</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s stream; its wealth and revenues</l>
<l n="tr">were vast, and ruthless was its quest of war.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is said that Juno, of all lands she loved,</l>
<l n="tr">most cherished this,—not <placeName key="tgn,7002673" authname="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>' self so dear.</l>
<l n="tr">Here were her arms, her chariot; even then</l>
<l n="tr">a throne of power o'er nations near and far,</l>
<l n="tr">if Fate opposed not, 't was her darling hope</l>
<l n="tr">to 'stablish here; but anxiously she heard</l>
<l n="tr">that of the Trojan blood there was a breed</l>
<l n="tr">then rising, which upon the destined day</l>
<l n="tr">should utterly o'erwhelm her Tyrian towers,</l>
<l n="tr">a people of wide sway and conquest proud</l>
<l n="tr">should compass <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>'s doom;—such was the web</l>
<l n="tr">the Fatal Sisters spun. Such was the fear</l>
<l n="tr">of Saturn's daughter, who remembered well</l>
<l n="tr">what long and unavailing strife she waged</l>
<l n="tr">for her loved Greeks at <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. Nor did she fail</l>
<l n="tr">to meditate th' occasions of her rage,</l>
<l n="tr">and cherish deep within her bosom proud</l>
<l n="tr">its griefs and wrongs: the choice by <persName>Paris</persName> made;</l>
<l n="tr">her scorned and slighted beauty; a whole race</l>
<l n="tr">rebellious to her godhead; and Jove's smile</l>
<l n="tr">that beamed on eagle-ravished Ganymede.</l>
<l n="tr">With all these thoughts infuriate, her power</l>
<l n="tr">pursued with tempests o'er the boundless main</l>
<l n="tr">the Trojans, though by Grecian victor spared</l>
<l n="tr">and fierce Achilles; so she thrust them far</l>
<l n="tr">from <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName>; and they drifted, Heaven-impelled,</l>
<l n="tr">year after year, o'er many an unknown sea—</l>
<l n="tr">O labor vast, to found the Roman line!</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="34" unit="card" />Below th' horizon the Sicilian isle</l>
<l n="tr">just sank from view, as for the open sea</l>
<l n="tr">with heart of hope they sailed, and every ship</l>
<l n="tr">clove with its brazen beak the salt, white waves.</l>
<l n="tr">But Juno of her everlasting wound</l>
<l n="tr">knew no surcease, but from her heart of pain</l>
<l n="tr">thus darkly mused: “Must I, defeated, fail</l>
<l n="tr">of what I will, nor turn the Teucrian King</l>
<l n="tr">from <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> away? Can Fate oppose?</l>
<l n="tr">Had Pallas power to lay waste in flame</l>
<l n="tr">the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> fleet and sink its mariners,</l>
<l n="tr">revenging but the sacrilege obscene</l>
<l n="tr">by Ajax wrought, Oileus' desperate son?</l>
<l n="tr">She, from the clouds, herself Jove's lightning threw,</l>
<l n="tr">scattered the ships, and ploughed the sea with storms.</l>
<l n="tr">Her foe, from his pierced breast out-breathing fire,</l>
<l n="tr">in whirlwind on a deadly rock she flung.</l>
<l n="tr">But I, who move among the gods a queen,</l>
<l n="tr">Jove's sister and his spouse, with one weak tribe</l>
<l n="tr">make war so long! Who now on Juno calls?</l>
<l n="tr">What suppliant gifts henceforth her altars crown?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="50" unit="card" />So, in her fevered heart complaining still,</l>
<l n="tr">unto the storm-cloud land the goddess came,</l>
<l n="tr">a region with wild whirlwinds in its womb,</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,5004216" authname="tgn,5004216">Aeolia</placeName> named, where royal Aeolus</l>
<l n="tr">in a high-vaulted cavern keeps control</l>
<l n="tr">o'er warring winds and loud concourse of storms.</l>
<l n="tr">There closely pent in chains and bastions strong,</l>
<l n="tr">they, scornful, make the vacant mountain roar,</l>
<l n="tr">chafing against their bonds. But from a throne</l>
<l n="tr">of lofty crag, their king with sceptred hand</l>
<l n="tr">allays their fury and their rage confines.</l>
<l n="tr">Did he not so, our ocean, earth, and sky</l>
<l n="tr">were whirled before them through the vast inane.</l>
<l n="tr">But over-ruling Jove, of this in fear,</l>
<l n="tr">hid them in dungeon dark: then o'er them piled</l>
<l n="tr">huge mountains, and ordained a lawful king</l>
<l n="tr">to hold them in firm sway, or know what time,</l>
<l n="tr">with Jove's consent, to loose them o'er the world.</l>
<l n="tr">To him proud Juno thus made lowly plea:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="65" unit="card" />“Thou in whose hands the Father of all gods</l>
<l n="tr">and Sovereign of mankind confides the power</l>
<l n="tr">to calm the waters or with winds upturn,</l>
<l n="tr">great Aeolus! a race with me at war</l>
<l n="tr">now sails the Tuscan main towards <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">bringing their <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> and its vanquished powers.</l>
<l n="tr">Uprouse thy gales. Strike that proud navy down!</l>
<l n="tr">Hurl far and wide, and strew the waves with dead!</l>
<l n="tr">Twice seven nymphs are mine, of rarest mould;</l>
<l n="tr">of whom Deiopea, the most fair,</l>
<l n="tr">I give thee in true wedlock for thine own,</l>
<l n="tr">to mate thy noble worth; she at thy side</l>
<l n="tr">shall pass long, happy years, and fruitful bring</l>
<l n="tr">her beauteous offspring unto thee their sire.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="76" unit="card" />Then Aeolus: “'T is thy sole task, O Queen,</l>
<l n="tr">to weigh thy wish and will. My fealty</l>
<l n="tr">thy high behest obeys. This humble throne</l>
<l n="tr">is of thy gift. Thy smiles for me obtain</l>
<l n="tr">authority from Jove. Thy grace concedes</l>
<l n="tr">my station at your bright Olympian board,</l>
<l n="tr">and gives me lordship of the darkening storm.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="81" unit="card" />Replying thus, he smote with spear reversed</l>
<l n="tr">the hollow mountain's wall; then rush the winds</l>
<l n="tr">through that wide breach in long, embattled line,</l>
<l n="tr">and sweep tumultuous from land to land:</l>
<l n="tr">with brooding pinions o'er the waters spread,</l>
<l n="tr">east wind and south, and boisterous Afric gale</l>
<l n="tr">upturn the sea; vast billows shoreward roll;</l>
<l n="tr">the shout of mariners, the creak of cordage,</l>
<l n="tr">follow the shock; low-hanging clouds conceal</l>
<l n="tr">from Trojan eyes all sight of heaven and day;</l>
<l n="tr">night o'er the ocean broods; from sky to sky</l>
<l n="tr">the thunders roll, the ceaseless lightnings glare;</l>
<l n="tr">and all things mean swift death for mortal man.</l>
<l n="tr">Straightway Aeneas, shuddering with amaze,</l>
<l n="tr">groaned loud, upraised both holy hands to Heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">and thus did plead: “O thrice and four times blest,</l>
<l n="tr">ye whom your sires and whom the walls of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">looked on in your last hour! O bravest son</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> ever bore, Tydides! O that I</l>
<l n="tr">had fallen on Ilian fields, and given this life</l>
<l n="tr">struck down by thy strong hand! where by the spear</l>
<l n="tr">of great Achilles, fiery Hector fell,</l>
<l n="tr">and huge Sarpedon; where the Simois</l>
<l n="tr">in furious flood engulfed and whirled away</l>
<l n="tr">so many helms and shields and heroes slain!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="102" unit="card" />While thus he cried to Heaven, a shrieking blast</l>
<l n="tr">smote full upon the sail. Up surged the waves</l>
<l n="tr">to strike the very stars; in fragments flew</l>
<l n="tr">the shattered oars; the helpless vessel veered</l>
<l n="tr">and gave her broadside to the roaring flood,</l>
<l n="tr">where watery mountains rose and burst and fell.</l>
<l n="tr">Now high in air she hangs, then yawning gulfs</l>
<l n="tr">lay bare the shoals and sands o'er which she drives.</l>
<l n="tr">Three ships a whirling south wind snatched and flung</l>
<l n="tr">on hidden rocks,—altars of sacrifice</l>
<l n="tr">Italians call them, which lie far from shore</l>
<l n="tr">a vast ridge in the sea; three ships beside</l>
<l n="tr">an east wind, blowing landward from the deep,</l>
<l n="tr">drove on the shallows,—pitiable sight,—</l>
<l n="tr">and girdled them in walls of drifting sand.</l>
<l n="tr">That ship, which, with his friend Orontes, bore</l>
<l n="tr">the Lycian mariners, a great, plunging wave</l>
<l n="tr">struck straight astern, before Aeneas' eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">Forward the steersman rolled and o'er the side</l>
<l n="tr">fell headlong, while three times the circling flood</l>
<l n="tr">spun the light bark through swift engulfing seas.</l>
<l n="tr">Look, how the lonely swimmers breast the wave!</l>
<l n="tr">And on the waste of waters wide are seen</l>
<l n="tr">weapons of war, spars, planks, and treasures rare,</l>
<l n="tr">once <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s boast, all mingled with the storm.</l>
<l n="tr">Now o'er Achates and Ilioneus,</l>
<l n="tr">now o'er the ship of Abas or Aletes,</l>
<l n="tr">bursts the tempestuous shock; their loosened seams</l>
<l n="tr">yawn wide and yield the angry wave its will.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="124" unit="card" />Meanwhile how all his smitten ocean moaned,</l>
<l n="tr">and how the tempest's turbulent assault</l>
<l n="tr">had vexed the stillness of his deepest cave,</l>
<l n="tr">great Neptune knew; and with indignant mien</l>
<l n="tr">uplifted o'er the sea his sovereign brow.</l>
<l n="tr">He saw the Teucrian navy scattered far</l>
<l n="tr">along the waters; and Aeneas' men</l>
<l n="tr">o'erwhelmed in mingling shock of wave and sky.</l>
<l n="tr">Saturnian Juno's vengeful stratagem</l>
<l n="tr">her brother's royal glance failed not to see;</l>
<l n="tr">and loud to eastward and to westward calling,</l>
<l n="tr">he voiced this word:<milestone ed="p" n="132" unit="card" />“What pride of birth or power</l>
<l n="tr">is yours, ye winds, that, reckless of my will,</l>
<l n="tr">audacious thus, ye ride through earth and heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">and stir these mountain waves? Such rebels I—</l>
<l n="tr">nay, first I calm this tumult! But yourselves</l>
<l n="tr">by heavier chastisement shall expiate</l>
<l n="tr">hereafter your bold trespass. Haste away</l>
<l n="tr">and bear your king this word! Not unto him</l>
<l n="tr">dominion o'er the seas and trident dread,</l>
<l n="tr">but unto me, Fate gives. Let him possess</l>
<l n="tr">wild mountain crags, thy favored haunt and home,</l>
<l n="tr">O Eurus! In his barbarous mansion there,</l>
<l n="tr">let Aeolus look proud, and play the king</l>
<l n="tr">in yon close-bounded prison-house of storms!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="142" unit="card" />He spoke, and swiftlier than his word subdued</l>
<l n="tr">the swelling of the floods; dispersed afar</l>
<l n="tr">th' assembled clouds, and brought back light to heaven.</l>
<l n="tr">Cymothoe then and Triton, with huge toil,</l>
<l n="tr">thrust down the vessels from the sharp-edged reef;</l>
<l n="tr">while, with the trident, the great god's own hand</l>
<l n="tr">assists the task; then, from the sand-strewn shore</l>
<l n="tr">out-ebbing far, he calms the whole wide sea,</l>
<l n="tr">and glides light-wheeled along the crested foam.</l>
<l n="tr">As when, with not unwonted tumult, roars</l>
<l n="tr">in some vast city a rebellious mob,</l>
<l n="tr">and base-born passions in its bosom burn,</l>
<l n="tr">till rocks and blazing torches fill the air</l>
<l n="tr">(rage never lacks for arms)—if haply then</l>
<l n="tr">some wise man comes, whose reverend looks attest</l>
<l n="tr">a life to duty given, swift silence falls;</l>
<l n="tr">all ears are turned attentive; and he sways</l>
<l n="tr">with clear and soothing speech the people's will.</l>
<l n="tr">So ceased the sea's uproar, when its grave Sire</l>
<l n="tr">looked o'er th' expanse, and, riding on in light,</l>
<l n="tr">flung free rein to his winged obedient car.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="157" unit="card" />Aeneas' wave-worn crew now landward made,</l>
<l n="tr">and took the nearest passage, whither lay</l>
<l n="tr">the coast of <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>. A haven there</l>
<l n="tr">walled in by bold sides of a rocky isle,</l>
<l n="tr">offers a spacious and secure retreat,</l>
<l n="tr">where every billow from the distant main</l>
<l n="tr">breaks, and in many a rippling curve retires.</l>
<l n="tr">Huge crags and two confronted promontories</l>
<l n="tr">frown heaven-high, beneath whose brows outspread</l>
<l n="tr">the silent, sheltered waters; on the heights</l>
<l n="tr">the bright and glimmering foliage seems to show</l>
<l n="tr">a woodland amphitheatre; and yet higher</l>
<l n="tr">rises a straight-stemmed grove of dense, dark shade.</l>
<l n="tr">Fronting on these a grotto may be seen,</l>
<l n="tr">o'erhung by steep cliffs; from its inmost wall</l>
<l n="tr">clear springs gush out; and shelving seats it has</l>
<l n="tr">of unhewn stone, a place the wood-nymphs love.</l>
<l n="tr">In such a port, a weary ship rides free</l>
<l n="tr">of weight of firm-fluked anchor or strong chain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="180" unit="card" />Hither Aeneas of his scattered fleet</l>
<l n="tr">saving but seven, into harbor sailed;</l>
<l n="tr">with passionate longing for the touch of land,</l>
<l n="tr">forth leap the Trojans to the welcome shore,</l>
<l n="tr">and fling their dripping limbs along the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Then good Achates smote a flinty stone,</l>
<l n="tr">secured a flashing spark, heaped on light leaves,</l>
<l n="tr">and with dry branches nursed the mounting flame.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Ceres' gift from the corrupting sea</l>
<l n="tr">they bring away; and wearied utterly</l>
<l n="tr">ply Ceres' cunning on the rescued corn,</l>
<l n="tr">and parch in flames, and mill 'twixt two smooth stones.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas meanwhile climbed the cliffs, and searched</l>
<l n="tr">the wide sea-prospect; haply Antheus there,</l>
<l n="tr">storm-buffeted, might sail within his ken,</l>
<l n="tr">with biremes, and his Phrygian mariners,</l>
<l n="tr">or Capys or <placeName key="tgn,1121615" authname="tgn,1121615">Caicus</placeName> armor-clad,</l>
<l n="tr">upon a towering deck. No ship is seen;</l>
<l n="tr">but while he looks, three stags along the shore</l>
<l n="tr">come straying by, and close behind them comes</l>
<l n="tr">the whole herd, browsing through the lowland vale</l>
<l n="tr">in one long line. Aeneas stopped and seized</l>
<l n="tr">his bow and swift-winged arrows, which his friend,</l>
<l n="tr">trusty Achates, close beside him bore.</l>
<l n="tr">His first shafts brought to earth the lordly heads</l>
<l n="tr">of the high-antlered chiefs; his next assailed</l>
<l n="tr">the general herd, and drove them one and all</l>
<l n="tr">in panic through the leafy wood, nor ceased</l>
<l n="tr">the victory of his bow, till on the ground</l>
<l n="tr">lay seven huge forms, one gift for every ship.</l>
<l n="tr">Then back to shore he sped, and to his friends</l>
<l n="tr">distributed the spoil, with that rare wine</l>
<l n="tr">which good Acestes while in <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">had stored in jars, and prince-like sent away</l>
<l n="tr">with his Ioved guest;—this too Aeneas gave;</l>
<l n="tr">and with these words their mournful mood consoled.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="198" unit="card" />“Companions mine, we have not failed to feel</l>
<l n="tr">calamity till now. O, ye have borne</l>
<l n="tr">far heavier sorrow: Jove will make an end</l>
<l n="tr">also of this. Ye sailed a course hard by</l>
<l n="tr">infuriate Scylla's howling cliffs and caves.</l>
<l n="tr">Ye knew the Cyclops' crags. Lift up your hearts!</l>
<l n="tr">No more complaint and fear! It well may be</l>
<l n="tr">some happier hour will find this memory fair.</l>
<l n="tr">Through chance and change and hazard without end,</l>
<l n="tr">our goal is <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName>; where our destinies</l>
<l n="tr">beckon to blest abodes, and have ordained</l>
<l n="tr">that <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> shall rise new-born! Have patience all!</l>
<l n="tr">And bide expectantly that golden day.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="208" unit="card" />Such was his word, but vexed with grief and care,</l>
<l n="tr">feigned hopes upon his forehead firm he wore,</l>
<l n="tr">and locked within his heart a hero's pain.</l>
<l n="tr">Now round the welcome trophies of his chase</l>
<l n="tr">they gather for a feast. Some flay the ribs</l>
<l n="tr">and bare the flesh below; some slice with knives,</l>
<l n="tr">and on keen prongs the quivering strips impale,</l>
<l n="tr">place cauldrons on the shore, and fan the fires.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, stretched at ease on couch of simple green,</l>
<l n="tr">they rally their lost powers, and feast them well</l>
<l n="tr">on seasoned wine and succulent haunch of game.</l>
<l n="tr">But hunger banished and the banquet done,</l>
<l n="tr">in long discourse of their lost mates they tell,</l>
<l n="tr">'twixt hopes and fears divided; for who knows</l>
<l n="tr">whether the lost ones live, or strive with death,</l>
<l n="tr">or heed no more whatever voice may call?</l>
<l n="tr">Chiefly Aeneas now bewails his friends,</l>
<l n="tr">Orontes brave and fallen Amycus,</l>
<l n="tr">or mourns with grief untold the untimely doom</l>
<l n="tr">of bold young Gyas and Cloanthus bold.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="223" unit="card" />After these things were past, exalted Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">from his ethereal sky surveying clear</l>
<l n="tr">the seas all winged with sails, lands widely spread,</l>
<l n="tr">and nations populous from shore to shore,</l>
<l n="tr">paused on the peak of heaven, and fixed his gaze</l>
<l n="tr">on <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>. But while he anxious mused,</l>
<l n="tr">near him, her radiant eyes all dim with tears,</l>
<l n="tr">nor smiling any more, Venus approached,</l>
<l n="tr">and thus complained: “O thou who dost control</l>
<l n="tr">things human and divine by changeless laws,</l>
<l n="tr">enthroned in awful thunder! What huge wrong</l>
<l n="tr">could my Aeneas and his Trojans few</l>
<l n="tr">achieve against thy power? For they have borne</l>
<l n="tr">unnumbered deaths, and, failing <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">the gates of all the world against them close.</l>
<l n="tr">Hast thou not given us thy covenant</l>
<l n="tr">that hence the Romans when the rolling years</l>
<l n="tr">have come full cycle, shall arise to power</l>
<l n="tr">from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s regenerate seed, and rule supreme</l>
<l n="tr">the unresisted lords of land and sea?</l>
<l n="tr">O Sire, what swerves thy will? How oft have I</l>
<l n="tr">in <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s most lamentable wreck and woe</l>
<l n="tr">consoled my heart with this, and balanced oft</l>
<l n="tr">our destined good against our destined ill!</l>
<l n="tr">But the same stormful fortune still pursues</l>
<l n="tr">my band of heroes on their perilous way.</l>
<l n="tr">When shall these labors cease, O glorious King?</l>
<l n="tr">Antenor, though th' Achaeans pressed him sore,</l>
<l n="tr">found his way forth, and entered unassailed</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,7016683" authname="tgn,7016683">Illyria</placeName>'s haven, and the guarded land</l>
<l n="tr">of the Liburni. Straight up stream he sailed</l>
<l n="tr">where like a swollen sea Timavus pours</l>
<l n="tr">a nine-fold flood from roaring mountain gorge,</l>
<l n="tr">and whelms with voiceful wave the fields below.</l>
<l n="tr">He built <placeName key="perseus,Patavium" authname="perseus,Patavium">Patavium</placeName> there, and fixed abodes</l>
<l n="tr">for <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s far-exiled sons; he gave a name</l>
<l n="tr">to a new land and race; the Trojan arms</l>
<l n="tr">were hung on temple walls; and, to this day,</l>
<l n="tr">lying in perfect peace, the hero sleeps.</l>
<l n="tr">But we of thine own seed, to whom thou dost</l>
<l n="tr">a station in the arch of heaven assign,</l>
<l n="tr">behold our navy vilely wrecked, because</l>
<l n="tr">a single god is angry; we endure</l>
<l n="tr">this treachery and violence, whereby</l>
<l n="tr">wide seas divide us from th' Hesperian shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Is this what piety receives? Or thus</l>
<l n="tr">doth Heaven's decree restore our fallen thrones?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="254" unit="card" />Smiling reply, the Sire of gods and men,</l>
<l n="tr">with such a look as clears the skies of storm</l>
<l n="tr">chastely his daughter kissed, and thus spake on:</l>
<l n="tr">“Let Cytherea cast her fears away!</l>
<l n="tr">Irrevocably blest the fortunes be</l>
<l n="tr">of thee and thine. Nor shalt thou fail to see</l>
<l n="tr">that City, and the proud predestined wall</l>
<l n="tr">encompassing <placeName key="perseus,Lavinium" authname="perseus,Lavinium">Lavinium</placeName>. Thyself</l>
<l n="tr">shall starward to the heights of heaven bear</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas the great-hearted. Nothing swerves</l>
<l n="tr">my will once uttered. Since such carking cares</l>
<l n="tr">consume thee, I this hour speak freely forth,</l>
<l n="tr">and leaf by leaf the book of fate unfold.</l>
<l n="tr">Thy son in <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> shall wage vast war</l>
<l n="tr">and, quell its nations wild; his city-wall</l>
<l n="tr">and sacred laws shall be a mighty bond</l>
<l n="tr">about his gathered people. Summers three</l>
<l n="tr">shall <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> call him king; and three times pass</l>
<l n="tr">the winter o'er Rutulia's vanquished hills.</l>
<l n="tr">His heir, Ascanius, now Iulus called</l>
<l n="tr">(Ilus it was while <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s kingdom stood),</l>
<l n="tr">full thirty months shall reign, then move the throne</l>
<l n="tr">from the Lavinian citadel, and build</l>
<l n="tr">for <placeName key="perseus,Alba Longa" authname="perseus,Alba Longa">Alba Longa</placeName> its well-bastioned wall.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="272" unit="card" />Here three full centuries shall Hector's race</l>
<l n="tr">have kingly power; till a priestess queen,</l>
<l n="tr">by Mars conceiving, her twin offspring bear;</l>
<l n="tr">then Romulus, wolf-nursed and proudly clad</l>
<l n="tr">in tawny wolf-skin mantle, shall receive</l>
<l n="tr">the sceptre of his race. He shall uprear</l>
<l n="tr">and on his Romans his own name bestow.</l>
<l n="tr">To these I give no bounded times or power,</l>
<l n="tr">but empire without end. Yea, even my Queen,</l>
<l n="tr">Juno, who now chastiseth land and sea</l>
<l n="tr">with her dread frown, will find a wiser way,</l>
<l n="tr">and at my sovereign side protect and bless</l>
<l n="tr">the Romans, masters of the whole round world,</l>
<l n="tr">who, clad in peaceful toga, judge mankind.</l>
<l n="tr">Such my decree! In lapse of seasons due,</l>
<l n="tr">the heirs of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s kings shall bind in chains</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>'s glory and Achilles' towers,</l>
<l n="tr">and over prostrate <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> sit supreme.</l>
<l n="tr">Of Trojan stock illustriously sprung,</l>
<l n="tr">lo, Caesar comes! whose power the ocean bounds,</l>
<l n="tr">whose fame, the skies. He shall receive the name</l>
<l n="tr">Iulus nobly bore, great Julius, he.</l>
<l n="tr">Him to the skies, in Orient trophies dress,</l>
<l n="tr">thou shalt with smiles receive; and he, like us,</l>
<l n="tr">shall hear at his own shrines the suppliant vow.</l>
<l n="tr">Then will the world grow mild; the battle-sound</l>
<l n="tr">will be forgot; for olden Honor then,</l>
<l n="tr">with spotless Vesta, and the brothers twain,</l>
<l n="tr">Remus and Romulus, at strife no more,</l>
<l n="tr">will publish sacred laws. The dreadful gates</l>
<l n="tr">whence issueth war, shall with close-jointed steel</l>
<l n="tr">be barred impregnably; and prisoned there</l>
<l n="tr">the heaven-offending Fury, throned on swords,</l>
<l n="tr">and fettered by a hundred brazen chains,</l>
<l n="tr">shall belch vain curses from his lips of gore.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="297" unit="card" />These words he gave, and summoned Maia's son,</l>
<l n="tr">the herald Mercury, who earthward flying,</l>
<l n="tr">should bid the Tyrian realms and new-built towers</l>
<l n="tr">welcome the Trojan waifs; lest Dido, blind</l>
<l n="tr">to Fate's decree, should thrust them from the land.</l>
<l n="tr">He takes his flight, with rhythmic stroke of wing,</l>
<l n="tr">across th' abyss of air, and soon draws near</l>
<l n="tr">unto the Libyan mainland. He fulfils</l>
<l n="tr">his heavenly task; the Punic hearts of stone</l>
<l n="tr">grow soft beneath the effluence divine;</l>
<l n="tr">and, most of all, the Queen, with heart at ease</l>
<l n="tr">awaits benignantly her guests from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="305" unit="card" />But good Aeneas, pondering all night long</l>
<l n="tr">his many cares, when first the cheerful dawn</l>
<l n="tr">upon him broke, resolved to take survey</l>
<l n="tr">of this strange country whither wind and wave</l>
<l n="tr">had driven him,—for desert land it seemed,—</l>
<l n="tr">to learn what tribes of man or beast possess</l>
<l n="tr">a place so wild, and careful tidings bring</l>
<l n="tr">back to his friends. His fleet of ships the while,</l>
<l n="tr">where dense, dark groves o'er-arch a hollowed crag,</l>
<l n="tr">he left encircled in far-branching shade.</l>
<l n="tr">Then with no followers save his trusty friend</l>
<l n="tr">Achates, he went forth upon his way,</l>
<l n="tr">two broad-tipped javelins poising in his hand.</l>
<l n="tr">Deep to the midmost wood he went, and there</l>
<l n="tr">his Mother in his path uprose; she seemed</l>
<l n="tr">in garb and countenance a maid, and bore,</l>
<l n="tr">like Spartan maids, a weapon; in such guise</l>
<l n="tr">Harpalyce the Thracian urges on</l>
<l n="tr">her panting coursers and in wild career</l>
<l n="tr">outstrips impetuous <placeName key="tgn,7002660" authname="tgn,7002660">Hebrus</placeName> as it flows.</l>
<l n="tr">Over her lovely shoulders was a bow,</l>
<l n="tr">slender and light, as fits a huntress fair;</l>
<l n="tr">her golden tresses without wimple moved</l>
<l n="tr">in every wind, and girded in a knot</l>
<l n="tr">her undulant vesture bared her marble knees.</l>
<l n="tr">She hailed them thus: “Ho, sirs, I pray you tell</l>
<l n="tr">if haply ye have noted, as ye came,</l>
<l n="tr">one of my sisters in this wood astray?</l>
<l n="tr">She bore a quiver, and a lynx's hide</l>
<l n="tr">her spotted mantle was; perchance she roused</l>
<l n="tr">some foaming boar, and chased with loud halloo.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="325" unit="card" />So Venus spoke, and Venus' son replied:</l>
<l n="tr">“No voice or vision of thy sister fair</l>
<l n="tr">has crossed my path, thou maid without a name!</l>
<l n="tr">Thy beauty seems not of terrestrial mould,</l>
<l n="tr">nor is thy music mortal! Tell me, goddess,</l>
<l n="tr">art thou bright Phoebus' sister? Or some nymph,</l>
<l n="tr">the daughter of a god? Whate'er thou art,</l>
<l n="tr">thy favor we implore, and potent aid</l>
<l n="tr">in our vast toil. Instruct us of what skies,</l>
<l n="tr">or what world's end, our storm-swept lives have found!</l>
<l n="tr">Strange are these lands and people where we rove,</l>
<l n="tr">compelled by wind and wave. Lo, this right hand</l>
<l n="tr">shall many a victim on thine altar slay!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="335" unit="card" />Then Venus: “Nay, I boast not to receive</l>
<l n="tr">honors divine. We Tyrian virgins oft</l>
<l n="tr">bear bow and quiver, and our ankles white</l>
<l n="tr">lace up in purple buskin. Yonder lies</l>
<l n="tr">the Punic power, where Tyrian masters hold</l>
<l n="tr">Agenor's town; but on its borders dwell</l>
<l n="tr">the Libyans, by battles unsubdued.</l>
<l n="tr">Upon the throne is Dido, exiled there</l>
<l n="tr">from <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, to flee th' unnatural enmity</l>
<l n="tr">of her own brother. 'T was an ancient wrong;</l>
<l n="tr">too Iong the dark and tangled tale would be;</l>
<l n="tr">I trace the larger outline of her story:</l>
<l n="tr">Sichreus was her spouse, whose acres broad</l>
<l n="tr">no Tyrian lord could match, and he was-blessed</l>
<l n="tr">by his ill-fated lady's fondest love,</l>
<l n="tr">whose father gave him her first virgin bloom</l>
<l n="tr">in youthful marriage. But the kingly power</l>
<l n="tr">among the Tyrians to her brother came,</l>
<l n="tr">Pygmalion, none deeper dyed in crime</l>
<l n="tr">in all that land. Betwixt these twain there rose</l>
<l n="tr">a deadly hatred,—and the impious wretch,</l>
<l n="tr">blinded by greed, and reckless utterly</l>
<l n="tr">of his fond sister's joy, did murder foul</l>
<l n="tr">upon defenceless and unarmed Sichaeus,</l>
<l n="tr">and at the very altar hewed him down.</l>
<l n="tr">Long did he hide the deed, and guilefully</l>
<l n="tr">deceived with false hopes, and empty words,</l>
<l n="tr">her grief and stricken love. But as she slept,</l>
<l n="tr">her husband's tombless ghost before her came,</l>
<l n="tr">with face all wondrous pale, and he laid bare</l>
<l n="tr">his heart with dagger pierced, disclosing so</l>
<l n="tr">the blood-stained altar and the infamy</l>
<l n="tr">that darkened now their house. His counsel was</l>
<l n="tr">to fly, self-banished, from her ruined land,</l>
<l n="tr">and for her journey's aid, he whispered where</l>
<l n="tr">his buried treasure lay, a weight unknown</l>
<l n="tr">of silver and of gold. Thus onward urged,</l>
<l n="tr">Dido, assembling her few trusted friends,</l>
<l n="tr">prepared her flight. There rallied to her cause</l>
<l n="tr">all who did hate and scorn the tyrant king,</l>
<l n="tr">or feared his cruelty. They seized his ships,</l>
<l n="tr">which haply rode at anchor in the bay,</l>
<l n="tr">and loaded them with gold; the hoarded wealth</l>
<l n="tr">of vile and covetous Pygmalion</l>
<l n="tr">they took to sea. A woman wrought this deed.</l>
<l n="tr">Then came they to these lands where now thine eyes</l>
<l n="tr">behold yon walls and yonder citadel</l>
<l n="tr">of newly rising <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>. For a price</l>
<l n="tr">they measured round so much of Afric soil</l>
<l n="tr">as one bull's hide encircles, and the spot</l>
<l n="tr">received its name, the Byrsa. But, I pray,</l>
<l n="tr">what men are ye? from what far land arrived,</l>
<l n="tr">and whither going?” When she questioned thus,</l>
<l n="tr">her son, with sighs that rose from his heart's depths,</l>
<l n="tr">this answer gave: </l><l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="372" unit="card" />“Divine one, if I tell</l>
<l n="tr">my woes and burdens all, and thou could'st pause</l>
<l n="tr">to heed the tale, first would the vesper star</l>
<l n="tr">th' Olympian portals close, and bid the day</l>
<l n="tr">in slumber lie. Of ancient <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> are we—</l>
<l n="tr">if aught of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> thou knowest! As we roved</l>
<l n="tr">from sea to sea, the hazard of the storm</l>
<l n="tr">cast us up hither on this Libyan coast.</l>
<l n="tr">I am Aeneas, faithful evermore</l>
<l n="tr">to Heaven's command; and in my ships I bear</l>
<l n="tr">my gods ancestral, which I snatched away</l>
<l n="tr">from peril of the foe. My fame is known</l>
<l n="tr">above the stars. I travel on in quest</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, my true home-land, and I</l>
<l n="tr">from Jove himself may trace my birth divine.</l>
<l n="tr">With twice ten ships upon the Phryglan main</l>
<l n="tr">I launched away. My mother from the skies</l>
<l n="tr">gave guidance, and I wrought what Fate ordained.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet now scarce seven shattered ships survive</l>
<l n="tr">the shock of wind and wave; and I myself</l>
<l n="tr">friendless, bereft, am wandering up and down</l>
<l n="tr">this Libyan wilderness! Behold me here,</l>
<l n="tr">from <placeName key="tgn,1000003" authname="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and from <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> exiled still!”</l>
<l n="tr">But Venus could not let him longer plain,</l>
<l n="tr">and stopped his grief midway: </l><l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="387" unit="card" />“Whoe'er thou art,</l>
<l n="tr">I deem that not unblest of heavenly powers,</l>
<l n="tr">with vital breath still thine, thou comest hither</l>
<l n="tr">unto our Tyrian town. Go steadfast on,</l>
<l n="tr">and to the royal threshold make thy way!</l>
<l n="tr">I bring thee tidings that thy comrades all</l>
<l n="tr">are safe at land; and all thy ships, conveyed</l>
<l n="tr">by favoring breezes, safe at anchor lie;</l>
<l n="tr">or else in vain my parents gave me skill</l>
<l n="tr">to read the skies. Look up at yonder swans!</l>
<l n="tr">A flock of twelve, whose gayly fluttering file,</l>
<l n="tr">erst scattered by Jove's eagle swooping down</l>
<l n="tr">from his ethereal haunt, now form anew</l>
<l n="tr">their long-drawn line, and make a landing-place,</l>
<l n="tr">or, hovering over, scan some chosen ground,</l>
<l n="tr">or soaring high, with whir of happy wings,</l>
<l n="tr">re-circle heaven in triumphant song:</l>
<l n="tr">likewise, I tell thee, thy Iost mariners</l>
<l n="tr">are landed, or fly landward at full sail.</l>
<l n="tr">Up, then! let yon plain path thy guidance be,”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="402" unit="card" />She ceased and turned away. A roseate beam</l>
<l n="tr">from her bright shoulder glowed; th' ambrosial hair</l>
<l n="tr">breathed more than mortal sweetness, while her robes</l>
<l n="tr">fell rippling to her feet. Each step revealed</l>
<l n="tr">the veritable goddess. Now he knew</l>
<l n="tr">that vision was his mother, and his words</l>
<l n="tr">pursued the fading phantom as it fled:</l>
<l n="tr">“Why is thy son deluded o'er and o'er</l>
<l n="tr">with mocking dreams,—another cruel god?</l>
<l n="tr">Hast thou no hand-clasp true, nor interchange</l>
<l n="tr">of words unfeigned betwixt this heart and thine?”</l>
<l n="tr">Such word of blame he spoke, and took his way</l>
<l n="tr">toward the city's rampart. Venus then</l>
<l n="tr">o'erveiled them as they moved in darkened air,—</l>
<l n="tr">a liquid mantle of thick cloud divine,—</l>
<l n="tr">that viewless they might pass, nor would any</l>
<l n="tr">obstruct, delay, or question why they came.</l>
<l n="tr">To <placeName key="tgn,7002373" authname="tgn,7002373">Paphos</placeName> then she soared, her Ioved abode,</l>
<l n="tr">where stands her temple, at whose hundred shrines</l>
<l n="tr">garlands of myrtle and fresh roses breathe,</l>
<l n="tr">and clouds of orient sweetness waft away.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="418" unit="card" />Meanwhile the wanderers swiftly journey on</l>
<l n="tr">along the clear-marked road, and soon they climb</l>
<l n="tr">the brow of a high hill, which close in view</l>
<l n="tr">o'er-towers the city's crown. The vast exploit,</l>
<l n="tr">where lately rose but Afric cabins rude,</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas wondered at: the smooth, wide ways;</l>
<l n="tr">the bastioned gates; the uproar of the throng.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrians toil unwearied; some up-raise</l>
<l n="tr">a wall or citadel, from far below</l>
<l n="tr">lifting the ponderous stone; or with due care</l>
<l n="tr">choose where to build, and close the space around</l>
<l n="tr">with sacred furrow; in their gathering-place</l>
<l n="tr">the people for just governors, just laws,</l>
<l n="tr">and for their reverend senate shout acclaim.</l>
<l n="tr">Some clear the harbor mouth; some deeply lay</l>
<l n="tr">the base of a great theatre, and carve out</l>
<l n="tr">proud columns from the mountain, to adorn</l>
<l n="tr">their rising stage with lofty ornament.</l>
<l n="tr">so busy bees above a field of flowers</l>
<l n="tr">in early summer amid sunbeams toil,</l>
<l n="tr">leading abroad their nation's youthful brood;</l>
<l n="tr">or with the flowing honey storing close</l>
<l n="tr">the pliant cells, until they quite run o'er</l>
<l n="tr">with nectared sweet; while from the entering swarm</l>
<l n="tr">they take their little loads; or lined for war,</l>
<l n="tr">rout the dull drones, and chase them from the hive;</l>
<l n="tr">brisk is the task, and all the honeyed air</l>
<l n="tr">breathes odors of wild thyme. “How blest of Heaven.</l>
<l n="tr">These men that see their promised ramparts rise!”</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas sighed; and swift his glances moved</l>
<l n="tr">from tower to tower; then on his way he fared,</l>
<l n="tr">veiled in the wonder-cloud, whence all unseen</l>
<l n="tr">of human eyes,—O strange the tale and true!—</l>
<l n="tr">he threaded the thronged streets, unmarked, unknown.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="441" unit="card" />Deep in the city's heart there was a grove</l>
<l n="tr">of beauteous shade, where once the Tyrians,</l>
<l n="tr">cast here by stormful waves, delved out of earth</l>
<l n="tr">that portent which Queen Juno bade them find,—</l>
<l n="tr">the head of a proud horse,—that ages long</l>
<l n="tr">their boast might be wealth, luxury and war.</l>
<l n="tr">Upon this spot Sidonian Dido raised</l>
<l n="tr">a spacious fane to Juno, which became</l>
<l n="tr">splendid with gifts, and hallowed far and wide</l>
<l n="tr">for potency divine. Its beams were bronze,</l>
<l n="tr">and on loud hinges swung the brazen doors.</l>
<l n="tr">A rare, new sight this sacred grove did show,</l>
<l n="tr">which calmed Aeneas' fears, and made him bold</l>
<l n="tr">to hope for safety, and with lifted heart</l>
<l n="tr">from his low-fallen fortunes re-aspire.</l>
<l n="tr">For while he waits the advent of the Queen,</l>
<l n="tr">he scans the mighty temple, and admires</l>
<l n="tr">the city's opulent pride, and all the skill</l>
<l n="tr">its rival craftsmen in their work approve.</l>
<l n="tr">Behold! he sees old <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s well-fought fields</l>
<l n="tr">in sequent picture, and those famous wars</l>
<l n="tr">now told upon men's lips the whole world round.</l>
<l n="tr">There Atreus' sons, there kingly Priam moved,</l>
<l n="tr">and fierce Pelides pitiless to both.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas paused, and, weeping, thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">“Alas, Achates, what far region now,</l>
<l n="tr">what land in all the world knows not our pain?</l>
<l n="tr">See, it is Priam! Virtue's wage is given—</l>
<l n="tr">O even here! Here also there be tears</l>
<l n="tr">for what men bear, and mortal creatures feel</l>
<l n="tr">each other's sorrow. Therefore, have no fear!</l>
<l n="tr">This story of our loss forbodes us well.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="464" unit="card" />So saying, he received into his heart</l>
<l n="tr">that visionary scene, profoundly sighed,</l>
<l n="tr">and let his plenteous tears unheeded flow.</l>
<l n="tr">There he beheld the citadel of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">girt with embattled foes; here, Greeks in flight</l>
<l n="tr">some Trojan onset 'scaped; there, Phrygian bands</l>
<l n="tr">before tall-plumed Achilles' chariot sped.</l>
<l n="tr">The snowy tents of Rhesus spread hard by</l>
<l n="tr">(he sees them through his tears), where Diomed</l>
<l n="tr">in night's first watch burst o'er them unawares</l>
<l n="tr">with bloody havoc and a host of deaths;</l>
<l n="tr">then drove his fiery coursers o'er the plain</l>
<l n="tr">before their thirst or hunger could be stayed</l>
<l n="tr">on Trojan corn or <placeName key="perseus,Xanthos" authname="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName>' cooling stream.</l>
<l n="tr">Here too was princely Troilus, despoiled,</l>
<l n="tr">routed and weaponless, O wretched boy!</l>
<l n="tr">Ill-matched against Achilles! His wild steeds</l>
<l n="tr">bear him along, as from his chariot's rear</l>
<l n="tr">he falls far back, but clutches still the rein;</l>
<l n="tr">his hair and shoulders on the ground go trailing,</l>
<l n="tr">and his down-pointing spear-head scrawls the dust.</l>
<l n="tr">Elsewhere, to Pallas' ever-hostile shrine,</l>
<l n="tr">daughters of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>, with unsnooded hair,</l>
<l n="tr">and lifting all in vain her hallowed pall,</l>
<l n="tr">walked suppliant and sad, beating their breasts,</l>
<l n="tr">with outspread palms. But her unswerving eyes</l>
<l n="tr">the goddess fixed on earth, and would not see.</l>
<l n="tr">Achilles round the Trojan rampart thrice</l>
<l n="tr">had dragged the fallen Hector, and for gold</l>
<l n="tr">was making traffic of the lifeless clay.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas groaned aloud, with bursting heart, </l>
<l n="tr">to see the spoils, the car, the very corpse</l>
<l n="tr">of his lost friend,—while Priam for the dead</l>
<l n="tr">stretched forth in piteous prayer his helpless hands.</l>
<l n="tr">There too his own presentment he could see</l>
<l n="tr">surrounded by Greek kings; and there were shown</l>
<l n="tr">hordes from the East, and black-browed Memnon's arms;</l>
<l n="tr">her band of Amazons, with moon-shaped shields,</l>
<l n="tr">Penthesilea led; her martial eye</l>
<l n="tr">flamed on from troop to troop; a belt of gold</l>
<l n="tr">beneath one bare, protruded breast she bound—</l>
<l n="tr">a warrior-virgin braving mail-clad men.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="494" unit="card" />While on such spectacle Aeneas' eyes</l>
<l n="tr">looked wondering, while mute and motionless</l>
<l n="tr">he stood at gaze, Queen Dido to the shrine</l>
<l n="tr">in lovely majesty drew near; a throng</l>
<l n="tr">of youthful followers pressed round her way.</l>
<l n="tr">So by the margin of Eurotas wide</l>
<l n="tr">or o'er the Cynthian steep, Diana leads</l>
<l n="tr">her bright processional; hither and yon</l>
<l n="tr">are visionary legions numberless</l>
<l n="tr">of Oreads; the regnant goddess bears</l>
<l n="tr">a quiver on her shoulders, and is seen</l>
<l n="tr">emerging tallest of her beauteous train;</l>
<l n="tr">while joy unutterable thrills the breast</l>
<l n="tr">of fond Latona: Dido not less fair</l>
<l n="tr">amid her subjects passed, and not less bright</l>
<l n="tr">her glow of gracious joy, while she approved</l>
<l n="tr">her future kingdom's pomp and vast emprise.</l>
<l n="tr">Then at the sacred portal and beneath</l>
<l n="tr">the temple's vaulted dome she took her place,</l>
<l n="tr">encompassed by armed men, and lifted high</l>
<l n="tr">upon a throne; her statutes and decrees</l>
<l n="tr">the people heard, and took what lot or toil</l>
<l n="tr">her sentence, or impartial urn, assigned.</l>
<l n="tr">But, lo! Aeneas sees among the throng</l>
<l n="tr">Antheus, Sergestus, and Cloanthus bold,</l>
<l n="tr">with other Teucrians, whom the black storm flung</l>
<l n="tr">far o'er the deep and drove on alien shores.</l>
<l n="tr">Struck dumb was he, and good Achates too,</l>
<l n="tr">half gladness and half fear. Fain would they fly</l>
<l n="tr">to friendship's fond embrace; but knowing not</l>
<l n="tr">what might befall, their hearts felt doubt and care.</l>
<l n="tr">Therefore they kept the secret, and remained</l>
<l n="tr">forth-peering from the hollow veil of cloud,</l>
<l n="tr">haply to learn what their friends' fate might be,</l>
<l n="tr">or where the fleet was landed, or what aim</l>
<l n="tr">had brought them hither; for a chosen few</l>
<l n="tr">from every ship had come to sue for grace,</l>
<l n="tr">and all the temple with their voices rang.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="520" unit="card" />The doors swung wide; and after access given</l>
<l n="tr">and leave to speak, revered Ilioneus</l>
<l n="tr">with soul serene these lowly words essayed:</l>
<l n="tr">“O Queen, who hast authority of Jove</l>
<l n="tr">to found this rising city, and subdue</l>
<l n="tr">with righteous governance its people proud,</l>
<l n="tr">we wretched Trojans, blown from sea to sea,</l>
<l n="tr">beseech thy mercy; keep the curse of fire</l>
<l n="tr">from our poor ships! We pray thee, do no wrong</l>
<l n="tr">unto a guiltless race. But heed our plea!</l>
<l n="tr">No Libyan hearth shall suffer by our sword,</l>
<l n="tr">nor spoil and plunder to our ships be borne;</l>
<l n="tr">such haughty violence fits not the souls</l>
<l n="tr">of vanquished men. We journey to a land</l>
<l n="tr">named, in Greek syllables, <placeName>Hesperia</placeName>:</l>
<l n="tr">a storied realm, made mighty by great wars</l>
<l n="tr">and wealth of fruitful land; in former days</l>
<l n="tr">Oenotrians had it, and their sons, 't is said,</l>
<l n="tr">have called it <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, a chieftain's name</l>
<l n="tr">to a whole region given. Thitherward</l>
<l n="tr">our ships did fare; but with swift-rising flood</l>
<l n="tr">the stormful season of Orion's star</l>
<l n="tr">drove us on viewless shoals; and angry gales</l>
<l n="tr">dispersed us, smitten by the tumbling surge,</l>
<l n="tr">among innavigable rocks. Behold,</l>
<l n="tr">we few swam hither, waifs upon your shore!</l>
<l n="tr">What race of mortals this? What barbarous land,</l>
<l n="tr">that with inhospitable laws ye thrust</l>
<l n="tr">a stranger from your coasts, and fly to arms,</l>
<l n="tr">nor grant mere foothold on your kingdom's bound?</l>
<l n="tr">If man thou scornest and all mortal power,</l>
<l n="tr">forget not that the gods watch good and ill!</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="544" unit="card" />A king we had; Aeneas,—never man</l>
<l n="tr">in all the world more loyal, just and true,</l>
<l n="tr">nor mightier in arms! If Heaven decree</l>
<l n="tr">his present safety, if he now do breathe</l>
<l n="tr">the air of earth and is not buried low</l>
<l n="tr">among the dreadful shades, then fear not thou!</l>
<l n="tr">For thou wilt never rue that thou wert prompt</l>
<l n="tr">to do us the first kindness. O'er the sea</l>
<l n="tr">in the Sicilian land, are cities proud,</l>
<l n="tr">with martial power, and great Acestes there</l>
<l n="tr">is of our Trojan kin. So grant us here</l>
<l n="tr">to beach our shattered ships along thy shore,</l>
<l n="tr">and from thy forest bring us beam and spar</l>
<l n="tr">to mend our broken oars. Then, if perchance</l>
<l n="tr">we find once more our comrades and our king,</l>
<l n="tr">and forth to <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> once more set sail,</l>
<l n="tr">to <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, our Latin hearth and home,</l>
<l n="tr">we will rejoicing go. But if our weal</l>
<l n="tr">is clean gone by, and thee, blest chief and sire,</l>
<l n="tr">these Libyan waters keep, and if no more</l>
<l n="tr">Iulus bids us hope,—then, at the least,</l>
<l n="tr">to yon Sicilian seas, to friendly lands</l>
<l n="tr">whence hither drifting with the winds we came,</l>
<l n="tr">let us retrace the journey and rejoin</l>
<l n="tr">good King Acestes.” So Ilioneus</l>
<l n="tr">ended his pleading; the Dardanidae</l>
<l n="tr">murmured assent.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="561" unit="card" />Then Dido, briefly and with downcast eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">her answer made: “O Teucrians, have no fear!</l>
<l n="tr">Bid care begone! It was necessity,</l>
<l n="tr">and my young kingdom's weakness, which compelled</l>
<l n="tr">the policy of force, and made me keep</l>
<l n="tr">such vigilant sentry my wide co'ast along.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas and his people, that fair town</l>
<l n="tr">of Troy—who knows them not? The whole world knows</l>
<l n="tr">those valorous chiefs and huge, far-flaming wars.</l>
<l n="tr">Our Punic hearts are not of substance all</l>
<l n="tr">insensible and dull: the god of day</l>
<l n="tr">drives not his fire-breathing steeds so far</l>
<l n="tr">from this our Tyrian town. If ye would go</l>
<l n="tr">to great Hesperia, where Saturn reigned,</l>
<l n="tr">or if voluptuous <placeName key="perseus,Eryx" authname="perseus,Eryx">Eryx</placeName> and the throne</l>
<l n="tr">of good Acestes be your journey's end,</l>
<l n="tr">I send you safe; I speed you on your way.</l>
<l n="tr">But if in these my realms ye will abide,</l>
<l n="tr">associates of my power, behold, I build</l>
<l n="tr">this city for your own! Choose haven here</l>
<l n="tr">for your good ships. Beneath my royal sway</l>
<l n="tr">Trojan and Tyrian equal grace will find.</l>
<l n="tr">But O, that this same storm had brought your King.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas, hither! I will bid explore</l>
<l n="tr">our <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>'s utmost bound, where haply he</l>
<l n="tr">in wilderness or hamlet wanders lost.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="579" unit="card" />By these fair words to joy profoundly stirred,</l>
<l n="tr">Father Aeneas and Achates brave</l>
<l n="tr">to cast aside the cloud that wrapped them round</l>
<l n="tr">yearned greatly; and Achates to his King</l>
<l n="tr">spoke thus: “O goddess-born, in thy wise heart</l>
<l n="tr">what purpose rises now? Lo! All is well!</l>
<l n="tr">Thy fleet and followers are safe at land.</l>
<l n="tr">One only comes not, who before our eyes </l>
<l n="tr">sank in the soundless sea. All else fulfils</l>
<l n="tr">thy mother's prophecy.” Scarce had he spoke</l>
<l n="tr">when suddenly that overmantling cloud</l>
<l n="tr">was cloven, and dissolved in lucent air;</l>
<l n="tr">forth stood Aeneas. A clear sunbeam smote</l>
<l n="tr">his god-like head and shoulders. Venus' son</l>
<l n="tr">of his own heavenly mother now received</l>
<l n="tr">youth's glowing rose, an eye of joyful fire,</l>
<l n="tr">and tresses clustering fair. 'T is even so</l>
<l n="tr">the cunning craftsman unto ivory gives</l>
<l n="tr">new beauty, or with circlet of bright gold</l>
<l n="tr">encloses silver or the Parian stone.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus of the Queen he sued, while wonderment</l>
<l n="tr">fell on all hearts. “Behold the man ye seek,</l>
<l n="tr">for I am here! Aeneas, Trojan-born,</l>
<l n="tr">brought safely hither from yon Libyan seas!</l>
<l n="tr">O thou who first hast looked with pitying eye</l>
<l n="tr">on <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s unutterable grief, who even to us</l>
<l n="tr">(escaped our Grecian victor, and outworn</l>
<l n="tr">by all the perils land and ocean know),</l>
<l n="tr">to us, bereft and ruined, dost extend</l>
<l n="tr">such welcome to thy kingdom and thy home!</l>
<l n="tr">I have no power, Dido, to give thanks</l>
<l n="tr">to match thine ample grace; nor is there power</l>
<l n="tr">in any remnant of our Dardan blood,</l>
<l n="tr">now fled in exile o'er the whole wide world.</l>
<l n="tr">May gods on high (if influence divine</l>
<l n="tr">bless faithful lives, or recompense be found</l>
<l n="tr">in justice and thy self-approving mind)</l>
<l n="tr">give thee thy due reward. What age was blest</l>
<l n="tr">by such a birth as thine? What parents proud</l>
<l n="tr">such offspring bore? O, while the rivers run</l>
<l n="tr">to mingle with the sea, while shadows pass</l>
<l n="tr">along yon rounded hills from vale to vale,</l>
<l n="tr">and while from heaven's unextinguished fire</l>
<l n="tr">the stars be fed—so Iong thy glorious name,</l>
<l n="tr">thy place illustrious and thy virtue's praise,</l>
<l n="tr">abide undimmed.—Yet I myself must go</l>
<l n="tr">to lands I know not where.” After this word</l>
<l n="tr">his right hand clasped his Ioved Ilioneus,</l>
<l n="tr">his left Serestus; then the comrades all,</l>
<l n="tr">brave Gyas, brave Cloanthus, and their peers.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="613" unit="card" />Sidonian Dido felt her heart stand still</l>
<l n="tr">when first she looked on him; and thrilled again</l>
<l n="tr">to hear what vast adventure had befallen</l>
<l n="tr">so great a hero. Thus she welcomed him:</l>
<l n="tr">“What chance, O goddess-born, o'er danger's path</l>
<l n="tr">impels? What power to this wild coast has borne?</l>
<l n="tr">Art thou Aeneas, great Anchises' son,</l>
<l n="tr">whom lovely Venus by the Phrygian stream</l>
<l n="tr">of Simois brought forth unto the day?</l>
<l n="tr">Now I bethink me of when Teucer came</l>
<l n="tr">to <placeName key="tgn,7002861" authname="tgn,7002861">Sidon</placeName>, exiled, and of Belus' power</l>
<l n="tr">desired a second throne. For Belus then,</l>
<l n="tr">our worshipped sire, despoiled the teeming land</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,1000112" authname="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>, as its conqueror and king.</l>
<l n="tr">And since that hour I oft have heard the tale</l>
<l n="tr">of fallen <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, of thine own noble name,</l>
<l n="tr">and of Achaean kings. Teucer was wont,</l>
<l n="tr">although their foe, to praise the Teucrian race,</l>
<l n="tr">and boasted him of that proud lineage sprung.</l>
<l n="tr">Therefore, behold, our portals are swung wide</l>
<l n="tr">for all your company. I also bore</l>
<l n="tr">hard fate like thine. I too was driven of storms</l>
<l n="tr">and after long toil was allowed at last</l>
<l n="tr">to call this land my home. O, I am wise</l>
<l n="tr">in sorrow, and I help all suffering souls!”</l>
<l n="tr">So saying, she bade Aeneas welcome take</l>
<l n="tr">beneath her royal roof, and to the gods</l>
<l n="tr">made sacrifice in temples, while she sent</l>
<l n="tr">unto the thankful Trojans on the shore</l>
<l n="tr">a score of bulls, and of huge, bristling swine,</l>
<l n="tr">a herd of a whole hundred, and a flock</l>
<l n="tr">of goodly lambs, a hundred, who ran close</l>
<l n="tr">beside the mother-ewes: and all were given</l>
<l n="tr">in joyful feast to please the Heavenly Powers.</l>
<l n="tr">Her palace showed a monarch's fair array</l>
<l n="tr">all glittering and proud, and feasts were spread</l>
<l n="tr">within the ample court. Rich broideries</l>
<l n="tr">hung deep incarnadined with Tyrian skill;</l>
<l n="tr">the board had massy silver, gold-embossed,</l>
<l n="tr">where gleamed the mighty deeds of all her sires,</l>
<l n="tr">a graven chronicle of peace and war</l>
<l n="tr">prolonged, since first her ancient line began,</l>
<l n="tr">from royal sire to son. </l><l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="643" unit="card" />Aeneas now</l>
<l n="tr">(for love in his paternal heart spoke loud</l>
<l n="tr">and gave no rest) bade swift Achates run</l>
<l n="tr">to tell Ascanius all, and from the ship</l>
<l n="tr">to guide him upward to the town,—for now</l>
<l n="tr">the father's whole heart for Ascanius yearned.</l>
<l n="tr">And gifts he bade them bring, which had been saved</l>
<l n="tr">in <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s fall: a richly broidered cloak</l>
<l n="tr">heavy with golden emblems; and a veil</l>
<l n="tr">by leaves of saffron lilies bordered round,</l>
<l n="tr">which Argive Helen o'er her beauty threw,</l>
<l n="tr">her mother Leda's gift most wonderful,</l>
<l n="tr">and which to <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> she bore, when flying far</l>
<l n="tr">in lawless wedlock from <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>'s towers;</l>
<l n="tr">a sceptre, too, once fair Ilione's,</l>
<l n="tr">eldest of Priam's daughters; and round pearls</l>
<l n="tr">strung in a necklace, and a double crown</l>
<l n="tr">of jewels set in gold. These gifts to find,</l>
<l n="tr">Achates to the tall ships sped away.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="657" unit="card" />But Cytherea in her heart revolved</l>
<l n="tr">new wiles, new schemes: how Cupid should transform</l>
<l n="tr">his countenance, and, coming in the guise</l>
<l n="tr">of sweet Ascanius, still more inflame</l>
<l n="tr">the amorous Queen with gifts, and deeply fuse</l>
<l n="tr">through all her yielding frame his fatal fire.</l>
<l n="tr">Sooth, Venus feared the many-languaged guile</l>
<l n="tr">which Tyrians use; fierce Juno's hate she feared,</l>
<l n="tr">and falling night renewed her sleepless care.</l>
<l n="tr">Therefore to Love, the light-winged god, she said:</l>
<l n="tr">“Sweet son, of whom my sovereignty and power</l>
<l n="tr">alone are given! O son, whose smile may scorn</l>
<l n="tr">the shafts of Jove whereby the Titans fell,</l>
<l n="tr">to thee I fly, and humbly here implore</l>
<l n="tr">thy help divine. Behold, from land to land</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas, thine own brother, voyages on</l>
<l n="tr">storm-driven, by Juno's causeless enmity.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou knowest it well, and oft hast sighed to see</l>
<l n="tr">my sighs and tears. Dido the Tyrian now</l>
<l n="tr">detains him with soft speeches; and I fear</l>
<l n="tr">such courtesy from Juno means us ill;</l>
<l n="tr">she is not one who, when the hour is ripe,</l>
<l n="tr">bids action pause. I therefore now intend</l>
<l n="tr">the Tyrian Queen to snare, and siege her breast</l>
<l n="tr">with our invading fire, before some god</l>
<l n="tr">shall change her mood. But let her bosom burn</l>
<l n="tr">with love of my Aeneas not less than mine.</l>
<l n="tr">This thou canst bring to pass. I pray thee hear</l>
<l n="tr">the plan I counsel. At his father's call</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius, heir of kings, makes haste to climb</l>
<l n="tr">to yon Sidonian citadel; my grace</l>
<l n="tr">protects him, and he bears gifts which were saved</l>
<l n="tr">from hazard of the sea and burning <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">Him lapped in slumber on <placeName key="tgn,7010869" authname="tgn,7010869">Cythera</placeName>'s hill,</l>
<l n="tr">or in Idalia's deep and hallowing shade,</l>
<l n="tr">myself will hide, lest haply he should learn</l>
<l n="tr">our stratagem, and burst in, foiling all.</l>
<l n="tr">Wear thou his shape for one brief night thyself,</l>
<l n="tr">and let thy boyhood feign another boy's</l>
<l n="tr">familiar countenance; when Dido there,</l>
<l n="tr">beside the royal feast and flowing wine,</l>
<l n="tr">all smiles and joy, shall clasp thee to her breast</l>
<l n="tr">while she caresses thee, and her sweet lips</l>
<l n="tr">touch close with thine, then let thy secret fire</l>
<l n="tr">breathe o'er her heart, to poison and betray.”</l>
<l n="tr">The love-god to his mother's dear behest</l>
<l n="tr">gave prompt assent. He put his pinions by</l>
<l n="tr">and tripped it like Iulus, light of heart.</l>
<l n="tr">But Venus o'er Ascanius' body poured</l>
<l n="tr">a perfect sleep, and, to her heavenly breast</l>
<l n="tr">enfolding him, far, far away upbore</l>
<l n="tr">to fair Idalia's grove, where fragrant buds</l>
<l n="tr">of softly-petalled marjoram embower</l>
<l n="tr">in pleasurable shade. </l><l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="695" unit="card" />Cupid straightway</l>
<l n="tr">obeyed his mother's word and bore the gifts,</l>
<l n="tr">each worthy of a king, as offerings</l>
<l n="tr">to greet the Tyrian throne; and as he went</l>
<l n="tr">he clasped Achates' friendly hand, and smiled.</l>
<l n="tr">Father Aeneas now, and all his band</l>
<l n="tr">of Trojan chivalry, at social feast,</l>
<l n="tr">on lofty purple-pillowed couches lie;</l>
<l n="tr">deft slaves fresh water on their fingers pour,</l>
<l n="tr">and from reed-woven basketry renew</l>
<l n="tr">the plenteous bread, or bring smooth napery</l>
<l n="tr">of softest weave; fifty handmaidens serve,</l>
<l n="tr">whose task it is to range in order fair</l>
<l n="tr">the varied banquet, or at altars bright</l>
<l n="tr">throw balm and incense on the sacred fires.</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred more serve with an equal band</l>
<l n="tr">of beauteous pages, whose obedient skill</l>
<l n="tr">piles high the generous board and fills the bowl.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrians also to the festal hall</l>
<l n="tr">come thronging, and receive their honor due,</l>
<l n="tr">each on his painted couch; with wondering eyes</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas' gifts they view, and wondering more,</l>
<l n="tr">mark young Iulus' radiant brows divine,</l>
<l n="tr">his guileful words, the golden pall he bears,</l>
<l n="tr">and broidered veil with saffron lilies bound.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrian Queen ill-starred, already doomed</l>
<l n="tr">to her approaching woe, scanned ardently,</l>
<l n="tr">with kindling cheek and never-sated eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">the precious gifts and wonder-gifted boy.</l>
<l n="tr">He round Aeneas' neck his arms entwined,</l>
<l n="tr">fed the deep yearning of his seeming sire,</l>
<l n="tr">then sought the Queen's embrace; her eyes, her soul</l>
<l n="tr">clave to him as she strained him to her breast.</l>
<l n="tr">For Dido knew not in that fateful hour</l>
<l n="tr">how great a god betrayed her. He began,</l>
<l n="tr">remembering his mother (she who bore</l>
<l n="tr">the lovely Acidalian Graces three),</l>
<l n="tr">to make the dear name of Sichaeus fade,</l>
<l n="tr">and with new life, new love, to re-possess</l>
<l n="tr">her Iong-since slumbering bosom's Iost desire.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="723" unit="card" />When the main feast is over, they replace</l>
<l n="tr">the banquet with huge bowls, and crown the wine</l>
<l n="tr">with ivy-leaf and rose. Loud rings the roof</l>
<l n="tr">with echoing voices; from the gilded vault</l>
<l n="tr">far-blazing cressets swing, or torches bright</l>
<l n="tr">drive the dark night away. The Queen herself</l>
<l n="tr">called for her golden chalice studded round</l>
<l n="tr">with jewels, and o'er-brimming it with wine</l>
<l n="tr">as Belus and his proud successors use,</l>
<l n="tr">commanded silence, and this utterance made:</l>
<l n="tr">“Great Jove, of whom are hospitable laws</l>
<l n="tr">for stranger-guest, may this auspicious day</l>
<l n="tr">bless both our Tyrians and the wanderers</l>
<l n="tr">from Trojan shore. May our posterity</l>
<l n="tr">keep this remembrance! Let kind Juno smile,</l>
<l n="tr">and Bacchus, Iord of mirth, attend us here!</l>
<l n="tr">And, O ye Tyrians, come one and all,</l>
<l n="tr">and with well-omened words our welcome share!”</l>
<l n="tr">So saying, she outpoured the sacred drop</l>
<l n="tr">due to the gods, and lightly from the rim</l>
<l n="tr">sipped the first taste, then unto Bitias gave</l>
<l n="tr">with urgent cheer; he seized it, nothing loth,</l>
<l n="tr">quaffed deep and long the foaming, golden bowl,</l>
<l n="tr">then passed to others. On a gilded Iyre</l>
<l n="tr">the flowing-haired Iopas woke a song</l>
<l n="tr">taught him by famous Atlas: of the moon</l>
<l n="tr">he sang, the wanderer, and what the sun's</l>
<l n="tr">vast labors be; then would his music tell</l>
<l n="tr">whence man and beast were born, and whence were bred</l>
<l n="tr">clouds, lightnings, and Arcturus' stormful sign,</l>
<l n="tr">the Hyades, rain-stars, and nigh the Pole</l>
<l n="tr">the great and lesser Wain; for well he knew</l>
<l n="tr">why colder suns make haste to quench their orb</l>
<l n="tr">in ocean-stream, and wintry nights be slow.</l>
<l n="tr">Loudly the Tyrians their minstrel praised,</l>
<l n="tr">and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> gave prompt applause. Dido the while</l>
<l n="tr">with varying talk prolonged the fateful night,</l>
<l n="tr">and drank both long and deep of love and wine.</l>
<l n="tr">Now many a tale of Priam would she crave,</l>
<l n="tr">of Hector many; or what radiant arms</l>
<l n="tr">Aurora's son did wear; what were those steeds</l>
<l n="tr">of Diomed, or what the stature seemed</l>
<l n="tr">of great Achilles. “Come, illustrious guest,</l>
<l n="tr">begin the tale,” she said, “begin and tell</l>
<l n="tr">the perfidy of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, thy people's fall,</l>
<l n="tr">and all thy wanderings. For now,—Ah, me!</l>
<l n="tr">Seven times the summer's burning stars have seen</l>
<l n="tr">thee wandering far o'er alien lands and seas.”</l></div1>
<div1 type="Book" n="2" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card" />
<l n="tr">A general silence fell; and all gave ear,</l>
<l n="tr">while, from his lofty station at the feast,</l>
<l n="tr">Father Aeneas with these words began :—</l>
<l n="tr">A grief unspeakable thy gracious word,</l>
<l n="tr">o sovereign lady, bids my heart live o'er:</l>
<l n="tr">how <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>'s glory and afflicted throne</l>
<l n="tr">the Greek flung down; which woeful scene I saw,</l>
<l n="tr">and bore great part in each event I tell.</l>
<l n="tr">But O! in telling, what Dolopian churl,</l>
<l n="tr">or Myrmidon, or gory follower</l>
<l n="tr">of grim Ulysses could the tears restrain?</l>
<l n="tr">'T is evening; lo! the dews of night begin</l>
<l n="tr">to fall from heaven, and yonder sinking stars</l>
<l n="tr">invite to slumber. But if thy heart yearn</l>
<l n="tr">to hear in brief of all our evil days</l>
<l n="tr">and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s last throes, although the memory</l>
<l n="tr">makes my soul shudder and recoil in pain,</l>
<l n="tr">I will essay it. <milestone ed="p" n="13" unit="card" />Wearied of the war,</l>
<l n="tr">and by ill-fortune crushed, year after year,</l>
<l n="tr">the kings of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, by Pallas' skill divine,</l>
<l n="tr">build a huge horse, a thing of mountain size,</l>
<l n="tr">with timbered ribs of fir. They falsely say</l>
<l n="tr">it has been vowed to Heaven for safe return,</l>
<l n="tr">and spread this lie abroad. Then they conceal</l>
<l n="tr">choice bands of warriors in the deep, dark side,</l>
<l n="tr">and fill the caverns of that monstrous womb</l>
<l n="tr">with arms and soldiery. <milestone ed="p" n="21" unit="card" />In sight of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">lies <placeName key="perseus,Tenedos" authname="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName>, an island widely famed</l>
<l n="tr">and opulent, ere Priam's kingdom fell,</l>
<l n="tr">but a poor haven now, with anchorage</l>
<l n="tr">not half secure; 't was thitherward they sailed,</l>
<l n="tr">and lurked unseen by that abandoned shore.</l>
<l n="tr">We deemed them launched away and sailing far,</l>
<l n="tr">bound homeward for <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>. Teucria then</l>
<l n="tr">threw off her grief inveterate; all her gates</l>
<l n="tr">swung wide; exultant went we forth, and saw</l>
<l n="tr">the Dorian camp untenanted, the siege</l>
<l n="tr">abandoned, and the shore without a keel.</l>
<l n="tr">“Here!” cried we, “the Dolopian pitched; the host</l>
<l n="tr">of fierce Achilles here; here lay the fleet;</l>
<l n="tr">and here the battling lines to conflict ran.”</l>
<l n="tr">Others, all wonder, scan the gift of doom</l>
<l n="tr">by virgin Pallas given, and view with awe</l>
<l n="tr">that horse which loomed so large. Thymoetes then</l>
<l n="tr">bade lead it through the gates, and set on high</l>
<l n="tr">within our citadel,—or traitor he,</l>
<l n="tr">or tool of fate in <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s predestined fall.</l>
<l n="tr">But Capys, as did all of wiser heart,</l>
<l n="tr">bade hurl into the sea the false Greek gift,</l>
<l n="tr">or underneath it thrust a kindling flame</l>
<l n="tr">or pierce the hollow ambush of its womb</l>
<l n="tr">with probing spear. Yet did the multitude</l>
<l n="tr">veer round from voice to voice and doubt of all.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="40" unit="card" />Then from the citadel, conspicuous,</l>
<l n="tr">Laocoon, with all his following choir,</l>
<l n="tr">hurried indignant down; and from afar</l>
<l n="tr">thus hailed the people: “O unhappy men!</l>
<l n="tr">What madness this? Who deems our foemen fled?</l>
<l n="tr">Think ye the gifts of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> can lack for guile?</l>
<l n="tr">Have ye not known Ulysses? The Achaean</l>
<l n="tr">hides, caged in yonder beams; or this is reared</l>
<l n="tr">for engin'ry on our proud battlements,</l>
<l n="tr">to spy upon our roof-tops, or descend</l>
<l n="tr">in ruin on the city. 'T is a snare.</l>
<l n="tr">Trust not this horse, O <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, whate'er it bode!</l>
<l n="tr">I fear the Greeks, though gift on gift they bear.”</l>
<l n="tr">So saying, he whirled with ponderous javelin</l>
<l n="tr">a sturdy stroke straight at the rounded side</l>
<l n="tr">of the great, jointed beast. A tremor struck</l>
<l n="tr">its towering form, and through the cavernous womb</l>
<l n="tr">rolled loud, reverberate rumbling, deep and long.</l>
<l n="tr">If heaven's decree, if our own wills, that hour,</l>
<l n="tr">had not been fixed on woe, his spear had brought</l>
<l n="tr">a bloody slaughter on our ambushed foe,</l>
<l n="tr">and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> were standing on the earth this day!</l>
<l n="tr">O Priam's towers, ye were unfallen still!</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="57" unit="card" />But, lo! with hands fast bound behind, a youth</l>
<l n="tr">by clamorous Dardan shepherds haled along,</l>
<l n="tr">was brought before our king,—to this sole end</l>
<l n="tr">a self-surrendered captive, that he might,</l>
<l n="tr">although a nameless stranger, cunningly</l>
<l n="tr">deliver to the Greek the gates of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">His firm-set mind flinched not from either goal,—</l>
<l n="tr">success in crime, or on swift death to fall.</l>
<l n="tr">The thronging Trojan youth made haste his way</l>
<l n="tr">from every side, all eager to see close</l>
<l n="tr">their captive's face, and clout with emulous scorn.</l>
<l n="tr">Hear now what Greek deception is, and learn</l>
<l n="tr">from one dark wickedness the whole. For he,</l>
<l n="tr">a mark for every eye, defenceless, dazed,</l>
<l n="tr">stood staring at our Phrygian hosts, and cried:</l>
<l n="tr">“Woe worth the day! What ocean or what shore</l>
<l n="tr">will have me now? What desperate path remains</l>
<l n="tr">for miserable me? Now have I lost</l>
<l n="tr">all foothold with the Greeks, and o'er my head</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s furious sons call bloody vengeance down.”</l>
<l n="tr">Such groans and anguish turned all rage away</l>
<l n="tr">and stayed our lifted hands. We bade him tell</l>
<l n="tr">his birth, his errand, and from whence might be</l>
<l n="tr">such hope of mercy for a foe in chains.</l>
<l n="tr">Then fearing us no more, this speech he dared:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="77" unit="card" />“O King! I will confess, whate'er befall,</l>
<l n="tr">the whole unvarnished truth. I will not hide</l>
<l n="tr">my Grecian birth. Yea, thus will I begin.</l>
<l n="tr">For Fortune has brought wretched Sinon low;</l>
<l n="tr">but never shall her cruelty impair</l>
<l n="tr">his honor and his truth. Perchance the name</l>
<l n="tr">of Palamedes, Belus' glorious son,</l>
<l n="tr">has come by rumor to your listening ears;</l>
<l n="tr">whom by false witness and conspiracy,</l>
<l n="tr">because his counsel was not for this war,</l>
<l n="tr">the Greeks condemned, though guiltless, to his death,</l>
<l n="tr">and now make much lament for him they slew.</l>
<l n="tr">I, his companion, of his kith and kin,</l>
<l n="tr">sent hither by my humble sire's command,</l>
<l n="tr">followed his arms and fortunes from my youth.</l>
<l n="tr">Long as his throne endured, and while he throve</l>
<l n="tr">in conclave with his kingly peers, we twain</l>
<l n="tr">some name and lustre bore; but afterward,</l>
<l n="tr">because that cheat Ulysses envied him</l>
<l n="tr">(Ye know the deed), he from this world withdrew,</l>
<l n="tr">and I in gloom and tribulation sore</l>
<l n="tr">lived miserably on, lamenting loud</l>
<l n="tr">my lost friend's blameless fall. A fool was I</l>
<l n="tr">that kept not these lips closed; but I had vowed</l>
<l n="tr">that if a conqueror home to <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> I came,</l>
<l n="tr">I would avenge. Such words moved wrath, and were</l>
<l n="tr">the first shock of my ruin; from that hour,</l>
<l n="tr">Ulysses whispered slander and alarm;</l>
<l n="tr">breathed doubt and malice into all men's ears,</l>
<l n="tr">and darkly plotted how to strike his blow.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor rest had he, till Calchas, as his tool,-</l>
<l n="tr">but why unfold this useless, cruel story?</l>
<l n="tr">Why make delay? Ye count all sons of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">arrayed as one; and to have heard thus far</l>
<l n="tr">suffices you. Take now your ripe revenge!</l>
<l n="tr">Ulysses smiles and Atreus' royal sons</l>
<l n="tr">with liberal price your deed of blood repay.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="105" unit="card" />We ply him then with passionate appeal</l>
<l n="tr">and question all his cause: of guilt so dire</l>
<l n="tr">or such Greek guile we harbored not the thought.</l>
<l n="tr">So on he prates, with well-feigned grief and fear,</l>
<l n="tr">and from his Iying heart thus told his tale:</l>
<l n="tr">"Full oft the Greeks had fain achieved their flight,</l>
<l n="tr">and raised the Trojan siege, and sailed away</l>
<l n="tr">war-wearied quite. O, would it had been so!</l>
<l n="tr">Full oft the wintry tumult of the seas</l>
<l n="tr">did wall them round, and many a swollen storm</l>
<l n="tr">their embarcation stayed. But chiefly when,</l>
<l n="tr">all fitly built of beams of maple fair,</l>
<l n="tr">this horse stood forth,— what thunders filled the skies!</l>
<l n="tr">With anxious fears we sent Eurypylus</l>
<l n="tr">to ask Apollo's word; and from the shrine</l>
<l n="tr">he brings the sorrowful commandment home:</l>
<l n="tr">‘By flowing blood and by a virgin slain</l>
<l n="tr">the wild winds were appeased, when first ye came,</l>
<l n="tr">ye sons of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, to <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s distant shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Through blood ye must return. Let some Greek life</l>
<l n="tr">your expiation be.’ The popular ear</l>
<l n="tr">the saying caught, all spirits were dimmed o'er;</l>
<l n="tr">cold doubt and horror through each bosom ran,</l>
<l n="tr">asking what fate would do, and on what wretch</l>
<l n="tr">Apollo's choice would fall. Ulysses, then,</l>
<l n="tr">amid the people's tumult and acclaim,</l>
<l n="tr">thrust Calchas forth, some prophecy to tell</l>
<l n="tr">to all the throng: he asked him o'er and o'er</l>
<l n="tr">what Heaven desired. Already not a few</l>
<l n="tr">foretold the murderous plot, and silently</l>
<l n="tr">watched the dark doom upon my life impend.</l>
<l n="tr">Twice five long days the seer his lips did seal,</l>
<l n="tr">and hid himself, refusing to bring forth</l>
<l n="tr"> His word of guile, and name what wretch should die.</l>
<l n="tr">At last, reluctant, and all loudly urged</l>
<l n="tr"> By false Ulysses, he fulfils their plot,</l>
<l n="tr">and, lifting up his voice oracular,</l>
<l n="tr">points out myself the victim to be slain.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor did one voice oppose. The mortal stroke</l>
<l n="tr">horribly hanging o'er each coward head</l>
<l n="tr">was changed to one man's ruin, and their hearts</l>
<l n="tr">endured it well. Soon rose th' accursed morn;</l>
<l n="tr">the bloody ritual was ready; salt</l>
<l n="tr">was sprinkled on the sacred loaf; my brows</l>
<l n="tr">were bound with fillets for the offering.</l>
<l n="tr">But I escaped that death—yes! I deny not!</l>
<l n="tr">I cast my fetters off, and darkling lay</l>
<l n="tr">concealed all night in lake-side sedge and mire,</l>
<l n="tr">awaiting their departure, if perchance</l>
<l n="tr">they should in truth set sail. But nevermore</l>
<l n="tr">shall my dear, native country greet these eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">No more my father or my tender babes</l>
<l n="tr">shall I behold. Nay, haply their own lives</l>
<l n="tr">are forfeit, when my foemen take revenge</l>
<l n="tr">for my escape, and slay those helpless ones,</l>
<l n="tr">in expiation of my guilty deed.</l>
<l n="tr">O, by yon powers in heaven which witness truth,</l>
<l n="tr">by aught in this dark world remaining now</l>
<l n="tr">of spotless human faith and innocence,</l>
<l n="tr">I do implore thee look with pitying eye</l>
<l n="tr">on these long sufferings my heart hath borne.</l>
<l n="tr">O, pity! I deserve not what I bear.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="145" unit="card" />Pity and pardon to his tears we gave,</l>
<l n="tr">and spared his life. King Priam bade unbind</l>
<l n="tr">the fettered hands and loose those heavy chains</l>
<l n="tr">that pressed him sore; then with benignant mien</l>
<l n="tr">addressed him thus: “ Whate'er thy place or name,</l>
<l n="tr">forget the people thou hast Iost, and be</l>
<l n="tr">henceforth our countryman. But tell me true!</l>
<l n="tr">What means the monstrous fabric of this horse?</l>
<l n="tr">Who made it? Why? What offering to Heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">or engin'ry of conquest may it be?”</l>
<l n="tr">He spake; and in reply, with skilful guile,</l>
<l n="tr">Greek that he was! the other lifted up</l>
<l n="tr">his hands, now freed and chainless, to the skies:</l>
<l n="tr">“O ever-burning and inviolate fires,</l>
<l n="tr">witness my word! O altars and sharp steel,</l>
<l n="tr">whose curse I fled, O fillets of the gods,</l>
<l n="tr">which bound a victim's helpless forehead, hear!</l>
<l n="tr">'T is lawful now to break the oath that gave</l>
<l n="tr">my troth to <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. To execrate her kings</l>
<l n="tr">is now my solemn duty. Their whole plot</l>
<l n="tr">I publish to the world. No fatherland</l>
<l n="tr">and no allegiance binds me any more.</l>
<l n="tr">O Troy, whom I have saved, I bid thee keep</l>
<l n="tr">the pledge of safety by good Priam given,</l>
<l n="tr">for my true tale shall my rich ransom be.</l>
<l n="tr">The Greeks' one hope, since first they opened war,</l>
<l n="tr">was Pallas, grace and power. But from the day</l>
<l n="tr">when Diomed, bold scorner of the gods,</l>
<l n="tr">and false Ulysses, author of all guile,</l>
<l n="tr">rose up and violently bore away</l>
<l n="tr">Palladium, her holy shrine, hewed down</l>
<l n="tr">the sentinels of her acropolis,</l>
<l n="tr">and with polluted, gory hands dared touch</l>
<l n="tr">the goddess, virgin fillets, white and pure,—</l>
<l n="tr">thenceforth, I say, the courage of the Greeks</l>
<l n="tr">ebbed utterly away; their strength was Iost,</l>
<l n="tr">and favoring Pallas all her grace withdrew.</l>
<l n="tr">No dubious sign she gave. Scarce had they set</l>
<l n="tr">her statue in our camp, when glittering flame</l>
<l n="tr">flashed from the staring eyes; from all its limbs</l>
<l n="tr">salt sweat ran forth; three times (O wondrous tale!)</l>
<l n="tr">it gave a sudden skyward leap, and made</l>
<l n="tr">prodigious trembling of her lance and shield.</l>
<l n="tr">The prophet Calchas bade us straightway take</l>
<l n="tr">swift flight across the sea; for fate had willed</l>
<l n="tr">the Trojan citadel should never fall</l>
<l n="tr">by Grecian arm, till once more they obtain</l>
<l n="tr">new oracles at <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, and restore</l>
<l n="tr">that god the round ships hurried o'er the sea.</l>
<l n="tr">Now in <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>, whither they are fled,</l>
<l n="tr">new help of heaven they find, and forge anew</l>
<l n="tr">the means of war. Back hither o'er the waves</l>
<l n="tr">they suddenly will come. So Calchas gave</l>
<l n="tr">the meaning of the god. Warned thus, they reared</l>
<l n="tr">in place of Pallas, desecrated shrine</l>
<l n="tr">yon image of the horse, to expiate</l>
<l n="tr">the woeful sacrilege. Calchas ordained</l>
<l n="tr">that they should build a thing of monstrous size</l>
<l n="tr">of jointed beams, and rear it heavenward,</l>
<l n="tr">so might it never pass your gates, nor come</l>
<l n="tr">inside your walls, nor anywise restore</l>
<l n="tr">unto the Trojans their lost help divine.</l>
<l n="tr">For had your hands Minerva's gift profaned,</l>
<l n="tr">a ruin horrible—O, may the gods</l>
<l n="tr">bring it on Calchas rather!—would have come</l>
<l n="tr">on Priam's throne and all the Phrygian power.</l>
<l n="tr">But if your hands should lift the holy thing</l>
<l n="tr">to your own citadel, then <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>'s host</l>
<l n="tr">would hurl aggression upon Pelops' land,</l>
<l n="tr">and all that curse on our own nation fall.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="195" unit="card" />Thus Sinon's guile and practiced perjury</l>
<l n="tr">our doubt dispelled. His stratagems and tears</l>
<l n="tr">wrought victory where neither Tydeus' son,</l>
<l n="tr">nor mountain-bred Achilles could prevail,</l>
<l n="tr">nor ten years' war, nor fleets a thousand strong.</l>
<l n="tr">But now a vaster spectacle of fear</l>
<l n="tr">burst over us, to vex our startled souls.</l>
<l n="tr">Laocoon, that day by cast of lot</l>
<l n="tr">priest unto Neptune, was in act to slay</l>
<l n="tr">a huge bull at the god's appointed fane.</l>
<l n="tr">Lo! o'er the tranquil deep from Tenedos</l>
<l n="tr">appeared a pair (I shudder as I tell)</l>
<l n="tr">of vastly coiling serpents, side by side,</l>
<l n="tr">stretching along the waves, and to the shore</l>
<l n="tr">taking swift course; their necks were lifted high,</l>
<l n="tr">their gory dragon-crests o'ertopped the waves;</l>
<l n="tr">all else, half seen, trailed low along the sea;</l>
<l n="tr">while with loud cleavage of the foaming brine</l>
<l n="tr">their monstrous backs wound forward fold on fold.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon they made land; the furious bright eyes</l>
<l n="tr">glowed with ensanguined fire; their quivering tongues</l>
<l n="tr">lapped hungrily the hissing, gruesome jaws.</l>
<l n="tr">All terror-pale we fled. Unswerving then</l>
<l n="tr">the monsters to Laocoon made way.</l>
<l n="tr">First round the tender limbs of his two sons</l>
<l n="tr">each dragon coiled, and on the shrinking flesh</l>
<l n="tr">fixed fast and fed. Then seized they on the sire,</l>
<l n="tr">who flew to aid, a javelin in his hand,</l>
<l n="tr">embracing close in bondage serpentine</l>
<l n="tr">twice round the waist; and twice in scaly grasp</l>
<l n="tr">around his neck, and o'er him grimly peered</l>
<l n="tr">with lifted head and crest; he, all the while,</l>
<l n="tr">his holy fillet fouled with venomous blood,</l>
<l n="tr">tore at his fetters with a desperate hand,</l>
<l n="tr">and lifted up such agonizing voice,</l>
<l n="tr">as when a bull, death-wounded, seeks to flee</l>
<l n="tr">the sacrificial altar, and thrusts back</l>
<l n="tr">from his doomed head the ill-aimed, glancing blade.</l>
<l n="tr">then swiftly writhed the dragon-pair away</l>
<l n="tr">unto the templed height, and in the shrine</l>
<l n="tr">of cruel Pallas sure asylum found</l>
<l n="tr">beneath the goddess' feet and orbed shield.</l>
<l n="tr">Such trembling horror as we ne'er had known</l>
<l n="tr">seized now on every heart. “ Of his vast guilt</l>
<l n="tr">Laocoon,” they say, “receives reward;</l>
<l n="tr">for he with most abominable spear</l>
<l n="tr">did strike and violate that blessed wood.</l>
<l n="tr">Yon statue to the temple! Ask the grace</l>
<l n="tr">of glorious Pallas!” So the people cried</l>
<l n="tr">in general acclaim.<milestone ed="p" n="234" unit="card" />Ourselves did make</l>
<l n="tr">a breach within our walls and opened wide</l>
<l n="tr">the ramparts of our city. One and all</l>
<l n="tr">were girded for the task. Smooth-gliding wheels</l>
<l n="tr">were 'neath its feet; great ropes stretched round its neck,</l>
<l n="tr">till o'er our walls the fatal engine climbed,</l>
<l n="tr">pregnant with men-at-arms. On every side</l>
<l n="tr">fair youths and maidens made a festal song,</l>
<l n="tr">and hauled the ropes with merry heart and gay.</l>
<l n="tr">So on and up it rolled, a tower of doom,</l>
<l n="tr">and in proud menace through our Forum moved.</l>
<l n="tr">O <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>, my country, where abode</l>
<l n="tr">the gods of all my sires! O glorious walls</l>
<l n="tr">of Dardan's sons! before your gates it passed,</l>
<l n="tr">four times it stopped and dreadful clash of arms</l>
<l n="tr">four times from its vast concave loudly rang.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet frantic pressed we on, our hearts all blind,</l>
<l n="tr">and in the consecrated citadel</l>
<l n="tr">set up the hateful thing. Cassandra then</l>
<l n="tr">from heaven-instructed heart our doom foretold;</l>
<l n="tr">but doomed to unbelief were <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s sons.</l>
<l n="tr">Our hapless nation on its dying day</l>
<l n="tr">flung free o'er streets and shrines the votive flowers.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="250" unit="card" />The skies rolled on; and o'er the ocean fell</l>
<l n="tr">the veil of night, till utmost earth and heaven</l>
<l n="tr">and all their Myrmidonian stratagems</l>
<l n="tr">were mantled darkly o'er. In silent sleep</l>
<l n="tr">the Trojan city lay; dull slumber chained</l>
<l n="tr">its weary life. But now the Greek array</l>
<l n="tr">of ordered ships moved on from <placeName key="perseus,Tenedos" authname="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">their only light the silent, favoring moon,</l>
<l n="tr">on to the well-known strand. The King displayed</l>
<l n="tr">torch from his own ship, and Sinon then,</l>
<l n="tr">whom wrathful Heaven defended in that hour,</l>
<l n="tr">let the imprisoned band of Greeks go free</l>
<l n="tr">from that huge womb of wood; the open horse</l>
<l n="tr">restored them to the light; and joyfully</l>
<l n="tr">emerging from the darkness, one by one,</l>
<l n="tr">princely Thessander, Sthenelus, and dire</l>
<l n="tr">Ulysses glided down the swinging cord.</l>
<l n="tr">Closely upon them Neoptolemus,</l>
<l n="tr">the son of Peleus, came, and Acamas,</l>
<l n="tr">King Menelaus, Thoas and Machaon,</l>
<l n="tr">and last, Epeus, who the fabric wrought.</l>
<l n="tr">Upon the town they fell, for deep in sleep</l>
<l n="tr">and drowsed with wine it lay; the sentinels</l>
<l n="tr">they slaughtered, and through gates now opened wide</l>
<l n="tr">let in their fellows, and arrayed for war</l>
<l n="tr">th' auxiliar legions of the dark design.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="268" unit="card" />That hour it was when heaven's first gift of sleep</l>
<l n="tr">on weary hearts of men most sweetly steals.</l>
<l n="tr">O, then my slumbering senses seemed to see</l>
<l n="tr">Hector, with woeful face and streaming eyes;</l>
<l n="tr">I seemed to see him from the chariot trailing,</l>
<l n="tr">foul with dark dust and gore, his swollen feet</l>
<l n="tr">pierced with a cruel thong. Ah me! what change</l>
<l n="tr">from glorious Hector when he homeward bore</l>
<l n="tr">the spoils of fierce Achilles; or hurled far</l>
<l n="tr">that shower of torches on the ships of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>!</l>
<l n="tr">Unkempt his beard, his tresses thick with blood,</l>
<l n="tr">and all those wounds in sight which he did take</l>
<l n="tr">defending <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. Then, weeping as I spoke,</l>
<l n="tr">I seemed on that heroic shape to call</l>
<l n="tr">with mournful utterance: “O star of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>!</l>
<l n="tr">O surest hope and stay of all her sons!</l>
<l n="tr">Why tarriest thou so Iong? What region sends</l>
<l n="tr">the long-expected Hector home once more?</l>
<l n="tr">These weary eyes that look on thee have seen</l>
<l n="tr">hosts of thy kindred die, and fateful change</l>
<l n="tr">upon thy people and thy city fall.</l>
<l n="tr">O, say what dire occasion has defiled</l>
<l n="tr">thy tranquil brows? What mean those bleeding wounds?”</l>
<l n="tr">Silent he stood, nor anywise would stay</l>
<l n="tr">my vain lament; but groaned, and answered thus:</l>
<l n="tr">“Haste, goddess-born, and out of yonder flames</l>
<l n="tr">achieve thy flight. Our foes have scaled the wall;</l>
<l n="tr">exalted <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> is falling. Fatherland</l>
<l n="tr">and Priam ask no more. If human arm</l>
<l n="tr">could profit <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, my own had kept her free.</l>
<l n="tr">Her Lares and her people to thy hands</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> here commends. Companions let them be</l>
<l n="tr">of all thy fortunes. Let them share thy quest</l>
<l n="tr">of that wide realm, which, after wandering far,</l>
<l n="tr">thou shalt achieve, at last, beyond the sea.”</l>
<l n="tr">He spoke: and from our holy hearth brought forth</l>
<l n="tr">the solemn fillet, the ancestral shrines,</l>
<l n="tr">and Vesta's ever-bright, inviolate fire.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="298" unit="card" />Now shrieks and loud confusion swept the town;</l>
<l n="tr">and though my father's dwelling stood apart</l>
<l n="tr">embowered deep in trees, th' increasing din</l>
<l n="tr">drew nearer, and the battle-thunder swelled.</l>
<l n="tr">I woke on sudden, and up-starting scaled</l>
<l n="tr">the roof, the tower, then stood with listening ear:</l>
<l n="tr">'t was like an harvest burning, when wild winds</l>
<l n="tr">uprouse the flames; 't was like a mountain stream</l>
<l n="tr">that bursts in flood and ruinously whelms</l>
<l n="tr">sweet fields and farms and all the ploughman's toil,</l>
<l n="tr">whirling whole groves along; while dumb with fear,</l>
<l n="tr">from some far cliff the shepherd hears the sound.</l>
<l n="tr">Now their Greek plot was plain, the stratagem</l>
<l n="tr">at last laid bare. Deiphobus' great house</l>
<l n="tr">sank vanquished in the fire. Ucalegon's</l>
<l n="tr">hard by was blazing, while the waters wide</l>
<l n="tr">around Sigeum gave an answering glow.</l>
<l n="tr">Shrill trumpets rang; Ioud shouting voices roared;</l>
<l n="tr">wildly I armed me (when the battle calls,</l>
<l n="tr">how dimly reason shines!); I burned to join</l>
<l n="tr">the rally of my peers, and to the heights</l>
<l n="tr">defensive gather. Frenzy and vast rage</l>
<l n="tr">seized on my soul. I only sought what way</l>
<l n="tr">with sword in hand some noble death to die.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="318" unit="card" />When Panthus met me, who had scarce escaped</l>
<l n="tr">the Grecian spears,—Panthus of Othrys' line,</l>
<l n="tr">Apollo's priest within our citadel;</l>
<l n="tr">his holy emblems, his defeated gods,</l>
<l n="tr">and his small grandson in his arms he bore,</l>
<l n="tr">while toward the gates with wild, swift steps he flew.</l>
<l n="tr">“How fares the kingdom, Panthus? What strong place</l>
<l n="tr">is still our own?” But scarcely could I ask</l>
<l n="tr">when thus, with many a groan, he made reply:—</l>
<l n="tr">“Dardania's death and doom are come to-day,</l>
<l n="tr">implacable. There is no <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> now;</l>
<l n="tr">our Trojan name is gone, the Teucrian throne</l>
<l n="tr"> Quite fallen. For the wrathful power of Jove</l>
<l n="tr">has given to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> all our boast and pride.</l>
<l n="tr">The Greek is Iord of all yon blazing towers.</l>
<l n="tr">yon horse uplifted on our city's heart</l>
<l n="tr">disgorges men-at-arms. False Sinon now,</l>
<l n="tr">with scorn exultant, heaps up flame on flame.</l>
<l n="tr">Others throw wide the gates. The whole vast horde</l>
<l n="tr">that out of proud <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> hither sailed</l>
<l n="tr">is at us. With confronting spears they throng</l>
<l n="tr">each narrow passage. Every steel-bright blade</l>
<l n="tr">is flashing naked, making haste for blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Our sentries helpless meet the invading shock</l>
<l n="tr">and give back blind and unavailing war.”</l>
<l n="tr">By Panthus' word and by some god impelled,</l>
<l n="tr">I flew to battle, where the flames leaped high,</l>
<l n="tr">where grim Bellona called, and all the air</l>
<l n="tr">resounded high as heaven with shouts of war.</l>
<l n="tr">Rhipeus and Epytus of doughty arm</l>
<l n="tr">were at my side, Dymas and Hypanis,</l>
<l n="tr">seen by a pale moon, join our little band;</l>
<l n="tr">and young Coroebus, Mygdon's princely son,</l>
<l n="tr">who was in <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> that hour because he loved</l>
<l n="tr">Cassandra madly, and had made a league</l>
<l n="tr">as Priam's kinsman with our Phrygian arms:</l>
<l n="tr">ill-starred, to heed not what the virgin raved!</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="347" unit="card" />When these I saw close-gathered for the fight,</l>
<l n="tr">I thus addressed them: “Warriors, vainly brave,</l>
<l n="tr">if ye indeed desire to follow one</l>
<l n="tr">who dares the uttermost brave men may do,</l>
<l n="tr">our evil plight ye see: the gods are fled</l>
<l n="tr">from every altar and protecting fire,</l>
<l n="tr">which were the kingdom's stay. Ye offer aid</l>
<l n="tr">unto your country's ashes. Let us fight</l>
<l n="tr">unto the death! To arms, my men, to arms!</l>
<l n="tr">The single hope and stay of desperate men</l>
<l n="tr">is their despair.” Thus did I rouse their souls.</l>
<l n="tr">Then like the ravening wolves, some night of cloud,</l>
<l n="tr">when cruel hunger in an empty maw</l>
<l n="tr">drives them forth furious, and their whelps behind</l>
<l n="tr">wait famine-throated; so through foemen's steel</l>
<l n="tr">we flew to surest death, and kept our way</l>
<l n="tr">straight through the midmost town . The wings of night</l>
<l n="tr">brooded above us in vast vault of shade.</l>
<l n="tr">But who the bloodshed of that night can tell?</l>
<l n="tr">What tongue its deaths shall number, or what eyes</l>
<l n="tr">find meed of tears to equal all its woe?</l>
<l n="tr">The ancient City fell, whose throne had stood</l>
<l n="tr">age after age. Along her streets were strewn</l>
<l n="tr">the unresisting dead; at household shrines</l>
<l n="tr">and by the temples of the gods they lay.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet not alone was Teucrian blood required:</l>
<l n="tr">oft out of vanquished hearts fresh valor flamed,</l>
<l n="tr">and the Greek victor fell. Anguish and woe</l>
<l n="tr">were everywhere; pale terrors ranged abroad,</l>
<l n="tr">and multitudinous death met every eye.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="370" unit="card" />Androgeos, followed by a thronging band</l>
<l n="tr">of Greeks, first met us on our desperate way;</l>
<l n="tr">but heedless, and confounding friend with foe,</l>
<l n="tr">thus, all unchallenged, hailed us as his own :</l>
<l n="tr">“Haste, heroes! Are ye laggards at this hour?</l>
<l n="tr">Others bear off the captives and the spoil</l>
<l n="tr">of burning <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. Just from the galleys ye?”</l>
<l n="tr">He spoke; but straightway, when no safe reply</l>
<l n="tr">returned, he knew himself entrapped, and fallen</l>
<l n="tr">into a foeman's snare; struck dumb was he</l>
<l n="tr">and stopped both word and motion; as one steps,</l>
<l n="tr">when blindly treading a thick path of thorns,</l>
<l n="tr">upon a snake, and sick with fear would flee</l>
<l n="tr">that lifted wrath and swollen gorge of green:</l>
<l n="tr">so trembling did Androgeos backward fall.</l>
<l n="tr">At them we flew and closed them round with war;</l>
<l n="tr">and since they could not know the ground, and fear </l>
<l n="tr">had whelmed them quite, we swiftly laid them low.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus Fortune on our first achievement smiled;</l>
<l n="tr">and, flushed with victory, Cormbus cried:</l>
<l n="tr">“Come, friends, and follow Fortune's finger, where</l>
<l n="tr">she beckons us what path deliverance lies.</l>
<l n="tr">Change we our shields, and these Greek emblems wear.</l>
<l n="tr">'Twixt guile and valor who will nicely weigh</l>
<l n="tr"> When foes are met? These dead shall find us arms.”</l>
<l n="tr">With this, he dons Androgeos' crested helm</l>
<l n="tr">and beauteous, blazoned shield; and to his side</l>
<l n="tr">girds on a Grecian blade. Young Rhipeus next,</l>
<l n="tr">with Dymas and the other soldiery,</l>
<l n="tr">repeat the deed, exulting, and array</l>
<l n="tr">their valor in fresh trophies from the slain.</l>
<l n="tr">Now intermingled with our foes we moved,</l>
<l n="tr">and alien emblems wore; the long, black night</l>
<l n="tr">brought many a grapple, and a host of Greeks</l>
<l n="tr">down to the dark we hurled. Some fled away,</l>
<l n="tr">seeking their safe ships and the friendly shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Some cowards foul went clambering back again</l>
<l n="tr">to that vast horse and hid them in its maw.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="402" unit="card" />But woe is me! If gods their help withhold,</l>
<l n="tr">'t is impious to be brave. That very hour</l>
<l n="tr">the fair Cassandra passed us, bound in chains,</l>
<l n="tr">King Priam's virgin daughter, from the shrine</l>
<l n="tr">and altars of Minerva; her loose hair</l>
<l n="tr">had lost its fillet; her impassioned eyes</l>
<l n="tr">were lifted in vain prayer,—her eyes alone!</l>
<l n="tr">For chains of steel her frail, soft hands confined.</l>
<l n="tr">Coroebus' eyes this horror not endured,</l>
<l n="tr">and, sorrow-crazed, he plunged him headlong in</l>
<l n="tr">the midmost fray, self-offered to be slain,</l>
<l n="tr">while in close mass our troop behind him poured.</l>
<l n="tr">But, at this point, the overwhelming spears</l>
<l n="tr">of our own kinsmen rained resistless down</l>
<l n="tr">from a high temple-tower; and carnage wild</l>
<l n="tr">ensued, because of the Greek arms we bore</l>
<l n="tr">and our false crests. The howling Grecian band,</l>
<l n="tr">crazed by Cassandra's rescue, charged at us</l>
<l n="tr">from every side; Ajax of savage soul,</l>
<l n="tr">the sons of Atreus, and that whole wild horde</l>
<l n="tr">Achilles from Dolopian deserts drew.</l>
<l n="tr">'T was like the bursting storm, when gales contend,</l>
<l n="tr">west wind and South, and jocund wind of morn</l>
<l n="tr">upon his orient steeds—while forests roar,</l>
<l n="tr">and foam-flecked Nereus with fierce trident stirs</l>
<l n="tr">the dark deep of the sea. All who did hide</l>
<l n="tr">in shadows of the night, by our assault</l>
<l n="tr">surprised, and driven in tumultuous flight,</l>
<l n="tr">now start to view. Full well they now can see</l>
<l n="tr">our shields and borrowed arms, and clearly note</l>
<l n="tr">our speech of alien sound; their multitude</l>
<l n="tr">o'erwhelms us utterly. Coroebus first</l>
<l n="tr">at mailed Minerva's altar prostrate lay,</l>
<l n="tr">pierced by Peneleus, blade; then Rhipeus fell;</l>
<l n="tr">we deemed him of all Trojans the most just, </l>
<l n="tr">most scrupulously righteous; but the gods</l>
<l n="tr">gave judgment otherwise. There Dymas died,</l>
<l n="tr">and Hypanis, by their compatriots slain;</l>
<l n="tr">nor thee, O Panthus, in that mortal hour,</l>
<l n="tr">could thy clean hands or Phoebus, priesthood save.</l>
<l n="tr">O ashes of my country! funeral pyre</l>
<l n="tr">of all my kin! bear witness that my breast</l>
<l n="tr">shrank not from any sword the Grecian drew,</l>
<l n="tr">and that my deeds the night my country died </l>
<l n="tr">deserved a warrior's death, had Fate ordained.</l>
<l n="tr">But soon our ranks were broken; at my side</l>
<l n="tr">stayed Iphitus and Pelias; one with age</l>
<l n="tr">was Iong since wearied, and the other bore</l>
<l n="tr">the burden of Ulysses' crippling wound.</l>
<l n="tr">Straightway the roar and tumult summoned us</l>
<l n="tr">to Priam's palace,<milestone ed="p" n="438" unit="card" />where a battle raged</l>
<l n="tr">as if save this no conflict else were known,</l>
<l n="tr">and all <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s dying brave were mustered there.</l>
<l n="tr">There we beheld the war-god unconfined;</l>
<l n="tr">The Greek besiegers to the roof-tops fled;</l>
<l n="tr">or, with shields tortoise-back, the gates assailed.</l>
<l n="tr">Ladders were on the walls; and round by round,</l>
<l n="tr">up the huge bulwark as they fight their way,</l>
<l n="tr">the shielded left-hand thwarts the falling spears,</l>
<l n="tr">the right to every vantage closely clings.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans hurl whole towers and roof-tops down</l>
<l n="tr">upon the mounting foe; for well they see</l>
<l n="tr">that the last hour is come, and with what arms</l>
<l n="tr">the dying must resist. Rich gilded beams,</l>
<l n="tr">with many a beauteous blazon of old time,</l>
<l n="tr">go crashing down. Men armed with naked swords</l>
<l n="tr">defend the inner doors in close array.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="453" unit="card" />Thus were our hearts inflamed to stand and strike</l>
<l n="tr">for the king's house, and to his body-guard</l>
<l n="tr">bring succor, and renew their vanquished powers.</l>
<l n="tr">A certain gate I knew, a secret way,</l>
<l n="tr">which gave free passage between Priam's halls,</l>
<l n="tr">and exit rearward; hither, in the days</l>
<l n="tr">before our fall, the lone Andromache</l>
<l n="tr">was wont with young Astyanax to pass</l>
<l n="tr">in quest of Priam and her husband's kin.</l>
<l n="tr">This way to climb the palace roof I flew,</l>
<l n="tr">where, desperate, the Trojans with vain skill</l>
<l n="tr">hurled forth repellent arms. A tower was there,</l>
<l n="tr">reared skyward from the roof-top, giving view</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s wide walls and full reconnaissance</l>
<l n="tr">of all <placeName key="tgn,7002733" authname="tgn,7002733">Achaea</placeName>'s fleets and tented field;</l>
<l n="tr">this, with strong steel, our gathered strength assailed,</l>
<l n="tr">and as the loosened courses offered us</l>
<l n="tr">great threatening fissures, we uprooted it</l>
<l n="tr">from its aerial throne and thrust it down.</l>
<l n="tr">It fell with instantaneous crash of thunder</l>
<l n="tr">along the Danaan host in ruin wide.</l>
<l n="tr">But fresh ranks soon arrive; thick showers of stone</l>
<l n="tr">rain down, with every missile rage can find.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="469" unit="card" />Now at the threshold of the outer court </l>
<l n="tr">Pyrrhus triumphant stood, with glittering arms</l>
<l n="tr">and helm of burnished brass. He glittered like</l>
<l n="tr">some swollen viper, fed on poison-leaves,</l>
<l n="tr">whom chilling winter shelters underground,</l>
<l n="tr">till, fresh and strong, he sheds his annual scales</l>
<l n="tr">and, crawling forth rejuvenate, uncoils</l>
<l n="tr">his slimy length; his lifted gorge insults</l>
<l n="tr">the sunbeam with three-forked and quivering tongue.</l>
<l n="tr">Huge Periphas was there; Automedon,</l>
<l n="tr">who drove Achilles' steeds, and bore his arms.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Scyros' island-warriors assault</l>
<l n="tr">the palaces, and hurl reiterate fire</l>
<l n="tr">at wall and tower. Pyrrhus led the van;</l>
<l n="tr">seizing an axe he clove the ponderous doors</l>
<l n="tr">and rent the hinges from their posts of bronze;</l>
<l n="tr">he cut the beams, and through the solid mass</l>
<l n="tr">burrowed his way, till like a window huge</l>
<l n="tr">the breach yawned wide, and opened to his gaze</l>
<l n="tr">a vista of long courts and corridors,</l>
<l n="tr">the hearth and home of many an ancient king,</l>
<l n="tr">and Priam's own; upon its sacred bourne</l>
<l n="tr">the sentry, all in arms, kept watch and ward.</l>
<l n="tr">Confusion, groans, and piteous turmoil</l>
<l n="tr">were in that dwelling; women shrieked and wailed</l>
<l n="tr">from many a dark retreat, and their loud cry</l>
<l n="tr">rang to the golden stars. Through those vast halls</l>
<l n="tr">the panic-stricken mothers wildly roved,</l>
<l n="tr">and clung with frantic kisses and embrace</l>
<l n="tr">unto the columns cold. Fierce as his sire,</l>
<l n="tr">Pyrrhus moves on; nor bar nor sentinel</l>
<l n="tr">may stop his way; down tumbles the great door</l>
<l n="tr">beneath the battering beam, and with it fall</l>
<l n="tr">hinges and framework violently torn.</l>
<l n="tr">Force bursts all bars; th' assailing Greeks break in,</l>
<l n="tr">do butchery, and with men-at-arms possess</l>
<l n="tr">what place they will. Scarce with an equal rage</l>
<l n="tr">a foaming river, when its dykes are down,</l>
<l n="tr">o'erwhelms its mounded shores, and through the plain</l>
<l n="tr">rolls mountain-high, while from the ravaged farms</l>
<l n="tr">its fierce flood sweeps along both flock and fold.</l>
<l n="tr">My own eyes looked on Neoptolemus</l>
<l n="tr">frenzied with slaughter, and both Atreus' sons</l>
<l n="tr">upon the threshold frowning; I beheld</l>
<l n="tr">her hundred daughters with old Hecuba;</l>
<l n="tr">and Priam, whose own bleeding wounds defiled</l>
<l n="tr">the altars where himself had blessed the fires;</l>
<l n="tr">there fifty nuptial beds gave promise proud</l>
<l n="tr">of princely heirs; but all their brightness now,</l>
<l n="tr">of broidered cunning and barbaric gold,</l>
<l n="tr">lay strewn and trampled on. The Danaan foe</l>
<l n="tr">stood victor, where the raging flame had failed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="506" unit="card" />But would ye haply know what stroke of doom</l>
<l n="tr">on Priam fell? Now when his anguish saw</l>
<l n="tr">his kingdom lost and fallen, his abode</l>
<l n="tr">shattered, and in his very hearth and home</l>
<l n="tr">th' exulting foe, the aged King did bind</l>
<l n="tr">his rusted armor to his trembling thews,—</l>
<l n="tr">all vainly,— and a useless blade of steel</l>
<l n="tr">he girded on; then charged, resolved to die</l>
<l n="tr">encircled by the foe. Within his walls</l>
<l n="tr">there stood, beneath the wide and open sky,</l>
<l n="tr">a lofty altar; an old laurel-tree</l>
<l n="tr">leaned o'er it, and enclasped in holy shade</l>
<l n="tr">the statues of the tutelary powers.</l>
<l n="tr">Here Hecuba and all the princesses</l>
<l n="tr">took refuge vain within the place of prayer.</l>
<l n="tr">Like panic-stricken doves in some dark storm,</l>
<l n="tr">close-gathering they sate, and in despair</l>
<l n="tr">embraced their graven gods. But when the Queen</l>
<l n="tr">saw Priam with his youthful harness on, </l>
<l n="tr">“What frenzy, O my wretched lord,” she cried,</l>
<l n="tr">“Arrayed thee in such arms? O, whither now?</l>
<l n="tr">Not such defences, nor such arm as thine,</l>
<l n="tr">the time requires, though thy companion were</l>
<l n="tr">our Hector's self. O, yield thee, I implore!</l>
<l n="tr">This altar now shall save us one and all,</l>
<l n="tr">or we must die together.” With these words</l>
<l n="tr">she drew him to her side, and near the shrine</l>
<l n="tr">made for her aged spouse a place to cling.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="526" unit="card" />But, lo! just 'scaped of Pyrrhus' murderous hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Polites, one of Priam's sons, fled fast</l>
<l n="tr">along the corridors, through thronging foes</l>
<l n="tr">and a thick rain of spears. Wildly he gazed</l>
<l n="tr">across the desolate halls, wounded to death.</l>
<l n="tr">Fierce Pyrrhus followed after, pressing hard</l>
<l n="tr">with mortal stroke, and now his hand and spear</l>
<l n="tr">were close upon:— when the lost youth leaped forth</l>
<l n="tr">into his father's sight, and prostrate there</l>
<l n="tr">lay dying, while his life-blood ebbed away.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Priam, though on all sides death was nigh,</l>
<l n="tr">quit not the strife, nor from loud wrath refrained:</l>
<l n="tr">“Thy crime and impious outrage, may the gods</l>
<l n="tr">(if Heaven to mortals render debt and due)</l>
<l n="tr">justly reward and worthy honors pay!</l>
<l n="tr">My own son's murder thou hast made me see,</l>
<l n="tr">blood and pollution impiously throwing</l>
<l n="tr">upon a father's head. Not such was he,</l>
<l n="tr">not such, Achilles, thy pretended sire,</l>
<l n="tr">when Priam was his foe. With flush of shame</l>
<l n="tr">he nobly listened to a suppliant's plea</l>
<l n="tr">in honor made. He rendered to the tomb</l>
<l n="tr">my Hector's body pale, and me did send</l>
<l n="tr">back to my throne a king.” With this proud word</l>
<l n="tr">the aged warrior hurled with nerveless arm</l>
<l n="tr">his ineffectual spear, which hoarsely rang</l>
<l n="tr">rebounding on the brazen shield, and hung</l>
<l n="tr">piercing the midmost boss,- but all in vain.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Pyrrhus: “Take these tidings, and convey</l>
<l n="tr">message to my father, Peleus' son!</l>
<l n="tr">tell him my naughty deeds! Be sure and say</l>
<l n="tr">how Neoptolemus hath shamed his sires.</l>
<l n="tr">Now die!” With this, he trailed before the shrines</l>
<l n="tr">the trembling King, whose feet slipped in the stream</l>
<l n="tr">of his son's blood. Then Pyrrhus' left hand clutched</l>
<l n="tr">the tresses old and gray; a glittering sword</l>
<l n="tr">his right hand lifted high, and buried it</l>
<l n="tr">far as the hilt in that defenceless heart.</l>
<l n="tr">So Priam's story ceased. Such final doom</l>
<l n="tr">fell on him, while his dying eyes surveyed</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> burning, and her altars overthrown,</l>
<l n="tr">though once of many an orient land and tribe</l>
<l n="tr">the boasted lord. In huge dismemberment</l>
<l n="tr">his severed trunk lies tombless on the shore,</l>
<l n="tr">the head from shoulder torn, the corpse unknown.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="559" unit="card" />Then first wild horror on my spirit fell</l>
<l n="tr">and dazed me utterly. A vision rose</l>
<l n="tr">of my own cherished father, as I saw</l>
<l n="tr">the King, his aged peer, sore wounded Iying</l>
<l n="tr">in mortal agony; a vision too</l>
<l n="tr">of lost Creusa at my ravaged hearth,</l>
<l n="tr">and young Iulus' peril. Then my eyes</l>
<l n="tr">looked round me seeking aid. But all were fled,</l>
<l n="tr">war-wearied and undone; some earthward leaped</l>
<l n="tr">from battlement or tower; some in despair</l>
<l n="tr">yielded their suffering bodies to the flame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="567" unit="card" />I stood there sole surviving; when, behold,</l>
<l n="tr">to Vesta's altar clinging in dumb fear,</l>
<l n="tr">hiding and crouching in the hallowed shade,</l>
<l n="tr">Tyndarus' daughter!— 't was the burning town</l>
<l n="tr">lighted full well my roving steps and eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">In fear was she both of some Trojan's rage</l>
<l n="tr">for <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> o'erthrown, and of some Greek revenge,</l>
<l n="tr">or her wronged husband's Iong indignant ire.</l>
<l n="tr">So hid she at that shrine her hateful brow,</l>
<l n="tr">being of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, full well she knew,</l>
<l n="tr">the common curse. Then in my bosom rose</l>
<l n="tr">a blaze of wrath; methought I should avenge</l>
<l n="tr">my dying country, and with horrid deed</l>
<l n="tr">pay crime for crime. “Shall she return unscathed</l>
<l n="tr">to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta" authname="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, to <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>'s golden pride,</l>
<l n="tr">and have a royal triumph? Shall her eyes</l>
<l n="tr">her sire and sons, her hearth and husband see,</l>
<l n="tr">while Phrygian captives follow in her train?</l>
<l n="tr">is Priam murdered? Have the flames swept o'er</l>
<l n="tr">my native <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>? and cloth our Dardan strand</l>
<l n="tr">sweat o'er and o'er with sanguinary dew?</l>
<l n="tr">O, not thus unavenged! For though there be</l>
<l n="tr">no glory if I smite a woman's crime,</l>
<l n="tr">nor conqueror's fame for such a victory won,</l>
<l n="tr">yet if I blot this monster out, and wring</l>
<l n="tr">full punishment from guilt, the time to come</l>
<l n="tr">will praise me, and sweet pleasure it will be</l>
<l n="tr">to glut my soul with vengeance and appease</l>
<l n="tr">the ashes of my kindred.”<milestone ed="p" n="588" unit="card" />So I raved,</l>
<l n="tr">and to such frenzied purpose gave my soul.</l>
<l n="tr">Then with clear vision (never had I seen</l>
<l n="tr">her presence so unclouded) I beheld,</l>
<l n="tr">in golden beams that pierced the midnight gloom,</l>
<l n="tr">my gracious mother, visibly divine,</l>
<l n="tr">and with that mien of majesty she wears</l>
<l n="tr">when seen in heaven; she stayed me with her hand,</l>
<l n="tr">and from her lips of rose this counsel gave:</l>
<l n="tr">“O son, what sorrow stirs thy boundless rage?</l>
<l n="tr">what madness this? Or whither vanisheth</l>
<l n="tr">thy love of me? Wilt thou not seek to know</l>
<l n="tr">where bides Anchises, thy abandoned sire,</l>
<l n="tr">now weak with age? or if Creusa lives</l>
<l n="tr">and young Ascanius, who are ringed about</l>
<l n="tr">with ranks of Grecian foes, and long ere this—</l>
<l n="tr">save that my love can shield them and defend—</l>
<l n="tr">had fallen on flame or fed some hungry sword?</l>
<l n="tr">Not Helen's hated beauty works thee woe;</l>
<l n="tr">nor Paris, oft-accused. The cruelty</l>
<l n="tr">of gods, of gods unaided, overwhelms</l>
<l n="tr">thy country's power, and from its Iofty height</l>
<l n="tr">casts <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> down. Behold, I take away</l>
<l n="tr">the barrier-cloud that dims thy mortal eye,</l>
<l n="tr">with murk and mist o'er-veiling. Fear not thou</l>
<l n="tr">to heed thy mother's word, nor let thy heart</l>
<l n="tr">refuse obedience to her counsel given.</l>
<l n="tr">'Mid yonder trembling ruins, where thou see'st</l>
<l n="tr">stone torn from stone, with dust and smoke uprolling,</l>
<l n="tr">'t is Neptune strikes the wall; his trident vast</l>
<l n="tr">makes her foundation tremble, and unseats</l>
<l n="tr">the city from her throne. Fierce Juno leads</l>
<l n="tr">resistless onset at the Scaean gate,</l>
<l n="tr">and summons from the ships the league of powers,</l>
<l n="tr">wearing her wrathful sword. On yonder height</l>
<l n="tr">behold Tritonia in the citadel</l>
<l n="tr">clothed with the lightning and her Gorgon-shield!</l>
<l n="tr">Unto the Greeks great Jove himself renews</l>
<l n="tr">their courage and their power; 't is he thrusts on</l>
<l n="tr">the gods themselves against the Trojan arms.</l>
<l n="tr">Fly, O my son! The war's wild work give o'er!</l>
<l n="tr">I will be always nigh and set thee safe</l>
<l n="tr">upon thy father's threshold.” Having said,</l>
<l n="tr">she fled upon the viewless night away.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="624" unit="card" />Then loomed o'er <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> the apparition vast</l>
<l n="tr">of her dread foes divine; I seemed to see</l>
<l n="tr">all <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> sink in fire, and sacred <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">of Neptune's building, utterly o'erthrown.</l>
<l n="tr">So some huge ash-tree on the mountain's brow</l>
<l n="tr">(when rival woodmen, heaving stroke on stroke</l>
<l n="tr">of two-edged axes, haste to cast her down)</l>
<l n="tr">sways ominously her trembling, leafy top,</l>
<l n="tr">and drops her smitten head; till by her wounds</l>
<l n="tr">vanquished at last, she makes her dying groan,</l>
<l n="tr">and falls in loud wreck from the cliffs uptorn.</l>
<l n="tr">I left the citadel; and, led by Heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">threaded the maze of deadly foes and fires,</l>
<l n="tr">through spears that glanced aside and flames that fell.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="634" unit="card" />Soon came I to my father's ancient seat,</l>
<l n="tr">our home and heritage. But lo! my sire</l>
<l n="tr">(whom first of all I sought, and first would bear</l>
<l n="tr">to safe asylum in the distant hills)</l>
<l n="tr">vowed he could never, after fallen <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">live longer on, or bear an exile's woe.</l>
<l n="tr">“O you,” he cried, “whose blood not yet betrays</l>
<l n="tr">the cruel taint of time, whose powers be still</l>
<l n="tr">unpropped and undecayed, go, take your flight.</l>
<l n="tr">If heavenly wrath had willed my life to spare,</l>
<l n="tr">this dwelling had been safe. It is too much</l>
<l n="tr">that I have watched one wreck, and for too Iong</l>
<l n="tr">outlived my vanquished country. Thus, O, thus!</l>
<l n="tr">Compose these limbs for death, and say farewell.</l>
<l n="tr">My own hand will procure it; or my foe</l>
<l n="tr">will end me of mere pity, and for spoil</l>
<l n="tr">will strip me bare. It is an easy loss</l>
<l n="tr">to have no grave. For many a year gone by,</l>
<l n="tr">accursed of Heaven, I tarry in this world</l>
<l n="tr">a useless burden, since that fatal hour</l>
<l n="tr">when Jove, of gods the Sire and men the King,</l>
<l n="tr">his lightnings o'er me breathed and blasting fire.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="650" unit="card" />Such fixed resolve he uttered o'er and o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">and would not yield, though with my tears did join</l>
<l n="tr">my spouse Creusa, fair Ascanius,</l>
<l n="tr">and our whole house, imploring the gray sire</l>
<l n="tr">not with himself to ruin all, nor add</l>
<l n="tr">yet heavier burdens to our crushing doom.</l>
<l n="tr">He still cried, “No!” and clung to where he sat</l>
<l n="tr">and to the same dread purpose. I once more</l>
<l n="tr">back to the fight would speed. For death alone</l>
<l n="tr">I made my wretched prayer. What space was left</l>
<l n="tr">for wisdom now? What chance or hope was given?</l>
<l n="tr">“Didst thou, dear father, dream that I could fly</l>
<l n="tr">sundered from thee? Did such an infamy</l>
<l n="tr">fall from a father's lips? If Heaven's decree</l>
<l n="tr">will of this mighty nation not let live</l>
<l n="tr">a single soul, if thine own purpose be</l>
<l n="tr">to cast thyself and thy posterity</l>
<l n="tr">into thy country's grave, behold, the door</l>
<l n="tr">is open to thy death! Lo, Pyrrhus comes</l>
<l n="tr">red-handed from King Priam! He has slain</l>
<l n="tr">a son before a father's eyes, and spilt</l>
<l n="tr">a father's blood upon his own hearthstone.</l>
<l n="tr">Was it for this, O heavenly mother mine,</l>
<l n="tr">that thou hast brought me safe through sword and fire?</l>
<l n="tr">that I might see these altars desecrate</l>
<l n="tr">by their worst foes? that I might look upon</l>
<l n="tr">my sire, my wife, and sweet Ascanius</l>
<l n="tr">dead at my feet in one another's blood?</l>
<l n="tr">To arms, my men, to arms! The hour of death</l>
<l n="tr">now beckons to the vanquished. Let me go</l>
<l n="tr">whither the Greeks are gathered; let me stand</l>
<l n="tr">where oft revives the flagging stroke of war:</l>
<l n="tr">Not all of us die unavenged this day!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="671" unit="card" />I clasped my sword-belt round me once again,</l>
<l n="tr">fitted my left arm to my shield, and turned</l>
<l n="tr">to fly the house; but at the threshold clung</l>
<l n="tr">Creusa to my knees, and lifted up</l>
<l n="tr">Iulus to his father's arms. “If thou</l>
<l n="tr">wouldst rush on death,” she cried, “O, suffer us</l>
<l n="tr">to share thy perils with thee to the end.</l>
<l n="tr">But if this day's work bid thee trust a sword,</l>
<l n="tr">defend thy hearthstone first. Who else shall guard</l>
<l n="tr">thy babe Iulus, or thy reverend sire?</l>
<l n="tr">Or me, thy wife that was—what help have I?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="679" unit="card" />So rang the roof-top with her piteous cries:</l>
<l n="tr">but lo! a portent wonderful to see</l>
<l n="tr">on sudden rose; for while his parents' grief</l>
<l n="tr">held the boy close in arm and full in view,</l>
<l n="tr">there seemed upon Iulus' head to glow</l>
<l n="tr">a flickering peak of fire; the tongue of flame</l>
<l n="tr">innocuous o'er his clustering tresses played,</l>
<l n="tr">and hovered round his brows. We, horror-struck,</l>
<l n="tr">grasped at his burning hair, and sprinkled him,</l>
<l n="tr">to quench that holy and auspicious fire.</l>
<l n="tr">then sire Anchises with exultant eyes</l>
<l n="tr">looked heavenward, and lifted to the stars</l>
<l n="tr">his voice and outstretched hands. “Almighty Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">if aught of prayer may move thee, let thy grace</l>
<l n="tr">now visit us! O, hear this holy vow!</l>
<l n="tr">And if for service at thine altars done,</l>
<l n="tr">we aught can claim, O Father, lend us aid,</l>
<l n="tr">and ratify the omen thou hast given!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="692" unit="card" />Scarce ceased his aged voice, when suddenly </l>
<l n="tr">from leftward, with a deafening thunder-peal, </l>
<l n="tr">cleaving the blackness of the vaulted sky,</l>
<l n="tr">a meteor-star in trailing splendor ran, </l>
<l n="tr">exceeding bright. We watched it glide sublime</l>
<l n="tr">o'er tower and town, until its radiant beam </l>
<l n="tr">in forest-mantled Ida died away;</l>
<l n="tr">but left a furrow on its track in air,</l>
<l n="tr">a glittering, Iong line, while far and wide</l>
<l n="tr">the sulphurous fume and exhalation flowed.</l>
<l n="tr">My father strove not now; but lifted him</l>
<l n="tr">in prayer to all the gods, in holy awe</l>
<l n="tr">of that auspicious star, and thus exclaimed:</l>
<l n="tr">“Tarry no moment more! Behold, I come!</l>
<l n="tr">Whithersoe'er ye lead, my steps obey.</l>
<l n="tr">Gods of my fathers, O, preserve our name!</l>
<l n="tr">Preserve my son, and his! This augury</l>
<l n="tr">is yours; and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> on your sole strength relies.</l>
<l n="tr">I yield, dear son; I journey at thy side.”</l>
<l n="tr">He spoke; and higher o'er the blazing walls</l>
<l n="tr">leaped the loud fire, while ever nearer drew</l>
<l n="tr">the rolling surges of tumultuous flame.</l>
<l n="tr">“Haste, father, on these bending shoulders climb!</l>
<l n="tr">This back is ready, and the burden light;</l>
<l n="tr">one peril smites us both, whate'er befall;</l>
<l n="tr">one rescue both shall find. Close at my side</l>
<l n="tr">let young Iulus run, while, not too nigh,</l>
<l n="tr">my wife Creusa heeds what way we go.</l>
<l n="tr">Ye servants of our house, give ear, I pray,</l>
<l n="tr">to my command. Outside the city's gates</l>
<l n="tr">lies a low mound and long since ruined fane</l>
<l n="tr">to Ceres vowed; a cypress, ancient shade</l>
<l n="tr">o'erhangs it, which our fathers' pious care</l>
<l n="tr">protected year by year; by various paths</l>
<l n="tr">be that our meeting-place. But in thy hands</l>
<l n="tr">bring, sire, our household gods, and sanctifies:</l>
<l n="tr">for me to touch, who come this very hour</l>
<l n="tr">from battle and the fresh blood of the slain,</l>
<l n="tr">were but abomination, till what time</l>
<l n="tr">in living waters I shall make me clean.”</l>
<l n="tr">So saying, I bowed my neck and shoulders broad,</l>
<l n="tr">o'erspread me with a lion's tawny skin,</l>
<l n="tr">and lifted up my load. Close at my side</l>
<l n="tr">little Iulus twined his hand in mine</l>
<l n="tr">and followed, with unequal step, his sire.</l>
<l n="tr">My wife at distance came. We hastened on,</l>
<l n="tr">creeping through shadows; I, who once had viewed</l>
<l n="tr">undaunted every instrument of war</l>
<l n="tr">and all the gathered Greeks in grim array,</l>
<l n="tr">now shook at every gust, and heard all sounds</l>
<l n="tr">with fevered trepidation, fearing both</l>
<l n="tr">for him I bore and him who clasped my hand.</l>
<l n="tr">Now near the gates I drew, and deemed our flight</l>
<l n="tr">safely at end, when suddenly I heard</l>
<l n="tr">the sounding tread of many warriors</l>
<l n="tr">that seemed hard-by, while through the murky night</l>
<l n="tr">my father peered, and shouted, “O my son,</l>
<l n="tr">away, away! for surely all our foes</l>
<l n="tr">are here upon us, and my eyes behold</l>
<l n="tr">the glance of glittering shields and flash of arms.”</l>
<l n="tr">O, then some evil-working, nameless god</l>
<l n="tr">clouded my senses quite: for while I sped</l>
<l n="tr">along our pathless way, and left behind</l>
<l n="tr">all paths and regions known—O wretched me!—</l>
<l n="tr">Creusa on some dark disaster fell;</l>
<l n="tr">she stopped, or wandered, or sank down undone,—</l>
<l n="tr">I never knew what way,—and nevermore</l>
<l n="tr">I looked on her alive. Yet knew I not</l>
<l n="tr">my loss, nor backward turned a look or thought,</l>
<l n="tr">till by that hallowed hill to Ceres vowed</l>
<l n="tr">we gathered all,— and she alone came not,</l>
<l n="tr">while husband, friends, and son made search in vain.</l>
<l n="tr">What god, what man, did not my grief accuse</l>
<l n="tr">in frenzied word? In all the ruined land</l>
<l n="tr">what worse woe had I seen? Entrusting then</l>
<l n="tr">my sire, my son, and all the Teucrian gods</l>
<l n="tr">to the deep shadows of a slanting vale</l>
<l n="tr">where my allies kept guard, I tried me back</l>
<l n="tr">to that doomed town, re-girt in glittering arms.</l>
<l n="tr">Resolved was I all hazards to renew,</l>
<l n="tr">all <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to re-explore, and once again</l>
<l n="tr">offer my life to perils without end.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="752" unit="card" />The walls and gloomy gates whence forth I came</l>
<l n="tr">I first revisit, and retrace my way,</l>
<l n="tr">searching the night once more. On all sides round</l>
<l n="tr">horror spread wide; the very silence breathed</l>
<l n="tr">a terror on my soul. I hastened then</l>
<l n="tr">back to my fallen home, if haply there</l>
<l n="tr">her feet had strayed; but the invading Greeks</l>
<l n="tr">were its possessors, though the hungry fire</l>
<l n="tr">was blown along the roof-tree, and the flames</l>
<l n="tr">rolled raging upward on the fitful gale.</l>
<l n="tr">To Priam's house I haste, and climb once more</l>
<l n="tr">the citadel; in Juno's temple there,</l>
<l n="tr">the chosen guardians of her wasted halls,</l>
<l n="tr">Phoenix and dread Ulysses watched the spoil.</l>
<l n="tr">Here, snatched away from many a burning fane,</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s treasures lay,—rich tables for the gods,</l>
<l n="tr">thick bowls of messy gold, and vestures rare,</l>
<l n="tr">confusedly heaped up, while round the pile</l>
<l n="tr">fair youths and trembling virgins stood forlorn.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet oft my voice rang dauntless through the gloom,</l>
<l n="tr">from street to street I cried with anguish vain;</l>
<l n="tr">and on Creusa piteously calling,</l>
<l n="tr">woke the lamenting echoes o'er and o'er.</l>
<l n="tr">While on this quest I roamed the city through,</l>
<l n="tr">of reason reft there rose upon my sight—</l>
<l n="tr">O shape of sorrow!— my Creusa's ghost,</l>
<l n="tr">hers truly, though a loftier port it wore.</l>
<l n="tr">I quailed, my hair rose, and I gasped for fear;</l>
<l n="tr">but thus she spoke, and soothed my grief away:</l>
<l n="tr">“Why to these frenzied sorrows bend thy soul,</l>
<l n="tr">O husband ever dear! The will of Heaven</l>
<l n="tr">hath brought all this to pass. Fate doth not send</l>
<l n="tr">Creusa the long journeys thou shalt take,</l>
<l n="tr">or hath th' Olympian King so given decree.</l>
<l n="tr">Long is thy banishment; thy ship must plough</l>
<l n="tr">the vast, far-spreading sea. Then shalt thou come</l>
<l n="tr">unto Hesperia, whose fruitful plains </l>
<l n="tr">are watered by the <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>, Lydian stream, </l>
<l n="tr">of smooth, benignant Bow. Thou shalt obtain </l>
<l n="tr">fair fortunes, and a throne and royal bride.</l>
<l n="tr">For thy beloved Creusa weep no more!</l>
<l n="tr">No Myrmidon's proud palace waits me now;</l>
<l n="tr">Dolopian shall not scorn, nor <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> dames</l>
<l n="tr">command a slave of Dardan's royal stem</l>
<l n="tr">and wife to Venus' son. On these loved shores</l>
<l n="tr">the Mother of the Gods compels my stay.</l>
<l n="tr">Farewell! farewell! O, cherish evermore</l>
<l n="tr">thy son and mine!” Her utterance scarce had ceased,</l>
<l n="tr">when, as I strove through tears to make reply,</l>
<l n="tr">she left me, and dissolved in empty air.</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice would my frustrate arms her form enfold;</l>
<l n="tr">thrice from the clasp of hand that vision fled,</l>
<l n="tr">like wafted winds and like a fleeting dream.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="795" unit="card" />The night had passed, and to my friends once more</l>
<l n="tr">I made my way, much wondering to find</l>
<l n="tr">a mighty multitude assembled there</l>
<l n="tr">of friends new-come,—matrons and men-at-arms,</l>
<l n="tr">and youth for exile bound,— a doleful throng.</l>
<l n="tr">From far and near they drew, their hearts prepared</l>
<l n="tr">and their possessions gathered, to sail forth</l>
<l n="tr">to lands unknown, wherever o'er the wave</l>
<l n="tr">I bade them follow. Now above the crest</l>
<l n="tr">of loftiest Ida rose the morning-star, </l>
<l n="tr">chief in the front of day. The Greeks held fast</l>
<l n="tr">the captive gates of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. No help or hope</l>
<l n="tr">was ours any more. Then, yielding all,</l>
<l n="tr">and lifting once again my aged sire,</l>
<l n="tr">for refuge to the distant hills I fled.</l></div1>
<div1 type="Book" n="3" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card" />
<l n="tr">When <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>'s power and Priam's race and throne,</l>
<l n="tr">though guiltless, were cast down by Heaven's decree,</l>
<l n="tr">when <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> proud had fallen, and Neptune's <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">in smouldering ash lay level with the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">to wandering exile then and regions wild</l>
<l n="tr">the gods by many an augury and sign</l>
<l n="tr">compelled us forth. We fashioned us a fleet</l>
<l n="tr">within Antander's haven, in the shade</l>
<l n="tr">of Phrygian Ida's peak (though knowing not</l>
<l n="tr">whither our fate would drive, or where afford</l>
<l n="tr">a resting-place at last), and my small band</l>
<l n="tr">of warriors I arrayed. As soon as smiled</l>
<l n="tr">the light of summer's prime, my reverend sire</l>
<l n="tr">Anchises bade us on the winds of Fate</l>
<l n="tr">to spread all sail. Through tears I saw recede</l>
<l n="tr">my native shore, the haven and the plains</l>
<l n="tr">where once was <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. An exile on the seas,</l>
<l n="tr">with son and followers and household shrines,</l>
<l n="tr">and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s great guardian-gods, I took my way.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="13" unit="card" />There is a far-off land where warriors breed,</l>
<l n="tr">where Thracians till the boundless plains, and where</l>
<l n="tr">the cruel-eyed Lycurgus once was king.</l>
<l n="tr">Troy's old ally it was, its deities</l>
<l n="tr">had brotherhood with ours before our fall.</l>
<l n="tr">Thither I fared, and on its winding shores</l>
<l n="tr">set my first walls, though partial Fate opposed</l>
<l n="tr">our entrance there. In memory of my name</l>
<l n="tr">I called its people the Aeneadae.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="19" unit="card" />Unto Dione's daughter, and all gods</l>
<l n="tr">who blessed our young emprise, due gifts were paid;</l>
<l n="tr">and unto the supreme celestial King</l>
<l n="tr">I slew a fair white bull beside the sea.</l>
<l n="tr">But haply near my place of sacrifice</l>
<l n="tr">a mound was seen, and on the summit grew</l>
<l n="tr">a copse of corner and a myrtle tree,</l>
<l n="tr">with spear-like limbs outbranched on every side.</l>
<l n="tr">This I approached, and tried to rend away</l>
<l n="tr">from its deep roots that grove of gloomy green,</l>
<l n="tr">and dress my altars in its leafy boughs.</l>
<l n="tr">But, horrible to tell, a prodigy</l>
<l n="tr">smote my astonished eyes: for the first tree,</l>
<l n="tr">which from the earth with broken roots I drew,</l>
<l n="tr">dripped black with bloody drops, and gave the ground</l>
<l n="tr">dark stains of gore. Cold horror shook my frame,</l>
<l n="tr">and every vein within me froze for fear.</l>
<l n="tr">Once more I tried from yet another stock</l>
<l n="tr">the pliant stem to tear, and to explore</l>
<l n="tr">the mystery within,—but yet again</l>
<l n="tr">the foul bark oozed with clots of blackest gore!</l>
<l n="tr">From my deep-shaken soul I made a prayer</l>
<l n="tr">to all the woodland nymphs and to divine</l>
<l n="tr">Gradivus, patron of the Thracian plain,</l>
<l n="tr">to bless this sight, to lift its curse away.</l>
<l n="tr">But when at a third sheaf of myrtle spears</l>
<l n="tr">I fell upon my knees, and tugged amain</l>
<l n="tr">against the adverse ground (I dread to tell!),</l>
<l n="tr">a moaning and a wail from that deep grave</l>
<l n="tr">burst forth and murmured in my listening ear:</l>
<l n="tr">“Why wound me, great Aeneas, in my woe?</l>
<l n="tr">O, spare the dead, nor let thy holy hands</l>
<l n="tr">do sacrilege and sin! I, Trojan-born,</l>
<l n="tr">was kin of thine. This blood is not of trees.</l>
<l n="tr">Haste from this murderous shore, this land of greed.</l>
<l n="tr">O, I am Polydorus! Haste away!</l>
<l n="tr">Here was I pierced; a crop of iron spears </l>
<l n="tr">has grown up o'er my breast, and multiplied </l>
<l n="tr">to all these deadly javelins, keen and strong.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then stood I, burdened with dark doubt and fear</l>
<l n="tr">I quailed, my hair rose and my utterance choked.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="49" unit="card" />For once this Polydorus, with much gold,</l>
<l n="tr">ill-fated Priam sent by stealth away</l>
<l n="tr">for nurture with the Thracian king, what time</l>
<l n="tr">Dardania's war Iooked hopeless, and her towers</l>
<l n="tr">were ringed about by unrelenting siege.</l>
<l n="tr">That king, when <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s cause was ebbing low,</l>
<l n="tr">and fortune frowned, gave o'er his plighted faith</l>
<l n="tr">to Agamemnon's might and victory;</l>
<l n="tr">he scorned all honor and did murder foul</l>
<l n="tr">on Polydorus, seizing lawlessly</l>
<l n="tr">on all the gold. O, whither at thy will,</l>
<l n="tr">curst greed of gold, may mortal hearts be driven?</l>
<l n="tr">Soon as my shuddering ceased, I told this tale</l>
<l n="tr">of prodigies before the people's chiefs,</l>
<l n="tr">who sat in conclave with my kingly sire,</l>
<l n="tr">and bade them speak their reverend counsel forth.</l>
<l n="tr">All found one voice; to leave that land of sin,</l>
<l n="tr">where foul abomination had profaned</l>
<l n="tr">a stranger's right; and once more to resign</l>
<l n="tr">our fleet unto the tempest and the wave.</l>
<l n="tr">But fit and solemn funeral rites were paid</l>
<l n="tr">to Polydorus. A high mound we reared</l>
<l n="tr">of heaped-up earth, and to his honored shade</l>
<l n="tr">built a perpetual altar, sadly dressed</l>
<l n="tr">in cypress dark and purple pall of woe.</l>
<l n="tr">Our Ilian women wailed with loosened hair;</l>
<l n="tr">new milk was sprinkled from a foaming cup,</l>
<l n="tr">and from the shallow bowl fresh blood out-poured</l>
<l n="tr">upon the sacred ground. So in its tomb</l>
<l n="tr">we laid his ghost to rest, and loudly sang,</l>
<l n="tr">with prayer for peace, the long, the last farewell.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="69" unit="card" />After these things, when first the friendly sea</l>
<l n="tr">looked safe and fair, and o'er its tranquil plain</l>
<l n="tr">light-whispering breezes bade us launch away,</l>
<l n="tr">my men drew down our galleys to the brine,</l>
<l n="tr">thronging the shore. Soon out of port we ran,</l>
<l n="tr">and watched the hills and cities fading far.</l>
<l n="tr">There is a sacred island in mid-seas,</l>
<l n="tr">to fruitful Doris and to Neptune dear,</l>
<l n="tr">which grateful Phoebus, wielder of the bow,</l>
<l n="tr">the while it drifted loose from land to land,</l>
<l n="tr">chained firmly where the crags of Gyaros</l>
<l n="tr">and Myconos uptower, and bade it rest</l>
<l n="tr">immovable, in scorn of wind and wave.</l>
<l n="tr">Thither I sped; by this my weary ships</l>
<l n="tr">found undisturbed retreat and haven fair.</l>
<l n="tr">To land we came and saw with reverent eyes</l>
<l n="tr">Apollo's citadel. King Anius,</l>
<l n="tr">his people's king, and priest at Phoebus' fane,</l>
<l n="tr">came forth to meet us, wearing on his brow</l>
<l n="tr">the fillets and a holy laurel crown.</l>
<l n="tr">Unto Anchises he gave greeting kind,</l>
<l n="tr">claimed old acquaintance, grasped us by the hand,</l>
<l n="tr">and bade us both his roof and welcome share.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="84" unit="card" />Then, kneeling at the shrine of time-worn stone:</l>
<l n="tr">“Thou who at Thymbra on the Trojan shore</l>
<l n="tr">hast often blessed my prayer, O, give to me</l>
<l n="tr">a hearth and home, and to this war-worn band</l>
<l n="tr">defensive towers and offspring multiplied</l>
<l n="tr">in an abiding city; give to <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">a second citadel, that shall survive</l>
<l n="tr">Achilles' wrath and all our <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> foe.</l>
<l n="tr">Whom shall we follow? Whither lies our way?</l>
<l n="tr">Where wilt thou grant us an abiding-place?</l>
<l n="tr">Send forth, O King, thy voice oracular,</l>
<l n="tr">and on our spirits move.” <milestone ed="p" n="90" unit="card" />Scarce had I spoke</l>
<l n="tr">when sudden trembling through the laurels ran</l>
<l n="tr">and smote the holy portals; far and wide</l>
<l n="tr">the mighty ridges of the mountain shook,</l>
<l n="tr">and from the opening shrine the tripod moaned.</l>
<l n="tr">Prostrate to earth we fall, as on our ears</l>
<l n="tr">this utterance breaks: “O breed of iron men,</l>
<l n="tr">ye sons of Dardanus! the self-same land</l>
<l n="tr">where bloomed at first your far-descended stem</l>
<l n="tr">shall to its bounteous bosom draw ye home.</l>
<l n="tr">Seek out your ancient Mother! There at last</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas' race shall reign on every shore,</l>
<l n="tr">and his sons' sons, and all their house to be.”</l>
<l n="tr">So Phoebus spoke; and mighty joy uprose</l>
<l n="tr">from all my thronging people, who would know</l>
<l n="tr">where Phoebus' city lay, and whitherward</l>
<l n="tr">the god ordained the wandering tribe's return.</l>
<l n="tr">Then spake my father, pondering olden days</l>
<l n="tr">and sacred memories of heroes gone:</l>
<l n="tr">“Hear, chiefs and princes, what your hopes shall be!</l>
<l n="tr">The Isle of <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, abode of lofty Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">rests in the middle sea. Thence Ida soars;</l>
<l n="tr">there is the cradle of our race. It boasts</l>
<l n="tr">a hundred cities, seats of fruitful power.</l>
<l n="tr">Thence our chief sire, if duly I recall</l>
<l n="tr">the olden tale, King Teucer sprung, who first</l>
<l n="tr">touched on the Trojan shore, and chose his seat</l>
<l n="tr">of kingly power. There was no <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> then</l>
<l n="tr">nor towered Pergama; in lowly vales</l>
<l n="tr">their dwelling; hence the ancient worship given</l>
<l n="tr">to the Protectress of Mount Cybele,</l>
<l n="tr">mother of Gods, what time in Ida's grove</l>
<l n="tr">the brazen Corybantic cymbals clang,</l>
<l n="tr">or sacred silence guards her mystery,</l>
<l n="tr">and lions yoked her royal chariot draw.</l>
<l n="tr">Up, then, and follow the behests divine!</l>
<l n="tr">Pour offering to the winds, and point your keels</l>
<l n="tr">unto that realm of Minos. It is near.</l>
<l n="tr">if Jove but bless, the third day's dawn should see</l>
<l n="tr">our ships at Cretan land.” So, having said,</l>
<l n="tr">he slew the victims for each altar's praise.</l>
<l n="tr">A bull to Neptune, and a bull to thee,</l>
<l n="tr">o beauteous Apollo! A black lamb</l>
<l n="tr">unto the clouds and storms; but fleece of snow</l>
<l n="tr">to the mild zephyrs was our offering.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="121" unit="card" />The tale was told us that Idomeneus,</l>
<l n="tr">from his hereditary kindgom driven,</l>
<l n="tr">had left his <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> abandoned, that no foe</l>
<l n="tr">now harbored there, but all its dwellings lay</l>
<l n="tr">untenanted of man. So forth we sailed</l>
<l n="tr">out of the port of <placeName key="perseus,Delos" authname="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>, and sped far</l>
<l n="tr">along the main. The maenad-haunted hills</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="perseus,Naxos City" authname="perseus,Naxos City">Naxos</placeName> came in view; the ridges green</l>
<l n="tr">of fair Donysa, with Olearos,</l>
<l n="tr">and <placeName key="perseus,Paros City" authname="perseus,Paros City">Paros</placeName>, gleaming white, and <placeName key="tgn,7011270" authname="tgn,7011270">Cyclades</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">scattered among the waves, as close we ran</l>
<l n="tr">where thick-strewn islands vex the channelled seas</l>
<l n="tr">with rival shout the sailors cheerly called:</l>
<l n="tr">“On, comrades! On, to <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> and to our sires!”</l>
<l n="tr">Freely behind us blew the friendly winds, </l>
<l n="tr">and gave smooth passage to that fabled shore,</l>
<l n="tr">the land of the Curetes, friends of Jove.</l>
<l n="tr">There eagerly I labored at the walls</l>
<l n="tr">of our long-prayed-for city; and its name</l>
<l n="tr">was Pergamea; to my Trojan band,</l>
<l n="tr">pleased with such name, I gave command to build</l>
<l n="tr">altar and hearth, and raise the lofty tower.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="135" unit="card" />But scarce the ships were beached along the strand</l>
<l n="tr">(While o'er the isle my busy mariners</l>
<l n="tr">ploughed in new fields and took them wives once more, —</l>
<l n="tr">I giving homes and laws) when suddenly</l>
<l n="tr">a pestilence from some infectious sky</l>
<l n="tr">seized on man's flesh, and horribly exhaled</l>
<l n="tr">o'er trees and crops a fatal year of plague.</l>
<l n="tr">Some breathed their last, while others weak and worn</l>
<l n="tr">lived on; the dog-star parched the barren fields;</l>
<l n="tr">grass withered, and the sickly, mouldering corn</l>
<l n="tr">refused us life. My aged father then</l>
<l n="tr">bade us re-cross the waves and re-implore</l>
<l n="tr">Apollo's mercy at his island shrine;</l>
<l n="tr">if haply of our weariness and woe</l>
<l n="tr">he might vouchsafe the end, or bid us find</l>
<l n="tr">help for our task, or guidance o'er the sea.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="147" unit="card" />'T was night, and sleep possessed all breathing things;</l>
<l n="tr">when, lo! the sacred effigies divine,</l>
<l n="tr">the Phrygian gods which through the flames I bore</l>
<l n="tr">from fallen <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, seemed in a vision clear</l>
<l n="tr">to stand before me where I slumbering lay,</l>
<l n="tr">bathed in bright beams which from the moon at full</l>
<l n="tr">streamed through the latticed wall: and thus they spoke</l>
<l n="tr">to soothe my care away. “Apollo's word,</l>
<l n="tr">which in far <placeName key="perseus,Delos" authname="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> the god meant for thee,</l>
<l n="tr">is uttered here. Behold, he sends ourselves</l>
<l n="tr">to this thy house, before thy prayer is made.</l>
<l n="tr">We from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s ashes have companioned thee</l>
<l n="tr">in every fight; and we the swollen seas,</l>
<l n="tr">guided by thee, in thine own ships have crossed;</l>
<l n="tr">our power divine shall set among the stars</l>
<l n="tr">thy seed to be, and to thy city give</l>
<l n="tr">dominion evermore. For mighty men</l>
<l n="tr">go build its mighty walls! Seek not to shun</l>
<l n="tr">the hard, long labors of an exile's way.</l>
<l n="tr">Change this abode! Not thine this Cretan shore,</l>
<l n="tr">nor here would Delian Phoebus have thee bide.</l>
<l n="tr">There is a land the roving Greeks have named</l>
<l n="tr">Hesperia. It is a storied realm</l>
<l n="tr">made mighty by great wars and fruitful land.</l>
<l n="tr">Oenotrians had it, and their sons, 't is said,</l>
<l n="tr">have called it <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, a chieftain's name</l>
<l n="tr">to a whole region given. That land alone</l>
<l n="tr">our true abode can be; for Dardanus</l>
<l n="tr">was cradled there, and old Iasius,</l>
<l n="tr">their blood the oldest of our ancient line.</l>
<l n="tr">Arise! go forth and cheer thy father gray</l>
<l n="tr">with the glad tidings! Bid him doubt no more!</l>
<l n="tr">Ausonia seek and Corythus; for Jove</l>
<l n="tr">denies this Cretan realm to thine and thee.”</l>
<l n="tr">I marvelled at the heavenly presences</l>
<l n="tr">so vocal and so bright, for 't was not sleep;</l>
<l n="tr">but face to face I deemed I could discern</l>
<l n="tr">each countenance august and holy brow,</l>
<l n="tr">each mantled head; and from my body ran</l>
<l n="tr">cold sweat of awe. From my low couch I sprang,</l>
<l n="tr">lifting to heaven my suppliant hands and prayer,</l>
<l n="tr">and o'er my hearth poured forth libations free.</l>
<l n="tr">After th' auspicious offering, I told</l>
<l n="tr">Anchises the whole tale in order due.</l>
<l n="tr">He owned our stock two-branched, of our great sires</l>
<l n="tr">the twofold line, and that his thought had strayed,</l>
<l n="tr">in new confusion mingling ancient names;</l>
<l n="tr">then spoke: “O son, in <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s doom severe</l>
<l n="tr">afflicted ever! To my ears alone</l>
<l n="tr">this dark vicissitude Cassandra sang.</l>
<l n="tr">I mind me now that her wild tongue foretold</l>
<l n="tr">such destiny. For oft she called aloud</l>
<l n="tr">‘Hesperia!’ oft ‘<placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italia</placeName>'s kingdom!’ called.</l>
<l n="tr">But who had faith that Teucer's sons should come</l>
<l n="tr">to far Hesperia? What mortal ear</l>
<l n="tr">gave heed to sad Cassandra's voice divine?</l>
<l n="tr">Now Phoebus speaks. Obedient let us be,</l>
<l n="tr">and, warned by him, our happier Iot pursue!”</l>
<l n="tr">He spoke: with heart of hope we all obeyed;</l>
<l n="tr">again we changed abode; and, leaving there</l>
<l n="tr">a feeble few, again with spreading sails</l>
<l n="tr">we coursed in hollow ship the spacious sea.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="192" unit="card" />When from the deep the shores had faded far,</l>
<l n="tr">and only sky and sea were round our way,</l>
<l n="tr">full in the zenith hung a purple cloud,</l>
<l n="tr">storm-laden, dark as night, and every wave</l>
<l n="tr">grew black and angry, while perpetual gales</l>
<l n="tr">came rolling o'er the main, and mountain-high</l>
<l n="tr">the wreckful surges rose; our ships were hurled</l>
<l n="tr">wide o'er the whirling waters; thunder-clouds</l>
<l n="tr">and misty murk of night made end of all</l>
<l n="tr">the light of heaven, save where the rifted storm</l>
<l n="tr">flashed with the oft-reiterate shaft of Jove.</l>
<l n="tr">Then went we drifting, beaten from our course,</l>
<l n="tr">upon a trackless sea. Not even the eyes</l>
<l n="tr">of Palinurus could tell night from noon</l>
<l n="tr">or ken our way. Three days of blinding dark,</l>
<l n="tr">three nights without a star, we roved the seas;</l>
<l n="tr">The fourth, land seemed to rise. Far distant hills</l>
<l n="tr">and rolling smoke we saw. Down came our sails,</l>
<l n="tr">out flew the oars, and with prompt stroke the crews</l>
<l n="tr">swept the dark waves and tossed the crested foam.</l>
<l n="tr">From such sea-peril safe, I made the shores</l>
<l n="tr">of Strophades,—a name the Grecians gave</l>
<l n="tr">to islands in the broad Ionic main, —</l>
<l n="tr">the Strophades, where dread Celaeno bides,</l>
<l n="tr">with other Harpies, who had quit the halls</l>
<l n="tr">of stricken Phineus, and for very fear</l>
<l n="tr">fled from the routed feast; no prodigy</l>
<l n="tr">more vile than these, nor plague more pitiless</l>
<l n="tr">ere rose by wrath divine from Stygian wave;</l>
<l n="tr">birds seem they, but with face like woman-kind;</l>
<l n="tr">foul-flowing bellies, hands with crooked claws,</l>
<l n="tr">and ghastly lips they have, with hunger pale.</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce had we made the haven, when, behold!</l>
<l n="tr">Fair herds of cattle roaming a wide plain,</l>
<l n="tr">and horned goats, untended, feeding free</l>
<l n="tr">in pastures green, surprised our happy eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">with eager blades we ran to take and slay,</l>
<l n="tr">asking of every god, and chicfly Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">to share the welcome prize: we ranged a feast,</l>
<l n="tr">with turf-built couches and a banquet-board</l>
<l n="tr">along the curving strand. But in a trice,</l>
<l n="tr">down from the high hills swooping horribly,</l>
<l n="tr">the Harpies loudly shrieking, flapped their wings,</l>
<l n="tr">snatched at our meats, and with infectious touch</l>
<l n="tr">polluted all; infernal was their cry,</l>
<l n="tr">the stench most vile. Once more in covert far</l>
<l n="tr">beneath a caverned rock, and close concealed</l>
<l n="tr">with trees and branching shade, we raised aloft</l>
<l n="tr">our tables, altars, and rekindled fires.</l>
<l n="tr">Once more from haunts unknown the clamorous flock</l>
<l n="tr">from every quarter flew, and seized its prey</l>
<l n="tr">with taloned feet and carrion lip most foul.</l>
<l n="tr">I called my mates to arms and opened war</l>
<l n="tr">on that accursed brood. My band obeyed;</l>
<l n="tr">and, hiding in deep grass their swords and shields,</l>
<l n="tr">in ambush lay. But presently the foe</l>
<l n="tr">swept o'er the winding shore with loud alarm :</l>
<l n="tr">then from a sentry-crag, Misenus blew</l>
<l n="tr">a signal on his hollow horn. My men</l>
<l n="tr">flew to the combat strange, and fain would wound</l>
<l n="tr">with martial steel those foul birds of the sea;</l>
<l n="tr">but on their sides no wounding blade could fall,</l>
<l n="tr">nor any plume be marred. In swiftest flight</l>
<l n="tr">to starry skies they soared, and left on earth</l>
<l n="tr">their half-gnawed, stolen feast, and footprints foul.</l>
<l n="tr">Celaeno only on a beetling crag</l>
<l n="tr">took lofty perch, and, prophetess of ill,</l>
<l n="tr">shrieked malediction from her vulture breast:</l>
<l n="tr">“Because of slaughtered kine and ravished herd,</l>
<l n="tr">sons of Laomedon, have ye made war?</l>
<l n="tr">And will ye from their rightful kingdom drive</l>
<l n="tr">the guiltless Harpies? Hear, O, hear my word</l>
<l n="tr">(Long in your bosoms may it rankle sore!)</l>
<l n="tr">which Jove omnipotent to Phoebus gave,</l>
<l n="tr">Phoebus to me: a word of doom, which I,</l>
<l n="tr">the Furies' elder sister, here unfold:</l>
<l n="tr">‘To <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> ye fare. The willing winds</l>
<l n="tr">your call have heard; and ye shall have your prayer</l>
<l n="tr">in some Italian haven safely moored.</l>
<l n="tr">But never shall ye rear the circling walls</l>
<l n="tr">of your own city, till for this our blood</l>
<l n="tr">by you unjustly spilt, your famished jaws</l>
<l n="tr">bite at your tables, aye,—and half devour.’”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="258" unit="card" />She spoke: her pinions bore her to the grove,</l>
<l n="tr">and she was seen no more. But all my band</l>
<l n="tr">shuddered with shock of fear in each cold vein;</l>
<l n="tr">their drooping spirits trusted swords no more,</l>
<l n="tr">but turned to prayers and offerings, asking grace,</l>
<l n="tr">scarce knowing if those creatures were divine,</l>
<l n="tr">or but vast birds, ill-omened and unclean.</l>
<l n="tr">Father Anchises to the gods in heaven</l>
<l n="tr">uplifted suppliant hands, and on that shore</l>
<l n="tr">due ritual made, crying aloud; “Ye gods</l>
<l n="tr">avert this curse, this evil turn away!</l>
<l n="tr">Smile, Heaven, upon your faithful votaries.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then bade he launch away, the chain undo,</l>
<l n="tr">set every cable free and spread all sail.</l>
<l n="tr">O'er the white waves we flew, and took our way</l>
<l n="tr">where'er the helmsman or the winds could guide.</l>
<l n="tr">Now forest-clad <placeName key="tgn,7011374" authname="tgn,7011374">Zacynthus</placeName> met our gaze,</l>
<l n="tr">engirdled by the waves; Dulichium,</l>
<l n="tr">same, and Neritos, a rocky steep,</l>
<l n="tr">uprose. We passed the cliffs of <placeName key="tgn,1007519" authname="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">that called <placeName key="perseus,Laertes" authname="perseus,Laertes">Laertes</placeName> king, and flung our curse</l>
<l n="tr">on fierce Ulysses' hearth and native land.</l>
<l n="tr">nigh hoar Leucate's clouded crest we drew,</l>
<l n="tr">where Phoebus' temple, feared by mariners,</l>
<l n="tr">loomed o'er us; thitherward we steered and reached</l>
<l n="tr">the little port and town. Our weary fleet</l>
<l n="tr">dropped anchor, and lay beached along the strand.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="278" unit="card" />So, safe at land, our hopeless peril past,</l>
<l n="tr">we offered thanks to Jove, and kindled high</l>
<l n="tr">his altars with our feast and sacrifice;</l>
<l n="tr">then, gathering on <placeName key="perseus,Actium,Acarnania" authname="perseus,Actium,Acarnania">Actium</placeName>'s holy shore,</l>
<l n="tr">made fair solemnities of pomp and game.</l>
<l n="tr">My youth, anointing their smooth, naked limbs,</l>
<l n="tr">wrestled our wonted way. For glad were we,</l>
<l n="tr">who past so many isles of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> had sped</l>
<l n="tr">and 'scaped our circling foes. Now had the sun</l>
<l n="tr">rolled through the year's full circle, and the waves</l>
<l n="tr">were rough with icy winter's northern gales.</l>
<l n="tr">I hung for trophy on that temple door</l>
<l n="tr">a swelling shield of brass (which once was worn</l>
<l n="tr">by mighty Abas) graven with this line:</l>
<l n="tr">SPOIL OF AENEAS FROM TRIUMPHANT FOES.</l>
<l n="tr">Then from that haven I command them forth;</l>
<l n="tr">my good crews take the thwarts, smiting the sea</l>
<l n="tr">with rival strokes, and skim the level main.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon sank Phaeacia's wind-swept citadels</l>
<l n="tr">out of our view; we skirted the bold shores</l>
<l n="tr">of proud <placeName key="tgn,7002705" authname="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName>, in Chaonian land,</l>
<l n="tr">and made <placeName key="perseus,Buthrotum" authname="perseus,Buthrotum">Buthrotum</placeName>'s port and towering town.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="294" unit="card" />Here wondrous tidings met us, that the son</l>
<l n="tr">of Priam, Helenus, held kingly sway</l>
<l n="tr">o'er many <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> cities, having wed</l>
<l n="tr">the Queen of Pyrrhus, great Achilles' son,</l>
<l n="tr">and gained his throne; and that Andromache</l>
<l n="tr">once more was wife unto a kindred lord.</l>
<l n="tr">Amazement held me; all my bosom burned</l>
<l n="tr">to see the hero's face and hear this tale</l>
<l n="tr">of strange vicissitude. So up I climbed,</l>
<l n="tr">leaving the haven, fleet, and friendly shore.</l>
<l n="tr">That self-same hour outside the city walls,</l>
<l n="tr">within a grove where flowed the mimic stream</l>
<l n="tr">of a new Simois, Andromache,</l>
<l n="tr">with offerings to the dead, and gifts of woe,</l>
<l n="tr">poured forth libation, and invoked the shade</l>
<l n="tr">of Hector, at a tomb which her fond grief</l>
<l n="tr">had consecrated to perpetual tears,</l>
<l n="tr">though void; a mound of fair green turf it stood,</l>
<l n="tr">and near it rose twin altars to his name.</l>
<l n="tr">She saw me drawing near; our Trojan helms</l>
<l n="tr">met her bewildered eyes, and, terror-struck</l>
<l n="tr">at the portentous sight, she swooning fell</l>
<l n="tr">and lay cold, rigid, lifeless, till at last,</l>
<l n="tr">scarce finding voice, her lips addressed me thus :</l>
<l n="tr">“Have I true vision? Bringest thou the word</l>
<l n="tr">Of truth, O goddess-born? Art still in flesh?</l>
<l n="tr">Or if sweet light be fled, my Hector, where?”</l>
<l n="tr">With flood of tears she spoke, and all the grove</l>
<l n="tr">reechoed to her cry. Scarce could I frame</l>
<l n="tr">brief answer to her passion, but replied</l>
<l n="tr">with broken voice and accents faltering:</l>
<l n="tr">“I live, 't is true. I lengthen out my days</l>
<l n="tr">through many a desperate strait. But O, believe</l>
<l n="tr">that what thine eyes behold is vision true.</l>
<l n="tr">Alas! what lot is thine, that wert unthroned</l>
<l n="tr">from such a husband's side? What after-fate</l>
<l n="tr">could give thee honor due? Andromache,</l>
<l n="tr">once Hector's wife, is Pyrrhus still thy lord?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="320" unit="card" />With drooping brows and lowly voice she cried :</l>
<l n="tr">“O, happy only was that virgin blest,</l>
<l n="tr">daughter of Priam, summoned forth to die</l>
<l n="tr">in sight of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>, on a foeman's tomb!</l>
<l n="tr">No casting of the lot her doom decreed,</l>
<l n="tr">nor came she to her conqueror's couch a slave.</l>
<l n="tr">Myself from burning <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> carried far</l>
<l n="tr">o'er seas and seas, endured the swollen pride</l>
<l n="tr">of that young scion of Achilles' race,</l>
<l n="tr">and bore him as his slave a son. When he</l>
<l n="tr">sued for Hermione, of Leda's line,</l>
<l n="tr">and nuptial-bond with Lacedaemon's Iords,</l>
<l n="tr">I, the slave-wife, to Helenus was given,</l>
<l n="tr">and slave was wed with slave. But afterward</l>
<l n="tr">Orestes, crazed by loss of her he loved,</l>
<l n="tr">and ever fury-driven from crime to crime,</l>
<l n="tr">crept upon Pyrrhus in a careless hour</l>
<l n="tr">and murdered him upon his own hearth-stone.</l>
<l n="tr">Part of the realm of Neoptolemus</l>
<l n="tr">fell thus to Helenus, who called his lands</l>
<l n="tr">Chaonian, and in Trojan Chaon's name</l>
<l n="tr">his kingdom is Chaonia. Yonder height</l>
<l n="tr">is <placeName key="perseus,Pergamon" authname="perseus,Pergamon">Pergamus</placeName>, our Ilian citadel.</l>
<l n="tr">What power divine did waft thee to our shore,</l>
<l n="tr">not knowing whither? Tell me of the boy</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius! Still breathes he earthly air?</l>
<l n="tr">In <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> she bore him—is he mourning still</l>
<l n="tr">that mother ravished from his childhood's eyes?</l>
<l n="tr">what ancient valor stirs the manly soul</l>
<l n="tr">of thine own son, of Hector's sister's child?”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus poured she forth full many a doleful word</l>
<l n="tr">with unavailing tears. But as she ceased,</l>
<l n="tr">out of the city gates appeared the son</l>
<l n="tr">of Priam, Helenus, with princely train.</l>
<l n="tr">He welcomed us as kin, and glad at heart</l>
<l n="tr">gave guidance to his house, though oft his words</l>
<l n="tr">fell faltering and few, with many a tear.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon to a humbler <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> I lift my eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">and of a mightier <placeName key="perseus,Pergamon" authname="perseus,Pergamon">Pergamus</placeName> discern</l>
<l n="tr">the towering semblance; there a scanty stream</l>
<l n="tr">runs on in <placeName key="perseus,Xanthos" authname="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName>' name, and my glad arms</l>
<l n="tr">the pillars of a Scaean gate embrace.</l>
<l n="tr">My Teucrian mariners with welcome free</l>
<l n="tr">enjoyed the friendly town; his ample halls</l>
<l n="tr">our royal host threw wide; full wine-cups flowed</l>
<l n="tr">within the palace; golden feast was spread,</l>
<l n="tr">and many a goblet quaffed. <milestone ed="p" n="356" unit="card" />Day followed day,</l>
<l n="tr">while favoring breezes beckoned us to sea,</l>
<l n="tr">and swelled the waiting canvas as they blew.</l>
<l n="tr">Then to the prophet-priest I made this prayer:</l>
<l n="tr">“Offspring of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, interpreter of Heaven!</l>
<l n="tr">Who knowest Phoebus' power, and readest well</l>
<l n="tr">the tripod, stars, and vocal laurel leaves</l>
<l n="tr">to Phoebus dear, who know'st of every bird</l>
<l n="tr">the ominous swift wing or boding song,</l>
<l n="tr">o, speak! For all my course good omens showed,</l>
<l n="tr">and every god admonished me to sail</l>
<l n="tr">in quest of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>'s far-distant shores;</l>
<l n="tr">but lone Celaeno, heralding strange woe,</l>
<l n="tr">foretold prodigious horror, vengeance dark,</l>
<l n="tr">and vile, unnatural hunger. How elude</l>
<l n="tr">such perils? Or by what hard duty done</l>
<l n="tr">may such huge host of evils vanquished be?”</l>
<l n="tr">Then Helenus, with sacrifice of kine</l>
<l n="tr">in order due, implored the grace of Heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">unloosed the fillets from his sacred brow,</l>
<l n="tr">and led me, Phoebus, to thy temple's door,</l>
<l n="tr">awed by th' o'er-brooding godhead, whose true priest,</l>
<l n="tr">with lips inspired, made this prophetic song:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="374" unit="card" />“O goddess-born, indubitably shines</l>
<l n="tr">the blessing of great gods upon thy path</l>
<l n="tr">across the sea; the heavenly King supreme</l>
<l n="tr">thy destiny ordains; 't is he unfolds</l>
<l n="tr">the grand vicissitude, which now pursues</l>
<l n="tr">a course immutable. I will declare</l>
<l n="tr">of thy large fate a certain bounded part;</l>
<l n="tr">that fearless thou may'st view the friendly sea,</l>
<l n="tr">and in Ausonia's haven at the last</l>
<l n="tr">find thee a fixed abode. Than this no more</l>
<l n="tr">the Sister Fates to Helenus unveil,</l>
<l n="tr">and Juno, Saturn's daughter, grants no more.</l>
<l n="tr">First, that <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italia</placeName> (which nigh at hand</l>
<l n="tr">thou deemest, and wouldst fondly enter in</l>
<l n="tr">by yonder neighboring bays) lies distant far</l>
<l n="tr">o'er trackless course and long, with interval</l>
<l n="tr">of far-extended lands. Thine oars must ply</l>
<l n="tr">the waves of <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>; thy fleet must cleave</l>
<l n="tr">the large expanse of that Ausonian brine;</l>
<l n="tr">the waters of Avernus thou shalt see,</l>
<l n="tr">and that enchanted island where abides</l>
<l n="tr">Aeaean Circe, ere on tranquil shore</l>
<l n="tr">thou mayest plant thy nation. Lo! a sign</l>
<l n="tr">I tell thee; hide this wonder in thy heart:</l>
<l n="tr">Beside a certain stream's sequestered wave,</l>
<l n="tr">thy troubled eyes, in shadowy flex grove</l>
<l n="tr">that fringes on the river, shall descry</l>
<l n="tr">a milk-white, monstrous sow, with teeming brood</l>
<l n="tr">of thirty young, new littered, white like her,</l>
<l n="tr">all clustering at her teats, as prone she lies.</l>
<l n="tr">There is thy city's safe, predestined ground,</l>
<l n="tr">and there thy labors' end. Vex not thy heart</l>
<l n="tr">about those ‘tables bitten’, for kind fate</l>
<l n="tr">thy path will show, and Phoebus bless thy prayer.</l>
<l n="tr">But from these lands and yon Italian shore,</l>
<l n="tr">where from this sea of ours the tide sweeps in,</l>
<l n="tr">escape and flee, for all its cities hold</l>
<l n="tr">pernicious Greeks, thy foes: the <placeName key="perseus,Locri" authname="perseus,Locri">Locri</placeName> there</l>
<l n="tr">have builded walls; the wide Sallentine fields</l>
<l n="tr">are filled with soldiers of Idomeneus;</l>
<l n="tr">there Meliboean Philoctetes' town,</l>
<l n="tr">petilia, towers above its little wall.</l>
<l n="tr">Yea, even when thy fleet has crossed the main,</l>
<l n="tr">and from new altars built along the shore</l>
<l n="tr">thy vows to Heaven are paid, throw o'er thy head</l>
<l n="tr">a purple mantle, veiling well thy brows,</l>
<l n="tr">lest, while the sacrificial fire ascends</l>
<l n="tr">in offering to the gods, thine eye behold</l>
<l n="tr">some face of foe, and every omen fail.</l>
<l n="tr">Let all thy people keep this custom due,</l>
<l n="tr">and thou thyself be faithful; let thy seed</l>
<l n="tr">forever thus th' immaculate rite maintain.</l>
<l n="tr">After departing hence, thou shalt be blown</l>
<l n="tr">toward <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, and strait Pelorus' bounds</l>
<l n="tr">will open wide. Then take the leftward way:</l>
<l n="tr">those leftward waters in long circuit sweep,</l>
<l n="tr">far from that billowy coast, the opposing side.</l>
<l n="tr">These regions, so they tell, in ages gone</l>
<l n="tr">by huge and violent convulsion riven</l>
<l n="tr">(Such mutability is wrought by time),</l>
<l n="tr">sprang wide asunder; where the doubled strand</l>
<l n="tr">sole and continuous lay, the sea's vast power</l>
<l n="tr">burst in between, and bade its waves divide</l>
<l n="tr">Hesperia's bosom from fair <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">while with a straitened firth it interflowed</l>
<l n="tr">their fields and cities sundered shore from shore.</l>
<l n="tr">The right side Scylla keeps; the left is given</l>
<l n="tr">to pitiless Charybdis, who draws down</l>
<l n="tr">to the wild whirling of her steep abyss</l>
<l n="tr">the monster waves, and ever and anon</l>
<l n="tr">flings them at heaven, to lash the tranquil stars.</l>
<l n="tr">But Scylla, prisoned in her eyeless cave,</l>
<l n="tr">thrusts forth her face, and pulls upon the rocks</l>
<l n="tr">ship after ship; the parts that first be seen</l>
<l n="tr">are human; a fair-breasted virgin she,</l>
<l n="tr">down to the womb; but all that lurks below</l>
<l n="tr">is a huge-membered fish, where strangely join</l>
<l n="tr">the flukes of dolphins and the paunch of wolves.</l>
<l n="tr">Better by far to round the distant goal</l>
<l n="tr">of the Trinacrian headlands, veering wide</l>
<l n="tr">from thy true course, than ever thou shouldst see</l>
<l n="tr">that shapeless Scylla in her vaulted cave,</l>
<l n="tr">where grim rocks echo her dark sea-dogs' roar.</l>
<l n="tr">Yea, more, if aught of prescience be bestowed</l>
<l n="tr">on Helenus, if trusted prophet he,</l>
<l n="tr">and Phoebus to his heart true voice have given,</l>
<l n="tr">o goddess-born, one counsel chief of all</l>
<l n="tr">I tell thee oft, and urge it o'er and o'er.</l>
<l n="tr">To Juno's godhead lift thy Ioudest prayer;</l>
<l n="tr">to Juno chant a fervent votive song,</l>
<l n="tr">and with obedient offering persuade</l>
<l n="tr">that potent Queen. So shalt thou, triumphing,</l>
<l n="tr">to <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> be sped, and leave behind</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Trinacria</placeName>.<milestone ed="p" n="441" unit="card" />When wafted to that shore,</l>
<l n="tr">repair to <placeName key="perseus,Cumae" authname="perseus,Cumae">Cumae</placeName>'s hill, and to the Lake</l>
<l n="tr">Avernus with its whispering grove divine.</l>
<l n="tr">There shalt thou see a frenzied prophetess,</l>
<l n="tr">who from beneath the hollow scarped crag</l>
<l n="tr">sings oracles, or characters on leaves</l>
<l n="tr">mysterious names. Whate'er the virgin writes,</l>
<l n="tr">on leaves inscribing the portentous song,</l>
<l n="tr">she sets in order, and conceals them well</l>
<l n="tr">in her deep cave, where they abide unchanged</l>
<l n="tr">in due array. Yet not a care has she,</l>
<l n="tr">if with some swinging hinge a breeze sweeps in,</l>
<l n="tr">to catch them as they whirl: if open door</l>
<l n="tr">disperse them flutterlig through the hollow rock,</l>
<l n="tr">she will not link their shifted sense anew,</l>
<l n="tr">nor re-invent her fragmentary song.</l>
<l n="tr">Oft her unanswered votaries depart,</l>
<l n="tr">scorning the Sibyl's shrine. But deem not thou</l>
<l n="tr">thy tarrying too Iong, whate'er thy stay.</l>
<l n="tr">Though thy companions chide, though winds of power</l>
<l n="tr">invite thy ship to sea, and well would speed</l>
<l n="tr">the swelling sail, yet to that Sibyl go.</l>
<l n="tr">Pray that her own lips may sing forth for thee</l>
<l n="tr">the oracles, uplifting her dread voice</l>
<l n="tr">in willing prophecy. Her rede shall tell</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, its wars and tribes to be,</l>
<l n="tr">and of what way each burden and each woe</l>
<l n="tr">may be escaped, or borne. Her favoring aid</l>
<l n="tr">will grant swift, happy voyages to thy prayer.</l>
<l n="tr">Such counsels Heaven to my lips allows.</l>
<l n="tr">arise, begone! and by thy glorious deeds</l>
<l n="tr">set <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> among the stars! “</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="463" unit="card" />So spake the prophet with benignant voice.</l>
<l n="tr">Then gifts he bade be brought of heavy gold</l>
<l n="tr">and graven ivory, which to our ships</l>
<l n="tr">he bade us bear; each bark was Ioaded full</l>
<l n="tr">with messy silver and <placeName key="perseus,Dodona" authname="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName>'s pride</l>
<l n="tr">of brazen cauldrons; a cuirass he gave</l>
<l n="tr">of linked gold enwrought and triple chain;</l>
<l n="tr">a noble helmet, too, with flaming crest</l>
<l n="tr">and lofty cone, th' accoutrement erewhile</l>
<l n="tr">of Neoptolemus. My father too</l>
<l n="tr">had fit gifts from the King; whose bounty then</l>
<l n="tr">gave steeds and riders; and new gear was sent</l>
<l n="tr">to every sea-worn ship, while he supplied</l>
<l n="tr">seafarers, kit to all my loyal crews.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="472" unit="card" />Anchises bade us speedily set sail,</l>
<l n="tr">nor lose a wind so fair; and answering him,</l>
<l n="tr">Apollo's priest made reverent adieu:</l>
<l n="tr">“Anchises, honored by the love sublime</l>
<l n="tr">of Venus, self and twice in safety borne</l>
<l n="tr">from falling <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, chief care of kindly Heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">th' Ausonian shore is thine. Sail thitherward!</l>
<l n="tr">For thou art pre-ordained to travel far</l>
<l n="tr">o'er yonder seas; far in the distance lies</l>
<l n="tr">that region of Ausonia, Phoebus' voice</l>
<l n="tr">to thee made promise of. Onward, I say,</l>
<l n="tr">o blest in the exceeding loyal love</l>
<l n="tr">of thy dear son! Why keep thee longer now?</l>
<l n="tr">Why should my words yon gathering winds detain?”</l>
<l n="tr">Likewise Andromache in mournful guise</l>
<l n="tr">took last farewell, bringing embroidered robes</l>
<l n="tr">of golden woof; a princely Phrygian cloak</l>
<l n="tr">she gave Ascanius, vying with the King</l>
<l n="tr">in gifts of honor; and threw o'er the boy</l>
<l n="tr">the labors of her loom, with words like these:</l>
<l n="tr">“Accept these gifts, sweet youth, memorials</l>
<l n="tr">of me and my poor handicraft, to prove</l>
<l n="tr">th' undying friendship of Andromache,</l>
<l n="tr">once Hector's wife. Take these last offerings</l>
<l n="tr">of those who are thy kin—O thou that art</l>
<l n="tr">of my Astyanax in all this world</l>
<l n="tr">the only image! His thy lovely eyes!</l>
<l n="tr">Thy hands, thy lips, are even what he bore,</l>
<l n="tr">and like thy own his youthful bloom would be.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus I made answer, turning to depart</l>
<l n="tr">with rising tears: “Live on, and be ye blessed,</l>
<l n="tr">whose greatness is accomplished! As for me,</l>
<l n="tr">from change to change Fate summons, and I go;</l>
<l n="tr">but ye have won repose. No leagues of sea</l>
<l n="tr">await your cleaving keel. Not yours the quest</l>
<l n="tr">of fading <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>'s delusive shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Here a new <placeName key="perseus,Xanthos" authname="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName> and a second <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">your labor fashioned and your eyes may see—</l>
<l n="tr">more blest, I trust, less tempting to our foes!</l>
<l n="tr">If e'er on <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> and its bordering vales</l>
<l n="tr">I safely enter, and these eyes behold</l>
<l n="tr">our destined walls, then in fraternal bond</l>
<l n="tr">let our two nations live, whose mutual boast</l>
<l n="tr">is one Dardanian blood, one common story.</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,7002705" authname="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName> with Hesperia shall be</l>
<l n="tr">one <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> in heart and soul. But this remains</l>
<l n="tr">for our sons' sons the happy task and care.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="506" unit="card" />Forth o'er the seas we sped and kept our course</l>
<l n="tr">nigh the Ceraunian headland, where begins</l>
<l n="tr">the short sea-passage unto <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon sank the sun, while down the shadowed hills</l>
<l n="tr">stole deeper gloom; then making shore, we flung</l>
<l n="tr">our bodies on a dry, sea-bordering sand,</l>
<l n="tr">couched on earth's welcome breast; the oars were ranged</l>
<l n="tr">in order due; the tides of slumber dark</l>
<l n="tr">o'erflowed our lives. But scarce the chariot</l>
<l n="tr">of Night, on wings of swift, obedient Hours,</l>
<l n="tr">had touched the middle sky, when wakeful sprang</l>
<l n="tr">good Palinurus from his pillowed stone:</l>
<l n="tr">with hand at ear he caught each airy gust</l>
<l n="tr">and questioned of the winds; the gliding stars</l>
<l n="tr">he called by name, as onward they advanced</l>
<l n="tr">through the still heaven; Arcturus he beheld,</l>
<l n="tr">the Hyades, rain-bringers, the twin Bears,</l>
<l n="tr">and vast Orion girt in golden arms.</l>
<l n="tr">He blew a trumpet from his ship; our camp</l>
<l n="tr">stirred to the signal for embarking; soon</l>
<l n="tr">we rode the seas once more with swelling sail.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="521" unit="card" />Scarce had Aurora's purple from the sky</l>
<l n="tr">warned off the stars, when Iying very low</l>
<l n="tr">along th' horizon, the dimmed hills we saw</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; Achates first gave cry</l>
<l n="tr">“<placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italia</placeName>!” with answering shouts of joy,</l>
<l n="tr">my comrades' voices cried, “<placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italia</placeName>, hail!”</l>
<l n="tr">Anchises, then, wreathed a great bowl with flowers</l>
<l n="tr">and filled with wine, invoking Heaven to bless,</l>
<l n="tr">and thus he prayed from our ship's lofty stern:</l>
<l n="tr">“O Iords of land and sea and every storm!</l>
<l n="tr">Breathe favoring breezes for our onward way!”</l>
<l n="tr">Fresh blew the prayed-for winds. A haven fair</l>
<l n="tr">soon widened near us; and its heights were crowned</l>
<l n="tr">by a Greek fane to Pallas. Yet my men</l>
<l n="tr">furled sail and shoreward veered the pointing prow.</l>
<l n="tr">the port receding from the orient wave</l>
<l n="tr">is curved into a bow; on either side</l>
<l n="tr">the jutting headlands toss the salt sea-foam</l>
<l n="tr">and hide the bay itself. Like double wall</l>
<l n="tr">the towered crags send down protecting arms,</l>
<l n="tr">while distant from the shore the temple stands.</l>
<l n="tr">Here on a green sward, the first omen given,</l>
<l n="tr">I saw four horses grazing through the field,</l>
<l n="tr">each white as snow. Father Anchises cried:</l>
<l n="tr">“Is war thy gift, O new and alien land?</l>
<l n="tr">Horses make war; of war these creatures bode.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet oft before the chariot of peace</l>
<l n="tr">their swift hoofs go, and on their necks they bear</l>
<l n="tr">th' obedient yoke and rein. Therefore a hope</l>
<l n="tr">of peace is also ours.” Then we implored</l>
<l n="tr">Minerva's mercy, at her sacred shrine,</l>
<l n="tr">the mail-clad goddess who gave welcome there;</l>
<l n="tr">and at an altar, mantling well our brows</l>
<l n="tr">the Phrygian way, as Helenus ordained,</l>
<l n="tr">we paid the honors his chief counsel urged,</l>
<l n="tr">with blameless rite, to Juno, Argive Queen.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="548" unit="card" />No tarrying now, but after sacrifice</l>
<l n="tr">we twirled the sailyards and shook out all sail,</l>
<l n="tr">leaving the cities of the sons of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">and that distrusted land. <placeName key="tgn,7004100" authname="tgn,7004100">Tarentum</placeName>'s bay</l>
<l n="tr">soon smiled before us, town of Hercules,</l>
<l n="tr">if fame be true; opposing it uptowers</l>
<l n="tr">Lacinia's headland unto Juno dear,</l>
<l n="tr">the heights of Caulon, and that sailors' bane,</l>
<l n="tr">ship-shattering Scylaceum. Thence half seen,</l>
<l n="tr">trinacrian <placeName key="tgn,7003867" authname="tgn,7003867">Aetna</placeName> cleaves th' horizon line;</l>
<l n="tr">we hear from far the crash of shouting seas,</l>
<l n="tr">where lifted billows leap the tide-swept sand.</l>
<l n="tr">Father Anchises cried: “'T is none but she—</l>
<l n="tr">Charybdis! Helenus this reef foretold,</l>
<l n="tr">and rocks of dreadful name. O, fly, my men!</l>
<l n="tr">Rise like one man with long, strong sweep of oars!”</l>
<l n="tr">Not unobedient they! First Palinure</l>
<l n="tr">veered to the leftward wave the willing keel,</l>
<l n="tr">and sails and oars together leftward strove.</l>
<l n="tr">We shot to skyward on the arching surge,</l>
<l n="tr">then, as she sank, dropped deeper than the grave;</l>
<l n="tr">thrice bellowed the vast cliffs from vaulted wall;</l>
<l n="tr">thrice saw we spouted foam and showers of stars.</l>
<l n="tr">After these things both wind and sun did fail;</l>
<l n="tr">and weary, worn, not witting of our way,</l>
<l n="tr">we drifted shoreward to the Cyclops' land.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="570" unit="card" />A spreading bay is there, impregnable</l>
<l n="tr">to all invading storms; and <placeName key="tgn,7003867" authname="tgn,7003867">Aetna</placeName>'s throat</l>
<l n="tr">with roar of frightful ruin thunders nigh.</l>
<l n="tr">Now to the realm of light it lifts a cloud</l>
<l n="tr">of pitch-black, whirling smoke, and fiery dust,</l>
<l n="tr">shooting out globes of flame, with monster tongues</l>
<l n="tr">that lick the stars; now huge crags of itself,</l>
<l n="tr">out of the bowels of the mountain torn,</l>
<l n="tr">its maw disgorges, while the molten rock</l>
<l n="tr">rolls screaming skyward; from the nether deep</l>
<l n="tr">the fathomless abyss makes ebb and flow.</l>
<l n="tr">Enceladus, his body lightning-scarred,</l>
<l n="tr">lies prisoned under all, so runs the tale:</l>
<l n="tr">o'er him gigantic <placeName key="tgn,7003867" authname="tgn,7003867">Aetna</placeName> breathes in fire</l>
<l n="tr">from crack and seam; and if he haply turn</l>
<l n="tr">to change his wearied side, <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Trinacria</placeName>'s isle</l>
<l n="tr">trembles and moans, and thick fumes mantle heaven.</l>
<l n="tr">That night in screen and covert of a grove</l>
<l n="tr">we bore the dire convulsion, unaware</l>
<l n="tr">whence the loud horror came. For not a star</l>
<l n="tr">its lamp allowed, nor burned in upper sky</l>
<l n="tr">the constellated fires, but all was gloom,</l>
<l n="tr">and frowning night confined the moon in cloud.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="588" unit="card" />When from the eastern waves the light of morn</l>
<l n="tr">began to peer, and from the upper sky</l>
<l n="tr">Aurora flamed away the dark and dew,</l>
<l n="tr">out of the forest sprang a startling shape</l>
<l n="tr">of hunger-wasted misery; a man</l>
<l n="tr">in wretched guise, who shoreward came with hands</l>
<l n="tr">outstretched in supplication. We turned back</l>
<l n="tr">and scanned him well. All grime and foulness he,</l>
<l n="tr">with long and tangled beard, his savage garb</l>
<l n="tr">fastened with thorns; but in all else he seemed</l>
<l n="tr">a Greek, and in his country's league of arms</l>
<l n="tr">sent to the seige of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. Then he beheld</l>
<l n="tr">the Dardan habit, and our Trojan steel,</l>
<l n="tr">he somewhat paused, as if in dread dismay</l>
<l n="tr">such sight to see, and falteringly moved;</l>
<l n="tr">but soon with headlong steps he sought the shore,</l>
<l n="tr">ejaculating broken sobs and prayers:</l>
<l n="tr">“By stars above! By gods on high! O, hear!</l>
<l n="tr">By this bright heavenly air we mortals breathe,</l>
<l n="tr">save me, sweet Trojans! Carry me away</l>
<l n="tr">unto what land ye will! I ask no more.</l>
<l n="tr">I came, I know it, in the ships of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>;</l>
<l n="tr">and I did war, 't is true, with <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>'s gods.</l>
<l n="tr">O, if the crime deserve it, fling my corse</l>
<l n="tr">on yonder waves, and in the boundless brine</l>
<l n="tr">sink me forever! Give me in my death</l>
<l n="tr">the comfort that by human hands I die.”</l>
<l n="tr">He clasped our knees, and writhing on his own</l>
<l n="tr">clung fast. We bid him tell his race and name,</l>
<l n="tr">and by what fate pursued. Anchises gave</l>
<l n="tr">his own right hand in swift and generous aid,</l>
<l n="tr">and by prompt token cheered the exile's heart,</l>
<l n="tr">who, banishing his fears, poured forth this tale :—</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="613" unit="card" />“My home was <placeName key="tgn,1007519" authname="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName>, and I partook</l>
<l n="tr">the fortunes of Ulysses evil-starred.</l>
<l n="tr">My name is Achemenides, my sire</l>
<l n="tr">was Adamastus, and I sailed for <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">being so poor,—O, that I ne'er had change</l>
<l n="tr">the lot I bore! In yon vast Cyclops' cave</l>
<l n="tr">my comrades, flying from its gruesome door,</l>
<l n="tr">left me behind, forgotten. 'T is a house</l>
<l n="tr">of gory feasts of flesh, 't is deep and dark,</l>
<l n="tr">and vaulted high. He looms as high as heaven;</l>
<l n="tr">I pray the blessed gods to rid the earth</l>
<l n="tr">of the vile monster! None can look on him,</l>
<l n="tr">none speak with him. He feeds on clotted gore</l>
<l n="tr">of disembowelled men. These very eyes</l>
<l n="tr">saw him seize two of our own company,</l>
<l n="tr">and, as he lolled back in the cave, he clutched</l>
<l n="tr">and dashed them on the stones, fouling the floor</l>
<l n="tr">with torrent of their blood; myself I saw him</l>
<l n="tr">crunch with his teeth the dripping, bloody limbs</l>
<l n="tr">still hot and pulsing on his hungry jaw.</l>
<l n="tr">But not without reward! For such a sight</l>
<l n="tr">Ulysses would not brook, and <placeName key="tgn,1007519" authname="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">forgot not in such strait the name he bore.</l>
<l n="tr">For soon as, gorged with feasting and o'ercome</l>
<l n="tr">with drunken slumber, the foul giant lay</l>
<l n="tr">sprawled through the cave, his head dropped helpless down,</l>
<l n="tr">disgorging as he slept thick drool of gore</l>
<l n="tr">and gobbets drenched with bloody wine; then we,</l>
<l n="tr">calling on Heaven and taking place by lot,</l>
<l n="tr">drew round him like one man, and with a beam</l>
<l n="tr">sharpened at end bored out that monster eye,</l>
<l n="tr">which, huge and sole, lay under the grim brow,</l>
<l n="tr">round as an <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> shield or Phoebus' star.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus took we joyful vengeance for the shades</l>
<l n="tr">of our lost mates. But, O ill-fated men!</l>
<l n="tr">Fly, I implore, and cut the cables free</l>
<l n="tr">along the beach! For in the land abide,</l>
<l n="tr">like Polyphemus, who in hollow cave</l>
<l n="tr">kept fleecy sheep, and milked his fruitful ewes,</l>
<l n="tr">a hundred other, huge as he, who rove</l>
<l n="tr">wide o'er this winding shore and mountains fair:</l>
<l n="tr">Cyclops accursed, bestial! Thrice the moon</l>
<l n="tr">has filled her horns with light, while here I dwell</l>
<l n="tr">in lonely woods and lairs of creatures wild;</l>
<l n="tr">or from tall cliffs out-peering I discern</l>
<l n="tr">the Cyclops, and shrink shuddering from the sound</l>
<l n="tr">of their vast step and cry. My sorry fare</l>
<l n="tr">is berries and hard corners dropped from trees,</l>
<l n="tr">or herb-roots torn out from the niggard ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Though watching the whole sea, only today</l>
<l n="tr"> Have I had sight of ships. To you I fled.</l>
<l n="tr">Whate'er ye be, it was my only prayer</l>
<l n="tr">to 'scape that monster brood. I ask no more.</l>
<l n="tr">O, set me free by any death ye will!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="655" unit="card" />He scarce had said, when moving o'er the crest</l>
<l n="tr">of a high hill a giant shape we saw:</l>
<l n="tr">that shepherd Polyphemus, with his flocks</l>
<l n="tr">down-wending to the well-known water-side;</l>
<l n="tr">huge, shapeless, horrible, with blinded eye,</l>
<l n="tr">bearing a lopped pine for a staff, he made</l>
<l n="tr">his footing sure, while the white, fleecy sheep,</l>
<l n="tr">sole pleasure now, and solace of his woes,</l>
<l n="tr">ran huddling at his side.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon to the vast flood of the level brine</l>
<l n="tr">he came, and washed the flowing gore away</l>
<l n="tr">from that out-hollowed eye; he gnashed his teeth,</l>
<l n="tr">groaning, and deep into the watery way</l>
<l n="tr">stalked on, his tall bulk wet by scarce a wave.</l>
<l n="tr">We fled in haste, though far, and with us bore</l>
<l n="tr">the truthful suppliant; cut silently</l>
<l n="tr">the anchor-ropes, and, bending to the oar,</l>
<l n="tr">swept on with eager strokes clean out to sea.</l>
<l n="tr">Aware he was, and toward our loud halloo</l>
<l n="tr">whirled sudden round; but when no power had he</l>
<l n="tr">to seize or harm, nor could his fierce pursuit</l>
<l n="tr">o'ertake the Ionian surges as they rolled,</l>
<l n="tr">he raised a cry incredible; the sea</l>
<l n="tr">with all its billows trembled; the wide shore</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> from glens and gorges moaned,</l>
<l n="tr">and <placeName key="tgn,7003867" authname="tgn,7003867">Aetna</placeName> roared from every vaulted cave.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="675" unit="card" />Then rallied from the grove-clad, Iofty isle</l>
<l n="tr">the Cyclops' clan, and lined the beach and bay.</l>
<l n="tr">We saw each lonely eyeball glare in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">as side by side those brothers Aetna-born</l>
<l n="tr">stood towering high, a conclave dark and dire:</l>
<l n="tr">as when, far up some mountain's famous crest,</l>
<l n="tr">wind-fronting oaks or cone-clad cypresses</l>
<l n="tr">have made assembling in the solemn hills,</l>
<l n="tr">Jove's giant wood or Dian's sacred grove.</l>
<l n="tr">We, terror-struck, would fly we knew not where,</l>
<l n="tr">with loosened sheet and canvas swelling strong</l>
<l n="tr">before a welcome wind; but Helenus</l>
<l n="tr">bade us both Scylla and Charybdis fear,</l>
<l n="tr">where 'twixt the twain death straitly hems the way;</l>
<l n="tr">and so the counsel was to veer our bark</l>
<l n="tr">the course it came. But lo! a northern gale</l>
<l n="tr">burst o'er us from Pelorus' narrowed side,</l>
<l n="tr">and on we rode far past Pantagia's bay</l>
<l n="tr">of unhewn rock, and past the haven strong</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="perseus,Megara" authname="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>, and Thapsus Iying low.</l>
<l n="tr">Such were the names retold, and such the shores</l>
<l n="tr">shown us by Achemenides, whose fate</l>
<l n="tr">made him familiar there, for he had sailed</l>
<l n="tr">with evil-starred Ulysses o'er that sea.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="692" unit="card" />Off the Sicilian shore an island lies,</l>
<l n="tr">wave-washed Plemmyrium, called in olden days</l>
<l n="tr">Ortygia; here Alpheus, river-god,</l>
<l n="tr">from <placeName key="perseus,Elis" authname="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName> flowed by secret sluice, they say,</l>
<l n="tr">beneath the sea, and mingles at thy mouth,</l>
<l n="tr">fair Arethusa! with Sicilian waves.</l>
<l n="tr">Our voices hailed the great gods of the land</l>
<l n="tr">with reverent prayer; then skirted we the shore,</l>
<l n="tr">where smooth Helorus floods the fruitful plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Under Pachynus' beetling precipice</l>
<l n="tr">we kept our course; then Camarina rose</l>
<l n="tr">in distant view, firm-seated evermore</l>
<l n="tr">by Fate's decree; and that far-spreading vale</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="perseus,Gela" authname="perseus,Gela">Gela</placeName>, with the name of power it takes</l>
<l n="tr">from its wide river; and, uptowering far,</l>
<l n="tr">the ramparts of proud <placeName key="tgn,7003808" authname="tgn,7003808">Acragas</placeName> appeared,</l>
<l n="tr">where fiery steeds were bred in days of old.</l>
<l n="tr">Borne by the winds, along thy coast I fled,</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Selinus" authname="perseus,Selinus">Selinus</placeName>, green with palm! and past the shore</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="perseus,Lilybaion" authname="perseus,Lilybaion">Lilybaeum</placeName> with its treacherous reef;</l>
<l n="tr">till at the last the port of <placeName key="perseus,Drepana" authname="perseus,Drepana">Drepanum</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">received me to its melancholy strand.</l>
<l n="tr">Here, woe is me I outworn by stormful seas,</l>
<l n="tr">my sire, sole comfort of my grievous doom,</l>
<l n="tr">Anchises ceased to be. O best of sires!</l>
<l n="tr">Here didst thou leave me in the weary way;</l>
<l n="tr">through all our perils—O the bitter loss! —</l>
<l n="tr">borne safely, but in vain. King Helenus,</l>
<l n="tr">whose prophet-tongue of dark events foretold,</l>
<l n="tr">spoke not this woe; nor did Celeno's curse</l>
<l n="tr">of this forebode. Such my last loss and pain;</l>
<l n="tr">such, of my weary way, the destined goal.</l>
<l n="tr">From thence departing, the divine behest</l>
<l n="tr">impelled me to thy shores, O listening queen!</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="716" unit="card" />Such was, while all gave ear, the tale sublime</l>
<l n="tr">father Aeneas, none but he, set forth</l>
<l n="tr">of wanderings and of dark decrees divine:</l>
<l n="tr">silent at last, he ceased, and took repose.</l></div1>
<div1 type="Book" n="4" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card" />
<l n="tr">Now felt the Queen the sharp, slow-gathering pangs</l>
<l n="tr">of love; and out of every pulsing vein</l>
<l n="tr">nourished the wound and fed its viewless fire.</l>
<l n="tr">Her hero's virtues and his lordly line</l>
<l n="tr">keep calling to her soul; his words, his glance,</l>
<l n="tr">cling to her heart like lingering, barbed steel,</l>
<l n="tr">and rest and peace from her vexed body fly.</l>
<l n="tr">A new day's dawn with Phoebus' lamp divine</l>
<l n="tr">lit up all lands, and from the vaulted heaven</l>
<l n="tr">Aurora had dispelled the dark and dew;</l>
<l n="tr">when thus unto the ever-answering heart</l>
<l n="tr">of her dear sister spoke the stricken Queen:</l>
<l n="tr">“Anna, my sister, what disturbing dreams</l>
<l n="tr">perplex me and alarm? What guest is this</l>
<l n="tr">new-welcomed to our house? How proud his mien!</l>
<l n="tr">What dauntless courage and exploits of war!</l>
<l n="tr">Sooth, I receive it for no idle tale</l>
<l n="tr">that of the gods he sprang. 'T is cowardice</l>
<l n="tr">betrays the base-born soul. Ah me! How fate</l>
<l n="tr">has smitten him with storms! What dire extremes</l>
<l n="tr">of war and horror in his tale he told!</l>
<l n="tr">O, were it not immutably resolved</l>
<l n="tr">in my fixed heart, that to no shape of man</l>
<l n="tr">I would be wed again (since my first love</l>
<l n="tr">left me by death abandoned and betrayed);</l>
<l n="tr">loathed I not so the marriage torch and train,</l>
<l n="tr">I could—who knows?—to this one weakness yield.</l>
<l n="tr">Anna, I hide it not! But since the doom</l>
<l n="tr">of my ill-starred Sichaeus, when our shrines</l>
<l n="tr">were by a brother's murder dabbled o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">this man alone has moved me; he alone</l>
<l n="tr">has shaken my weak will. I seem to feel</l>
<l n="tr">the motions of love's lost, familiar fire.</l>
<l n="tr">But may the earth gape open where I tread,</l>
<l n="tr">and may almighty Jove with thunder-scourge</l>
<l n="tr">hurl me to Erebus' abysmal shade,</l>
<l n="tr">to pallid ghosts and midnight fathomless,</l>
<l n="tr">before, O Chastity! I shall offend</l>
<l n="tr">thy holy power, or cast thy bonds away!</l>
<l n="tr">He who first mingled his dear life with mine</l>
<l n="tr">took with him all my heart. 'T is his alone —</l>
<l n="tr">o, let it rest beside him in the grave!”</l>
<l n="tr">She spoke: the bursting tears her breast o'erflowed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="31" unit="card" />“O dearer to thy sister than her life,”</l>
<l n="tr">Anna replied, “wouldst thou in sorrow's weed</l>
<l n="tr">waste thy long youth alone, nor ever know</l>
<l n="tr">sweet babes at thine own breast, nor gifts of love?</l>
<l n="tr">Will dust and ashes, or a buried ghost</l>
<l n="tr">reck what we do? 'T is true thy grieving heart</l>
<l n="tr">was cold to earlier wooers, <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>'s now,</l>
<l n="tr">and long ago in <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>. Iarbas knew</l>
<l n="tr">thy scorn, and many a prince and captain bred</l>
<l n="tr">in Afric's land of glory. Why resist</l>
<l n="tr">a love that makes thee glad? Hast thou no care</l>
<l n="tr">what alien lands are these where thou dost reign?</l>
<l n="tr">Here are Gaetulia's cities and her tribes</l>
<l n="tr">unconquered ever; on thy borders rove</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,7016752" authname="tgn,7016752">Numidia</placeName>'s uncurbed cavalry; here too</l>
<l n="tr">lies Syrtis' cruel shore, and regions wide</l>
<l n="tr">of thirsty desert, menaced everywhere</l>
<l n="tr">by the wild hordes of <placeName key="tgn,7000645" authname="tgn,7000645">Barca</placeName>. Shall I tell</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>'s hostilities, the threats and rage</l>
<l n="tr">of our own brother? Friendly gods, I bow,</l>
<l n="tr">wafted the Teucrian ships, with Juno's aid,</l>
<l n="tr">to these our shores. O sister, what a throne,</l>
<l n="tr">and what imperial city shall be thine,</l>
<l n="tr">if thus espoused! With Trojan arms allied</l>
<l n="tr">how far may not our Punic fame extend</l>
<l n="tr">in deeds of power? Call therefore on the gods</l>
<l n="tr">to favor thee; and, after omens fair,</l>
<l n="tr">give queenly welcome, and contrive excuse</l>
<l n="tr">to make him tarry, while yon wintry seas</l>
<l n="tr">are loud beneath Orion's stormful star,</l>
<l n="tr">and on his battered ships the season frowns.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="54" unit="card" />So saying, she stirred a passion-burning breast</l>
<l n="tr">to Iove more madly still; her words infused</l>
<l n="tr">a doubting mind with hope, and bade the blush</l>
<l n="tr">of shame begone. First to the shrines they went</l>
<l n="tr">and sued for grace; performing sacrifice,</l>
<l n="tr">choosing an offering of unblemished ewes,</l>
<l n="tr">to law-bestowing Ceres, to the god</l>
<l n="tr">of light, to sire Lyeus, Iord of wine;</l>
<l n="tr">but chiefly unto Juno, patroness</l>
<l n="tr">of nuptial vows. There Dido, beauteous Queen</l>
<l n="tr">held forth in her right hand the sacred bowl</l>
<l n="tr">and poured it full between the lifted horns</l>
<l n="tr">of the white heifer; or on temple floors</l>
<l n="tr">she strode among the richly laden shrines,</l>
<l n="tr">the eyes of gods upon her, worshipping</l>
<l n="tr">with many a votive gift; or, peering deep</l>
<l n="tr">into the victims' cloven sides, she read</l>
<l n="tr">the fate-revealing tokens trembling there.</l>
<l n="tr">How blind the hearts of prophets be! Alas!</l>
<l n="tr">Of what avail be temples and fond prayers</l>
<l n="tr">to change a frenzied mind? Devouring ever,</l>
<l n="tr">love's fire burns inward to her bones; she feels</l>
<l n="tr">quick in her breast the viewless, voiceless wound.</l>
<l n="tr">Ill-fated Dido ranges up and down</l>
<l n="tr">the spaces of her city, desperate</l>
<l n="tr">her life one flame—like arrow-stricken doe</l>
<l n="tr">through Cretan forest rashly wandering,</l>
<l n="tr">pierced by a far-off shepherd, who pursues</l>
<l n="tr">with shafts, and leaves behind his light-winged steed,</l>
<l n="tr">not knowing; while she scours the dark ravines</l>
<l n="tr">of Dicte and its woodlands; at her heart</l>
<l n="tr">the mortal barb irrevocably clings.</l>
<l n="tr">around her city's battlements she guides</l>
<l n="tr">aeneas, to make show of <placeName key="tgn,7002861" authname="tgn,7002861">Sidon</placeName>'s gold,</l>
<l n="tr">and what her realm can boast; full oft her voice</l>
<l n="tr">essays to speak and frembling dies away:</l>
<l n="tr">or, when the daylight fades, she spreads anew</l>
<l n="tr">a royal banquet, and once more will plead</l>
<l n="tr">mad that she is, to hear the Trojan sorrow;</l>
<l n="tr">and with oblivious ravishment once more</l>
<l n="tr">hangs on his lips who tells; or when her guests</l>
<l n="tr">are scattered, and the wan moon's fading horn</l>
<l n="tr">bedims its ray, while many a sinking star</l>
<l n="tr">invites to slumber, there she weeps alone</l>
<l n="tr">in the deserted hall, and casts her down</l>
<l n="tr">on the cold couch he pressed. Her love from far</l>
<l n="tr">beholds her vanished hero and receives</l>
<l n="tr">his voice upon her ears; or to her breast,</l>
<l n="tr">moved by a father's image in his child,</l>
<l n="tr">she clasps Ascanius, seeking to deceive</l>
<l n="tr">her unblest passion so. Her enterprise</l>
<l n="tr">of tower and rampart stops: her martial host</l>
<l n="tr">no Ionger she reviews, nor fashions now</l>
<l n="tr">defensive haven and defiant wall;</l>
<l n="tr">but idly all her half-built bastions frown,</l>
<l n="tr">and enginery of sieges, high as heaven.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="90" unit="card" />But soon the chosen spouse of Jove perceived</l>
<l n="tr">the Queen's infection; and because the voice</l>
<l n="tr">of honor to such frenzy spoke not, she,</l>
<l n="tr">daughter of Saturn, unto Venus turned</l>
<l n="tr">and counselled thus: “How noble is the praise,</l>
<l n="tr">how glorious the spoils of victory,</l>
<l n="tr">for thee and for thy boy! Your names should be</l>
<l n="tr">in lasting, vast renown—that by the snare</l>
<l n="tr">of two great gods in league one woman fell!</l>
<l n="tr">it 'scapes me not that my protected realms</l>
<l n="tr">have ever been thy fear, and the proud halls</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> thy vexation and annoy.</l>
<l n="tr">Why further go? Prithee, what useful end</l>
<l n="tr">has our long war? Why not from this day forth</l>
<l n="tr">perpetual peace and nuptial amity?</l>
<l n="tr">Hast thou not worked thy will? Behold and see</l>
<l n="tr">how Iove-sick Dido burns, and all her flesh</l>
<l n="tr">'The madness feels! So let our common grace</l>
<l n="tr">smile on a mingled people! Let her serve</l>
<l n="tr">a Phrygian husband, while thy hands receive</l>
<l n="tr">her Tyrian subjects for the bridal dower!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="105" unit="card" />In answer (reading the dissembler's mind</l>
<l n="tr">which unto Libyan shores were fain to shift</l>
<l n="tr">italia's future throne) thus Venus spoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“'T were mad to spurn such favor, or by choice</l>
<l n="tr">be numbered with thy foes. But can it be</l>
<l n="tr">that fortune on thy noble counsel smiles?</l>
<l n="tr">To me Fate shows but dimly whether Jove</l>
<l n="tr">unto the Trojan wanderers ordains</l>
<l n="tr">a common city with the sons of <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">with mingling blood and sworn, perpetual peace.</l>
<l n="tr">His wife thou art; it is thy rightful due</l>
<l n="tr">to plead to know his mind. Go, ask him, then!</l>
<l n="tr">For humbly I obey!” With instant word</l>
<l n="tr">Juno the Queen replied: “Leave that to me!</l>
<l n="tr">But in what wise our urgent task and grave</l>
<l n="tr">may soon be sped, I will in brief unfold</l>
<l n="tr">to thine attending ear. A royal hunt</l>
<l n="tr">in sylvan shades unhappy Dido gives</l>
<l n="tr">for her Aeneas, when to-morrow's dawn</l>
<l n="tr">uplifts its earliest ray and Titan's beam</l>
<l n="tr">shall first unveil the world. But I will pour</l>
<l n="tr">black storm-clouds with a burst of heavy hail</l>
<l n="tr">along their way; and as the huntsmen speed</l>
<l n="tr">to hem the wood with snares, I will arouse</l>
<l n="tr">all heaven with thunder. The attending train</l>
<l n="tr">shall scatter and be veiled in blinding dark,</l>
<l n="tr">while Dido and her hero out of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">to the same cavern fly. My auspices</l>
<l n="tr">I will declare—if thou alike wilt bless;</l>
<l n="tr">and yield her in true wedlock for his bride.</l>
<l n="tr">Such shall their spousal be!” To Juno's will</l>
<l n="tr">Cythera's Queen inclined assenting brow,</l>
<l n="tr">and laughed such guile to see. <milestone ed="p" n="129" unit="card" />Aurora rose,</l>
<l n="tr">and left the ocean's rim. The city's gates</l>
<l n="tr">pour forth to greet the morn a gallant train</l>
<l n="tr">of huntsmen, bearing many a woven snare</l>
<l n="tr">and steel-tipped javelin; while to and fro</l>
<l n="tr">run the keen-scented dogs and Libyan squires.</l>
<l n="tr">The Queen still keeps her chamber; at her doors</l>
<l n="tr">the Punic lords await; her palfrey, brave</l>
<l n="tr">in gold and purple housing, paws the ground</l>
<l n="tr">and fiercely champs the foam-flecked bridle-rein.</l>
<l n="tr">At last, with numerous escort, forth she shines:</l>
<l n="tr">her Tyrian pall is bordered in bright hues,</l>
<l n="tr">her quiver, gold; her tresses are confined</l>
<l n="tr">only with gold; her robes of purple rare</l>
<l n="tr">meet in a golden clasp. To greet her come</l>
<l n="tr">the noble Phrygian guests; among them smiles</l>
<l n="tr">the boy Iulus; and in fair array</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas, goodliest of all his train.</l>
<l n="tr">In such a guise Apollo (when he leaves</l>
<l n="tr">cold Lycian hills and <placeName key="perseus,Xanthos" authname="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName>' frosty stream</l>
<l n="tr">to visit <placeName key="perseus,Delos" authname="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> to Latona dear)</l>
<l n="tr">ordains the song, while round his altars cry</l>
<l n="tr">the choirs of many islands, with the pied,</l>
<l n="tr">fantastic Agathyrsi; soon the god</l>
<l n="tr">moves o'er the Cynthian steep; his flowing hair</l>
<l n="tr">he binds with laurel garland and bright gold;</l>
<l n="tr">upon his shining shoulder as he goes</l>
<l n="tr">the arrows ring:—not less uplifted mien</l>
<l n="tr">aeneas wore; from his illustrious brow</l>
<l n="tr">such beauty shone. Soon to the mountains tall</l>
<l n="tr">the cavalcade comes nigh, to pathless haunts</l>
<l n="tr">of woodland creatures; the wild goats are seen,</l>
<l n="tr">from pointed crag descending leap by leap</l>
<l n="tr">down the steep ridges; in the vales below</l>
<l n="tr">are routed deer, that scour the spreading plain,</l>
<l n="tr">and mass their dust-blown squadrons in wild flight,</l>
<l n="tr">far from the mountain's bound. Ascanius</l>
<l n="tr">flushed with the sport, spurs on a mettled steed</l>
<l n="tr">from vale to vale, and many a flying herd</l>
<l n="tr">his chase outspeeds; but in his heart he prays</l>
<l n="tr">among these tame things suddenly to see</l>
<l n="tr">a tusky boar, or, leaping from the hills,</l>
<l n="tr">a growling mountain-lion, golden-maned.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="160" unit="card" />Meanwhile low thunders in the distant sky</l>
<l n="tr">mutter confusedly; soon bursts in full</l>
<l n="tr">the storm-cloud and the hail. The Tyrian troop</l>
<l n="tr">is scattered wide; the chivalry of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">with the young heir of Dardan's kingly line,</l>
<l n="tr">of Venus sprung, seek shelter where they may, </l>
<l n="tr">with sudden terror; down the deep ravines</l>
<l n="tr">the swollen torrents roar. In that same hour</l>
<l n="tr">Queen Dido and her hero out of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">to the same cavern fly. Old Mother-Earth</l>
<l n="tr">and wedlock-keeping Juno gave the sign;</l>
<l n="tr">the flash of lightnings on the conscious air</l>
<l n="tr">were torches to the bridal; from the hills</l>
<l n="tr">the wailing wood-nymphs sobbed a wedding song.</l>
<l n="tr">Such was that day of death, the source and spring</l>
<l n="tr">of many a woe. For Dido took no heed</l>
<l n="tr">of honor and good-name; nor did she mean</l>
<l n="tr">her loves to hide; but called the lawlessness</l>
<l n="tr">a marriage, and with phrases veiled her shame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="173" unit="card" />Swift through the Libyan cities Rumor sped.</l>
<l n="tr">Rumor! What evil can surpass her speed?</l>
<l n="tr">In movement she grows mighty, and achieves</l>
<l n="tr">strength and dominion as she swifter flies.</l>
<l n="tr">small first, because afraid, she soon exalts</l>
<l n="tr">her stature skyward, stalking through the lands</l>
<l n="tr">and mantling in the clouds her baleful brow.</l>
<l n="tr">The womb of Earth, in anger at high Heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">bore her, they say, last of the Titan spawn,</l>
<l n="tr">sister to Coeus and Enceladus.</l>
<l n="tr">Feet swift to run and pinions like the wind</l>
<l n="tr">the dreadful monster wears; her carcase huge</l>
<l n="tr">is feathered, and at root of every plume</l>
<l n="tr">a peering eye abides; and, strange to tell,</l>
<l n="tr">an equal number of vociferous tongues,</l>
<l n="tr">foul, whispering lips, and ears, that catch at all.</l>
<l n="tr">At night she spreads midway 'twixt earth and heaven</l>
<l n="tr">her pinions in the darkness, hissing loud,</l>
<l n="tr">nor e'er to happy slumber gives her eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">but with the morn she takes her watchful throne</l>
<l n="tr">high on the housetops or on lofty towers,</l>
<l n="tr">to terrify the nations. She can cling</l>
<l n="tr">to vile invention and malignant wrong,</l>
<l n="tr">or mingle with her word some tidings true.</l>
<l n="tr">She now with changeful story filled men's ears,</l>
<l n="tr">exultant, whether false or true she sung:</l>
<l n="tr">how, Trojan-born Aeneas having come,</l>
<l n="tr">Dido, the lovely widow, Iooked his way,</l>
<l n="tr">deigning to wed; how all the winter long</l>
<l n="tr">they passed in revel and voluptuous ease,</l>
<l n="tr">to dalliance given o'er; naught heeding now</l>
<l n="tr">of crown or kingdom—shameless! lust-enslaved!</l>
<l n="tr">Such tidings broadcast on the lips of men</l>
<l n="tr">the filthy goddess spread; and soon she hied</l>
<l n="tr">to King Iarbas, where her hateful song</l>
<l n="tr">to newly-swollen wrath his heart inflamed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="198" unit="card" />Him the god Ammon got by forced embrace</l>
<l n="tr">upon a Libyan nymph; his kingdoms wide</l>
<l n="tr">possessed a hundred ample shrines to Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">a hundred altars whence ascended ever</l>
<l n="tr">the fires of sacrifice, perpetual seats</l>
<l n="tr">for a great god's abode, where flowing blood</l>
<l n="tr">enriched the ground, and on the portals hung</l>
<l n="tr">garlands of every flower. The angered King,</l>
<l n="tr">half-maddened by malignant Rumor's voice,</l>
<l n="tr">unto his favored altars came, and there,</l>
<l n="tr">surrounded by the effluence divine,</l>
<l n="tr">upraised in prayer to Jove his suppliant hands.</l>
<l n="tr">“Almighty Jupiter, to whom each day,</l>
<l n="tr">at banquet on the painted couch reclined,</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,7016752" authname="tgn,7016752">Numidia</placeName> pours libation! Do thine eyes</l>
<l n="tr">behold us? Or when out of yonder heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">o sire, thou launchest the swift thunderbolt,</l>
<l n="tr">is it for naught we fear thee? Do the clouds</l>
<l n="tr">shoot forth blind fire to terrify the soul</l>
<l n="tr">with wild, unmeaning roar? O, Iook upon</l>
<l n="tr">that woman, who was homeless in our realm,</l>
<l n="tr">and bargained where to build her paltry town,</l>
<l n="tr">receiving fertile coastland for her farms,</l>
<l n="tr">by hospitable grant! She dares disdain</l>
<l n="tr">our proffered nuptial vow. She has proclaimed</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas partner of her bed and throne.</l>
<l n="tr">And now that Paris, with his eunuch crew,</l>
<l n="tr">beneath his chin and fragrant, oozy hair</l>
<l n="tr">ties the soft Lydian bonnet, boasting well</l>
<l n="tr">his stolen prize. But we to all these fanes,</l>
<l n="tr">though they be thine, a fruitless offering bring,</l>
<l n="tr">and feed on empty tales our trust in thee.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="219" unit="card" />As thus he prayed and to the altars clung,</l>
<l n="tr">th' Omnipotent gave ear, and turned his gaze</l>
<l n="tr">upon the royal dwelling, where for love</l>
<l n="tr">the amorous pair forgot their place and name.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus to Mercury he gave command:</l>
<l n="tr">“Haste thee, my son, upon the Zephyrs call,</l>
<l n="tr">and take thy winged way! My mandate bear</l>
<l n="tr">unto that prince of Troy who tarries now</l>
<l n="tr">in Tyrian Carthage, heedless utterly</l>
<l n="tr">of empire Heaven-bestowed. On winged winds</l>
<l n="tr">hasten with my decrees. Not such the man</l>
<l n="tr">his beauteous mother promised; not for this</l>
<l n="tr">twice did she shield him from the Greeks in arms:</l>
<l n="tr">but that he might rule <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, a land</l>
<l n="tr">pregnant with thrones and echoing with war;</l>
<l n="tr">that he of Teucer's seed a race should sire,</l>
<l n="tr">and bring beneath its law the whole wide world.</l>
<l n="tr">If such a glory and event supreme</l>
<l n="tr">enkindle not his bosom; if such task</l>
<l n="tr">to his own honor speak not; can the sire</l>
<l n="tr">begrudge Ascanius the heritage</l>
<l n="tr">of the proud name of <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>? What plans he now?</l>
<l n="tr">What mad hope bids him linger in the lap</l>
<l n="tr">of enemies, considering no more</l>
<l n="tr">the land Lavinian and Ausonia's sons.</l>
<l n="tr">Let him to sea! Be this our final word:</l>
<l n="tr">this message let our herald faithful bear.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="238" unit="card" />He spoke. The god a prompt obedience gave</l>
<l n="tr">to his great sire's command. He fastened first</l>
<l n="tr">those sandals of bright gold, which carry him</l>
<l n="tr">aloft o'er land or sea, with airy wings</l>
<l n="tr">that race the fleeting wind; then lifted he</l>
<l n="tr">his wand, wherewith he summons from the grave</l>
<l n="tr">pale-featured ghosts, or, if he will, consigns</l>
<l n="tr">to doleful Tartarus; or by its power</l>
<l n="tr">gives slumber or dispels; or quite unseals</l>
<l n="tr">the eyelids of the dead: on this relying,</l>
<l n="tr">he routs the winds or cleaves th' obscurity</l>
<l n="tr">of stormful clouds. Soon from his flight he spied</l>
<l n="tr">the summit and the sides precipitous</l>
<l n="tr">of stubborn Atlas, whose star-pointing peak</l>
<l n="tr">props heaven; of Atlas, whose pine-wreathed brow</l>
<l n="tr">is girdled evermore with misty gloom</l>
<l n="tr">and lashed of wind and rain; a cloak of snow</l>
<l n="tr">melts on his shoulder; from his aged chin</l>
<l n="tr">drop rivers, and ensheathed in stiffening ice</l>
<l n="tr">glitters his great grim beard. Here first was stayed</l>
<l n="tr">the speed of Mercury's well-poising wing;</l>
<l n="tr">here making pause, from hence he headlong flung</l>
<l n="tr">his body to the sea; in motion like</l>
<l n="tr">some sea-bird's, which along the levelled shore</l>
<l n="tr">or round tall crags where rove the swarming fish,</l>
<l n="tr">flies Iow along the waves: o'er-hovering so</l>
<l n="tr">between the earth and skies, Cyllene's god</l>
<l n="tr">flew downward from his mother's mountain-sire,</l>
<l n="tr">parted the winds and skimmed the sandy merge</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>. When first his winged feet</l>
<l n="tr">came nigh the clay-built Punic huts, he saw</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas building at a citadel,</l>
<l n="tr">and founding walls and towers; at his side</l>
<l n="tr">was girt a blade with yellow jaspers starred,</l>
<l n="tr">his mantle with the stain of Tyrian shell</l>
<l n="tr">flowed purple from his shoulder, broidered fair</l>
<l n="tr">by opulent Dido with fine threads of gold,</l>
<l n="tr">her gift of love; straightway the god began:</l>
<l n="tr">“Dost thou for lofty <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> toil, to build</l>
<l n="tr">foundations strong? Dost thou, a wife's weak thrall,</l>
<l n="tr">build her proud city? Hast thou, shameful loss! </l>
<l n="tr">Forgot thy kingdom and thy task sublime?</l>
<l n="tr">From bright <placeName key="perseus,Olympos,Lycia" authname="perseus,Olympos,Lycia">Olympus</placeName>, I. He who commands</l>
<l n="tr">all gods, and by his sovran deity</l>
<l n="tr">moves earth and heaven—he it was who bade</l>
<l n="tr">me bear on winged winds his high decree.</l>
<l n="tr">What plan is thine? By what mad hope dost thou</l>
<l n="tr">linger so Iong in lap of Libyan land?</l>
<l n="tr">If the proud reward of thy destined way</l>
<l n="tr">move not thy heart, if all the arduous toil</l>
<l n="tr">to thine own honor speak not, Iook upon</l>
<l n="tr">Iulus in his bloom, thy hope and heir</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius. It is his rightful due</l>
<l n="tr">in <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> o'er Roman lands to reign.”</l>
<l n="tr">After such word Cyllene's winged god</l>
<l n="tr">vanished, and e'er his accents died away,</l>
<l n="tr">dissolved in air before the mortal's eyes.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="279" unit="card" />Aeneas at the sight stood terror-dumb</l>
<l n="tr">with choking voice and horror-rising hair.</l>
<l n="tr">He fain would fly at once and get him gone</l>
<l n="tr">from that voluptuous land, much wondering</l>
<l n="tr">at Heaven's wrathful word. Alas! how stir?</l>
<l n="tr">What cunning argument can plead his cause</l>
<l n="tr">before th' infuriate Queen? How break such news?</l>
<l n="tr">Flashing this way and that, his startled mind</l>
<l n="tr">makes many a project and surveys them all.</l>
<l n="tr">But, pondering well, his final counsel stopped</l>
<l n="tr">at this resolve: he summoned to his side</l>
<l n="tr">Mnestheus, Sergestus, and Serestus bold,</l>
<l n="tr">and bade them fit the fleet, all silently</l>
<l n="tr">gathering the sailors and collecting gear,</l>
<l n="tr">but carefully dissembling what emprise</l>
<l n="tr">such novel stir intends: himself the while</l>
<l n="tr">(Since high-born Dido dreamed not love so fond</l>
<l n="tr">could have an end) would seek an audience,</l>
<l n="tr">at some indulgent time, and try what shift</l>
<l n="tr">such matters may require. With joy they heard,</l>
<l n="tr">and wrought, assiduous, at their prince's plan.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="296" unit="card" />But what can cheat true love? The Queen foreknew</l>
<l n="tr">his stratagem, and all the coming change</l>
<l n="tr">perceived ere it began. Her jealous fear</l>
<l n="tr">counted no hour secure. That unclean tongue</l>
<l n="tr">of Rumor told her fevered heart the fleet</l>
<l n="tr">was fitting forth, and hastening to be gone.</l>
<l n="tr">Distractedly she raved, and passion-tossed</l>
<l n="tr">roamed through her city, like a Maenad roused</l>
<l n="tr">by the wild rout of Bacchus, when are heard</l>
<l n="tr">the third year's orgies, and the midnight scream</l>
<l n="tr">to cold Cithaeron calls the frenzied crew.</l>
<l n="tr">Finding Aeneas, thus her plaint she poured:</l>
<l n="tr">“Didst hope to hide it, false one, that such crime</l>
<l n="tr">was in thy heart,—to steal without farewell</l>
<l n="tr">out of my kingdom? Did our mutual joy</l>
<l n="tr">not move thee; nor thine own true promise given</l>
<l n="tr">once on a time? Nor Dido, who will die</l>
<l n="tr">a death of sorrow? Why compel thy ships</l>
<l n="tr">to brave the winter stars? Why off to sea</l>
<l n="tr">so fast through stormy skies? O, cruelty!</l>
<l n="tr">If <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> still stood, and if thou wert not bound</l>
<l n="tr">for alien shore unknown, wouldst steer for <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">through yonder waste of waves? Is it from me</l>
<l n="tr">thou takest flight? O, by these flowing tears,</l>
<l n="tr">by thine own plighted word (for nothing more</l>
<l n="tr">my weakness left to miserable me),</l>
<l n="tr">by our poor marriage of imperfect vow,</l>
<l n="tr">if aught to me thou owest, if aught in me</l>
<l n="tr">ever have pleased thee—O, be merciful</l>
<l n="tr">to my low-fallen fortunes! I implore,</l>
<l n="tr">if place be left for prayer, thy purpose change!</l>
<l n="tr">Because of thee yon Libyan savages</l>
<l n="tr">and nomad chiefs are grown implacable,</l>
<l n="tr">and my own Tyrians hate me. Yes, for thee</l>
<l n="tr">my chastity was slain and honor fair,</l>
<l n="tr">by which alone to glory I aspired,</l>
<l n="tr">in former days. To whom dost thou in death</l>
<l n="tr">abandon me? my guest!—since but this name</l>
<l n="tr">is left me of a husband! Shall I wait</l>
<l n="tr">till fell Pygmalion, my brother, raze</l>
<l n="tr">my city walls? Or the Gaetulian king,</l>
<l n="tr">Iarbas, chain me captive to his car? .</l>
<l n="tr">O, if, ere thou hadst fled, I might but bear</l>
<l n="tr">some pledge of love to thee, and in these halls</l>
<l n="tr">watch some sweet babe Aeneas at his play,</l>
<l n="tr">whose face should be the memory of thine own —</l>
<l n="tr">I were not so forsaken, Iost, undone!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="331" unit="card" />She said. But he, obeying Jove's decree,</l>
<l n="tr">gazed steadfastly away; and in his heart</l>
<l n="tr">with strong repression crushed his cruel pain;</l>
<l n="tr">then thus the silence broke: “O Queen, not one</l>
<l n="tr">of my unnumbered debts so strongly urged</l>
<l n="tr">would I gainsay. Elissa's memory</l>
<l n="tr">will be my treasure Iong as memory holds,</l>
<l n="tr">or breath of life is mine. Hear my brief plea!</l>
<l n="tr">'T was not my hope to hide this flight I take,</l>
<l n="tr">as thou hast dreamed. Nay, I did never light</l>
<l n="tr">a bridegroom's torch, nor gave I thee the vow</l>
<l n="tr">of marriage. Had my destiny decreed,</l>
<l n="tr">that I should shape life to my heart's desire,</l>
<l n="tr">and at my own will put away the weight</l>
<l n="tr">of foil and pain, my place would now be found</l>
<l n="tr">in <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, among the cherished sepulchres</l>
<l n="tr">of my own kin, and Priam's mansion proud</l>
<l n="tr">were standing still; or these my loyal hands</l>
<l n="tr">had rebuilt <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> for her vanquished sons.</l>
<l n="tr">But now to <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> Apollo's power</l>
<l n="tr">commands me forth; his Lycian oracles</l>
<l n="tr">are loud for Italy. My heart is there,</l>
<l n="tr">and there my fatherland. If now the towers</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> and thy Libyan colony</l>
<l n="tr">delight thy Tyrian eyes; wilt thou refuse</l>
<l n="tr">to Trojan exiles their Ausonian shore?</l>
<l n="tr">I too by Fate was driven, not less than thou,</l>
<l n="tr">to wander far a foreign throne to find.</l>
<l n="tr">Oft when in dewy dark night hides the world,</l>
<l n="tr">and flaming stars arise, Anchises' shade</l>
<l n="tr">looks on me in my dreams with angered brow.</l>
<l n="tr">I think of my Ascanius, and the wrong</l>
<l n="tr">to that dear heart, from whom I steal away</l>
<l n="tr">Hesperia, his destined home and throne.</l>
<l n="tr">But now the winged messenger of Heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">sent down by Jove (I swear by thee and me!),</l>
<l n="tr">has brought on winged winds his sire's command.</l>
<l n="tr">My own eyes with unclouded vision saw</l>
<l n="tr">the god within these walls; I have received</l>
<l n="tr">with my own ears his word. No more inflame</l>
<l n="tr">with lamentation fond thy heart and mine.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is not my own free act seeks <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="362" unit="card" />She with averted eyes and glance that rolled</l>
<l n="tr">speechless this way and that, had listened long</l>
<l n="tr">to his reply, till thus her rage broke forth:</l>
<l n="tr">“No goddess gave thee birth. No Dardanus</l>
<l n="tr">begot thy sires. But on its breast of stone</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,1108814" authname="tgn,1108814">Caucasus</placeName> bore thee, and the tigresses</l>
<l n="tr">of fell <placeName key="tgn,7016639" authname="tgn,7016639">Hyrcania</placeName> to thy baby lip</l>
<l n="tr">their udders gave. Why should I longer show</l>
<l n="tr">a lying smile? What worse can I endure?</l>
<l n="tr">Did my tears draw one sigh? Did he once drop</l>
<l n="tr">his stony stare? or did he yield a tear</l>
<l n="tr">to my lament, or pity this fond heart?</l>
<l n="tr">Why set my wrongs in order? Juno, now,</l>
<l n="tr">and Jove, the son of Saturn, heed no more</l>
<l n="tr">where justice lies. No trusting heart is safe</l>
<l n="tr">in all this world. That waif and castaway</l>
<l n="tr">I found in beggary and gave him share—</l>
<l n="tr">fool that I was!—in my own royal glory.</l>
<l n="tr">His Iost fleet and his sorry crews I steered</l>
<l n="tr">from death away. O, how my fevered soul</l>
<l n="tr">unceasing raves! Forsooth Apollo speaks!</l>
<l n="tr">His Lycian oracles! and sent by Jove</l>
<l n="tr">the messenger of Heaven on fleeting air</l>
<l n="tr">the ruthless bidding brings! Proud business</l>
<l n="tr">for gods, I trow, that such a task disturbs</l>
<l n="tr">their still abodes! I hold thee back no more,</l>
<l n="tr">nor to thy cunning speeches give the lie.</l>
<l n="tr">Begone! Sail on to <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, thy throne,</l>
<l n="tr">through wind and wave! I pray that, if there be</l>
<l n="tr">any just gods of power, thou mayest drink down</l>
<l n="tr">death on the mid-sea rocks, and often call</l>
<l n="tr">with dying gasps on Dido's name—while I</l>
<l n="tr">pursue with vengeful fire. When cold death rends</l>
<l n="tr">the body from the breath, my ghost shall sit</l>
<l n="tr">forever in thy path. Full penalties</l>
<l n="tr">thy stubborn heart shall pay. They'll bring me never</l>
<l n="tr">in yon deep gulf of death of all thy woe.”</l>
<l n="tr">Abrupt her utterance ceased; and sick at heart</l>
<l n="tr">she fled the light of day, as if to shrink</l>
<l n="tr">from human eyes, and left Aeneas there</l>
<l n="tr">irresolute with horror, while his soul</l>
<l n="tr">framed many a vain reply. Her swooning shape</l>
<l n="tr">her maidens to a marble chamber bore</l>
<l n="tr">and on her couch the helpless limbs reposed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="393" unit="card" />Aeneas, faithful to a task divine,</l>
<l n="tr">though yearning sore to remedy and soothe</l>
<l n="tr">such misery, and with the timely word</l>
<l n="tr">her grief assuage, and though his burdened heart</l>
<l n="tr">was weak because of love, while many a groan</l>
<l n="tr">rose from his bosom, yet no whit did fail</l>
<l n="tr">to do the will of Heaven, but of his fleet</l>
<l n="tr">resumed command. The Trojans on the shore</l>
<l n="tr">ply well their task and push into the sea</l>
<l n="tr">the lofty ships. Now floats the shining keel,</l>
<l n="tr">and oars they bring all leafy from the grove,</l>
<l n="tr">with oak half-hewn, so hurried was the flight.</l>
<l n="tr">Behold them how they haste—from every gate</l>
<l n="tr">forth-streaming!—just as when a heap of corn</l>
<l n="tr">is thronged with ants, who, knowing winter nigh,</l>
<l n="tr">refill their granaries; the long black line</l>
<l n="tr">runs o'er the levels, and conveys the spoil</l>
<l n="tr">in narrow pathway through the grass; a part</l>
<l n="tr">with straining and assiduous shoulder push</l>
<l n="tr">the kernels huge; a part array the file,</l>
<l n="tr">and whip the laggards on; their busy track</l>
<l n="tr">swarms quick and eager with unceasing toil.</l>
<l n="tr">O Dido, how thy suffering heart was wrung,</l>
<l n="tr">that spectacle to see! What sore lament</l>
<l n="tr">was thine, when from the towering citadel</l>
<l n="tr">the whole shore seemed alive, the sea itself</l>
<l n="tr">in turmoil with loud cries! Relentless Love,</l>
<l n="tr">to what mad courses may not mortal hearts</l>
<l n="tr">by thee be driven? Again her sorrow flies</l>
<l n="tr">to doleful plaint and supplication vain;</l>
<l n="tr">again her pride to tyrant Love bows down</l>
<l n="tr">lest, though resolved to die, she fail to prove</l>
<l n="tr">each hope of living: <milestone ed="p" n="416" unit="card" />“O Anna, dost thou see</l>
<l n="tr">yon busy shore? From every side they come.</l>
<l n="tr">their canvas wooes the winds, and o'er each prow</l>
<l n="tr">the merry seamen hang their votive flowers.</l>
<l n="tr">Dear sister, since I did forebode this grief,</l>
<l n="tr">I shall be strong to bear it. One sole boon</l>
<l n="tr">my sorrow asks thee, Anna! Since of thee,</l>
<l n="tr">thee only, did that traitor make a friend,</l>
<l n="tr">and trusted thee with what he hid so deep —</l>
<l n="tr">the feelings of his heart; since thou alone</l>
<l n="tr">hast known what way, what hour the man would yield</l>
<l n="tr">to soft persuasion—therefore, sister, haste,</l>
<l n="tr">and humbly thus implore our haughty foe:</l>
<l n="tr">‘I was not with the Greeks what time they swore</l>
<l n="tr">at <placeName key="perseus,Aulis" authname="perseus,Aulis">Aulis</placeName> to cut off the seed of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>;</l>
<l n="tr">I sent no ships to <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>. Pray, have I</l>
<l n="tr">profaned Anchises' tomb, or vexed his shade?’</l>
<l n="tr">Why should his ear be deaf and obdurate</l>
<l n="tr">to all I say? What haste? May he not make</l>
<l n="tr">one last poor offering to her whose love</l>
<l n="tr">is only pain? O, bid him but delay</l>
<l n="tr">till flight be easy and the winds blow fair.</l>
<l n="tr">I plead no more that bygone marriage-vow</l>
<l n="tr">by him forsworn, nor ask that he should lose</l>
<l n="tr">his beauteous <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> and his realm to be.</l>
<l n="tr">Nothing but time I crave! to give repose</l>
<l n="tr">and more room to this fever, till my fate</l>
<l n="tr">teach a crushed heart to sorrow. I implore</l>
<l n="tr">this last grace. (To thy sister's grief be kind!)</l>
<l n="tr">I will requite with increase, till I die.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="437" unit="card" />Such plaints, such prayers, again and yet again,</l>
<l n="tr">betwixt the twain the sorrowing sister bore.</l>
<l n="tr">But no words move, no lamentations bring</l>
<l n="tr">persuasion to his soul; decrees of Fate</l>
<l n="tr">oppose, and some wise god obstructs the way</l>
<l n="tr">that finds the hero's ear. Oft-times around</l>
<l n="tr">the aged strength of some stupendous oak</l>
<l n="tr">the rival blasts of wintry Alpine winds</l>
<l n="tr">smite with alternate wrath: Ioud is the roar,</l>
<l n="tr">and from its rocking top the broken boughs</l>
<l n="tr">are strewn along the ground; but to the crag</l>
<l n="tr">steadfast it ever clings; far as toward heaven</l>
<l n="tr">its giant crest uprears, so deep below</l>
<l n="tr">its roots reach down to Tartarus:—not less</l>
<l n="tr">the hero by unceasing wail and cry</l>
<l n="tr">is smitten sore, and in his mighty heart</l>
<l n="tr">has many a pang, while his serene intent</l>
<l n="tr">abides unmoved, and tears gush forth in vain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="450" unit="card" />Then wretched Dido, by her doom appalled,</l>
<l n="tr">asks only death. It wearies her to see</l>
<l n="tr">the sun in heaven. Yet that she might hold fast</l>
<l n="tr">her dread resolve to quit the light of day,</l>
<l n="tr">behold, when on an incense-breathing shrine</l>
<l n="tr">her offering was laid—O fearful tale!—</l>
<l n="tr">the pure libation blackened, and the wine</l>
<l n="tr">flowed like polluting gore. She told the sight</l>
<l n="tr">to none, not even to her sister's ear.</l>
<l n="tr">A second sign was given: for in her house</l>
<l n="tr">a marble altar to her husband's shade,</l>
<l n="tr">with garlands bright and snowy fleeces dressed,</l>
<l n="tr">had fervent worship; here strange cries were heard</l>
<l n="tr">as if her dead spouse called while midnight reigned,</l>
<l n="tr">and round her towers its inhuman song</l>
<l n="tr">the lone owl sang, complaining o'er and o'er</l>
<l n="tr">with lamentation and long shriek of woe.</l>
<l n="tr">Forgotten oracles by wizards told</l>
<l n="tr">whisper old omens dire. In dreams she feels</l>
<l n="tr">cruel Aeneas goad her madness on,</l>
<l n="tr">and ever seems she, friendless and alone,</l>
<l n="tr">some lengthening path to travel, or to seek</l>
<l n="tr">her Tyrians through wide wastes of barren lands.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus frantic Pentheus flees the stern array</l>
<l n="tr">of the Eumenides, and thinks to see</l>
<l n="tr">two noonday lights blaze oer his doubled <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>;</l>
<l n="tr">or murdered Agamemnon's haunted son,</l>
<l n="tr">Orestes, flees his mother's phantom scourge</l>
<l n="tr">of flames and serpents foul, while at his door</l>
<l n="tr">avenging horrors wait. <milestone ed="p" n="474" unit="card" />Now sorrow-crazed</l>
<l n="tr">and by her grief undone, resolved on death,</l>
<l n="tr">the manner and the time her secret soul</l>
<l n="tr">prepares, and, speaking to her sister sad,</l>
<l n="tr">she masks in cheerful calm her fatal will:</l>
<l n="tr">“I know a way—O, wish thy sister joy!—</l>
<l n="tr">to bring him back to Iove, or set me free.</l>
<l n="tr">On Ocean's bound and next the setting sun</l>
<l n="tr">lies the last Aethiop land, where Atlas tall</l>
<l n="tr">lifts on his shoulder the wide wheel of heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">studded with burning stars. From thence is come</l>
<l n="tr">a witch, a priestess, a Numidian crone,</l>
<l n="tr">who guards the shrine of the Hesperides</l>
<l n="tr">and feeds the dragon; she protects the fruit</l>
<l n="tr">of that enchanting tree, and scatters there</l>
<l n="tr">her slumb'rous poppies mixed with honey-dew.</l>
<l n="tr">Her spells and magic promise to set free</l>
<l n="tr">what hearts she will, or visit cruel woes</l>
<l n="tr">on men afar. She stops the downward flow</l>
<l n="tr">of rivers, and turns back the rolling stars;</l>
<l n="tr">on midnight ghosts she calls: her vot'ries hear</l>
<l n="tr">earth bellowing loud below, while from the hills</l>
<l n="tr">the ash-trees travel down. But, sister mine,</l>
<l n="tr">thou knowest, and the gods their witness give,</l>
<l n="tr">how little mind have I to don the garb</l>
<l n="tr">of sorcery. Depart in secret, thou,</l>
<l n="tr">and bid them build a lofty funeral pyre</l>
<l n="tr">inside our palalce-wall, and heap thereon</l>
<l n="tr">the hero's arms, which that blasphemer hung</l>
<l n="tr">within my chamber; every relic bring,</l>
<l n="tr">and chiefly that ill-omened nuptial bed,</l>
<l n="tr">my death and ruin! For I must blot out</l>
<l n="tr">all sight and token of this husband vile.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is what the witch commands.” She spoke no more,</l>
<l n="tr">and pallid was her brow. Yet Anna's mind</l>
<l n="tr">knew not what web of death her sister wove</l>
<l n="tr">by these strange rites, nor what such frenzy dares;</l>
<l n="tr">nor feared she worse than when Sichaeus died,</l>
<l n="tr">but tried her forth the errand to fulfil.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="504" unit="card" />Soon as the funeral pyre was builded high</l>
<l n="tr">in a sequestered garden, Iooming huge </l>
<l n="tr">with boughs of pine and faggots of cleft oak,</l>
<l n="tr">the queen herself enwreathed it with sad flowers</l>
<l n="tr">and boughs of mournful shade; and crowning all</l>
<l n="tr">she laid on nuptial bed the robes and sword</l>
<l n="tr">by him abandoned; and stretched out thereon</l>
<l n="tr">a mock Aeneas;—but her doom she knew.</l>
<l n="tr">Altars were there; and with loose locks unbound</l>
<l n="tr">the priestess with a voice of thunder called</l>
<l n="tr">three hundred gods, Hell, Chaos, the three shapes</l>
<l n="tr">of triple Hecate, the faces three</l>
<l n="tr">of virgin Dian. She aspersed a stream</l>
<l n="tr">from dark Avernus drawn, she said; soft herbs</l>
<l n="tr">were cut by moonlight with a blade of bronze,</l>
<l n="tr">oozing black poison-sap; and she had plucked</l>
<l n="tr">that philter from the forehead of new foal</l>
<l n="tr">before its dam devours. Dido herself,</l>
<l n="tr">sprinkling the salt meal, at the altar stands;</l>
<l n="tr">one foot unsandalled, and with cincture free,</l>
<l n="tr">on all the gods and fate-instructed stars,</l>
<l n="tr">foreseeing death, she calls. But if there be</l>
<l n="tr">some just and not oblivious power on high,</l>
<l n="tr">who heeds when lovers plight unequal vow,</l>
<l n="tr">to that god first her supplications rise.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="522" unit="card" />Soon fell the night, and peaceful slumbers breathed</l>
<l n="tr">on all earth's weary creatures; the loud seas</l>
<l n="tr">and babbling forests entered on repose;</l>
<l n="tr">now midway in their heavenly course the stars</l>
<l n="tr">wheeled silent on; the outspread lands below</l>
<l n="tr">lay voiceless; all the birds of tinted wing,</l>
<l n="tr">and flocks that haunt the merge of waters wide</l>
<l n="tr">or keep the thorny wold, oblivious lay</l>
<l n="tr">beneath the night so still; the stings of care</l>
<l n="tr">ceased troubling, and no heart its burden knew.</l>
<l n="tr">Not so the Tyrian Queen's deep-grieving soul!</l>
<l n="tr">To sleep she could not yield; her eyes and heart</l>
<l n="tr">refused the gift of night; her suffering</l>
<l n="tr">redoubled, and in full returning tide</l>
<l n="tr">her love rebelled, while on wild waves of rage</l>
<l n="tr">she drifted to and fro. So, ceasing not</l>
<l n="tr">from sorrow, thus she brooded on her wrongs:</l>
<l n="tr">“What refuge now? Shall I invite the scorn</l>
<l n="tr">of my rejected wooers, or entreat</l>
<l n="tr">of some disdainful, nomad blackamoor</l>
<l n="tr">to take me to his bed—though many a time</l>
<l n="tr">such husbands I made mock of? Shall I sail</l>
<l n="tr">on Ilian ships away, and sink to be</l>
<l n="tr">the Trojans' humble thrall? Do they rejoice</l>
<l n="tr">that once I gave them bread? Lives gratitude</l>
<l n="tr">in hearts like theirs for bygone kindnesses?</l>
<l n="tr">O, who, if so I stooped, would deign to bear</l>
<l n="tr">on yon proud ships the scorned and fallen Queen?</l>
<l n="tr">Lost creature! Woe betide thee! Knowest thou not    </l>
<l n="tr">the perjured children of Laomedon?</l>
<l n="tr">What way is left? Should I take flight alone</l>
<l n="tr">and join the revelling sailors? Or depart</l>
<l n="tr">with Tyrians, the whole attending train</l>
<l n="tr">of my own people? Hard the task to force</l>
<l n="tr">their hearts from <placeName key="tgn,7002861" authname="tgn,7002861">Sidon</placeName>'s towers; how once more</l>
<l n="tr">compel to sea, and bid them spread the sail?</l>
<l n="tr">Nay, perish! Thou hast earned it. Let the sword</l>
<l n="tr">from sorrow save thee! Sister of my blood—</l>
<l n="tr">who else but thee,—my own tears borne down,</l>
<l n="tr">didst heap disaster on my frantic soul,</l>
<l n="tr">and fling me to this foe? Why could I not</l>
<l n="tr">pass wedlock by, and live a blameless life</l>
<l n="tr">as wild things do, nor taste of passion's pain?</l>
<l n="tr">But I broke faith! I cast the vows away</l>
<l n="tr">made at Sichaeus' grave.” <milestone ed="p" n="553" unit="card" />Such loud lament</l>
<l n="tr">burst from her breaking heart with doleful sound.</l>
<l n="tr">Meanwhile Aeneas on his lofty ship,</l>
<l n="tr">having made ready all, and fixed his mind</l>
<l n="tr">to launch away upon brief slumher fell.</l>
<l n="tr">But the god came; and in the self-same guise</l>
<l n="tr">once more in monitory vision spoke,</l>
<l n="tr">all guised as Mercury,—his voice, his hue,</l>
<l n="tr">his golden locks, and young limbs strong and fair.</l>
<l n="tr">“Hail, goddess-born! Wouldst linger on in sleep</l>
<l n="tr">at such an hour? Nor seest thou the snares</l>
<l n="tr">that hem thee round? Nor hearest thou the voice</l>
<l n="tr">of friendly zephyrs calling? Senseless man!</l>
<l n="tr">That woman's breast contrives some treachery</l>
<l n="tr">and horrid stroke; for, resolute to die,</l>
<l n="tr">she drifts on swollen floods of wrath and scorn. </l>
<l n="tr">Wilt thou not fly before the hastening hour</l>
<l n="tr">of flight is gone? To-morrow thou wilt see</l>
<l n="tr">yon waters thronged with ships, the cruel glare</l>
<l n="tr">of fire-brands, and yonder shore all flame,</l>
<l n="tr">if but the light of morn again surprise</l>
<l n="tr">thee loitering in this land. Away! Away!</l>
<l n="tr">Stay not! A mutable and shifting thing</l>
<l n="tr">is woman ever.” Such command he spoke,</l>
<l n="tr">then melted in the midnight dark away.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="571" unit="card" />Aeneas, by that fleeting vision struck</l>
<l n="tr">with an exceeding awe, straightway leaped forth</l>
<l n="tr">from slumber's power, and to his followers cried :</l>
<l n="tr">“Awake, my men! Away! Each to his place</l>
<l n="tr">upon the thwarts! Unfurl at once the sails!</l>
<l n="tr">A god from heaven a second time sent down</l>
<l n="tr">urges our instant flight and bids us cut</l>
<l n="tr">the twisted cords. Whatever be thy name,</l>
<l n="tr">behold, we come, O venerated Power!</l>
<l n="tr">Again with joy we follow! Let thy grace</l>
<l n="tr">assist us as we go! And may thy power</l>
<l n="tr">bring none but stars benign across our sky.”</l>
<l n="tr">So saying, from its scabbard forth he flashed</l>
<l n="tr">the lightning of his sword, with naked blade</l>
<l n="tr">striking the hawsers free. Like ardor seized</l>
<l n="tr">on all his willing men, who raced and ran;</l>
<l n="tr">and, while their galleys shadowed all the sea,</l>
<l n="tr">clean from the shore they scudded, with strong strokes</l>
<l n="tr">sweeping the purple waves and crested foam.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="584" unit="card" />Aurora's first young beams to earth were pouring</l>
<l n="tr">as from Tithonus' saffron bed she sprang;</l>
<l n="tr">while from her battlements the wakeful Queen</l>
<l n="tr">watched the sky brighten, saw the mated sails</l>
<l n="tr">push forth to sea, till all her port and strand</l>
<l n="tr">held not an oar or keel. Thrice and four times</l>
<l n="tr">she smote her lovely breast with wrathful hand,</l>
<l n="tr">and tore her golden hair. “Great Jove,” she cries,</l>
<l n="tr">“Shall that departing fugitive make mock</l>
<l n="tr">of me, a queen? Will not my men-at-arms</l>
<l n="tr">draw sword, give chase, from all my city thronging?</l>
<l n="tr">Down from the docks, my ships! Out, out! Begone!</l>
<l n="tr">Take fire and sword! Bend to your oars, ye slaves!</l>
<l n="tr">What have I said? Where am I? What mad thoughts</l>
<l n="tr">delude this ruined mind? Woe unto thee,</l>
<l n="tr">thou wretched Dido, now thy impious deeds</l>
<l n="tr">strike back upon thee. Wherefore struck they not,</l>
<l n="tr">as was most fit, when thou didst fling away</l>
<l n="tr">thy sceptre from thy hand? O Iying oaths!</l>
<l n="tr">O faith forsworn! of him who brings, they boast,</l>
<l n="tr">his father's gods along, and bowed his back</l>
<l n="tr">to lift an age-worn sire! Why dared I not</l>
<l n="tr">seize on him, rend his body limb from limb,</l>
<l n="tr">and hurl him piecemeal on the rolling sea?</l>
<l n="tr">Or put his troop of followers to the sword,</l>
<l n="tr">ascanius too, and set his flesh before</l>
<l n="tr">that father for a feast? Such fearful war</l>
<l n="tr">had been of doubtful issue. Be it so!</l>
<l n="tr">What fears a woman dying? Would I had</l>
<l n="tr">attacked their camp with torches, kindled flame</l>
<l n="tr">from ship to ship, until that son and sire,</l>
<l n="tr">with that whole tribe, were unto ashes burned</l>
<l n="tr">in one huge holocaust—myself its crown!</l>
<l n="tr">Great orb of light whose holy beam surveys</l>
<l n="tr">all earthly deeds! Great Juno, patroness</l>
<l n="tr">of conjugal distress, who knowest all!</l>
<l n="tr">Pale Hecate, whose name the witches cry</l>
<l n="tr">at midnight crossways! O avenging furies!</l>
<l n="tr">O gods that guard Queen Dido's dying breath!</l>
<l n="tr">Give ear, and to my guiltless misery</l>
<l n="tr">extend your power. Hear me what I pray!</l>
<l n="tr">If it be fated that yon creature curst</l>
<l n="tr">drift to the shore and happy haven find,</l>
<l n="tr">if Father Iove's irrevocable word</l>
<l n="tr">such goal decree—there may he be assailed</l>
<l n="tr">by peoples fierce and bold. A banished man,</l>
<l n="tr">from his Iulus' kisses sundered far,</l>
<l n="tr">may his own eyes see miserably slain</l>
<l n="tr">his kin and kind, and sue for alien arms.</l>
<l n="tr">nor when he basely bows him to receive</l>
<l n="tr">terms of unequal peace, shall he be blest</l>
<l n="tr">with sceptre or with life; but perish there</l>
<l n="tr">before his time, and lie without a grave</l>
<l n="tr">upon the barren sand. For this I pray.</l>
<l n="tr">This dying word is flowing from my heart</l>
<l n="tr">with my spilt blood. And—O ye Tyrians! I</l>
<l n="tr">sting with your hatred all his seed and tribe </l>
<l n="tr">forevermore. This is the offering </l>
<l n="tr">my ashes ask. Betwixt our nations twain,</l>
<l n="tr"> No Iove! No truce or amity! Arise,</l>
<l n="tr"> Out of my dust, unknown Avenger, rise!</l>
<l n="tr">To harry and lay waste with sword and flame</l>
<l n="tr">those Dardan settlers, and to vex them sore,</l>
<l n="tr">to-day, to-morrow, and as long as power</l>
<l n="tr">is thine to use! My dying curse arrays</l>
<l n="tr">shore against shore and the opposing seas</l>
<l n="tr">in shock of arms with arms. May living foes</l>
<l n="tr">pass down from sire to son insatiate war!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="630" unit="card" />She said. From point to point her purpose flew,</l>
<l n="tr">seeking without delay to quench the flame</l>
<l n="tr">of her loathed life. Brief bidding she addressed</l>
<l n="tr">to <placeName key="tgn,7000645" authname="tgn,7000645">Barce</placeName> then, Sichaeus' nurse (her own</l>
<l n="tr">lay dust and ashes in a lonely grave</l>
<l n="tr">beside the Tyrian shore), “Go, nurse, and call</l>
<l n="tr">my sister Anna! Bid her quickly bathe</l>
<l n="tr">her limbs in living water, and procure</l>
<l n="tr">due victims for our expiating fires.</l>
<l n="tr">bid her make haste. Go, bind on thy own brow</l>
<l n="tr">the sacred fillet. For to Stygian Jove</l>
<l n="tr">it is my purpose now to consummate</l>
<l n="tr">the sacrifice ordained, ending my woe,</l>
<l n="tr">and touch with flame the Trojan's funeral pyre.”</l>
<l n="tr">The aged crone to do her bidding ran</l>
<l n="tr">with trembling zeal. But Dido (horror-struck</l>
<l n="tr">at her own dread design, unstrung with fear,</l>
<l n="tr">her bloodshot eyes wide-rolling, and her cheek</l>
<l n="tr">twitching and fever-spotted, her cold brow</l>
<l n="tr">blanched with approaching death)—sped past the doors</l>
<l n="tr">into the palace garden; there she leaped,</l>
<l n="tr">a frenzied creature, on the lofty pyre</l>
<l n="tr">and drew the Trojan's sword; a gift not asked</l>
<l n="tr">for use like this! When now she saw the garb</l>
<l n="tr">of Ilian fashion, and the nuptial couch</l>
<l n="tr">she knew too well, she lingered yet awhile</l>
<l n="tr">for memory and tears, and, falling prone</l>
<l n="tr">on that cold bed, outpoured a last farewell:</l>
<l n="tr">“Sweet relics! Ever dear when Fate and Heaven</l>
<l n="tr">upon me smiled, receive my parting breath,</l>
<l n="tr">and from my woe set free! My life is done.</l>
<l n="tr">I have accomplished what my lot allowed;</l>
<l n="tr">and now my spirit to the world of death</l>
<l n="tr">in royal honor goes. The founder I</l>
<l n="tr">of yonder noble city, I have seen</l>
<l n="tr">walls at my bidding rise. I was avenged</l>
<l n="tr">for my slain husband: I chastised the crimes</l>
<l n="tr">of our injurious brother. Woe is me!</l>
<l n="tr">Blest had I been, beyond deserving blest, </l>
<l n="tr">if but the Trojan galleys ne'er had moored</l>
<l n="tr">upon my kingdom's bound!”<milestone ed="p" n="659" unit="card" />So saying, she pressed</l>
<l n="tr">one last kiss on the couch. “Though for my death</l>
<l n="tr">no vengeance fall, O, give me death!” she cried.</l>
<l n="tr">“O thus! O thus! it is my will to take</l>
<l n="tr">the journey to the dark. From yonder sea</l>
<l n="tr">may his cold Trojan eyes discern the flames</l>
<l n="tr">that make me ashes! Be this cruel death</l>
<l n="tr">his omen as he sails!” She spoke no more.</l>
<l n="tr">But almost ere she ceased, her maidens all</l>
<l n="tr">thronged to obey her cry, and found their Queen</l>
<l n="tr">prone fallen on the sword, the reeking steel</l>
<l n="tr">still in her bloody hands. Shrill clamor flew</l>
<l n="tr">along the lofty halls; wild rumor spread</l>
<l n="tr">through the whole smitten city: Ioud lament,</l>
<l n="tr">groans and the wail of women echoed on</l>
<l n="tr">from roof to roof, and to the dome of air</l>
<l n="tr">the noise of mourning rose. Such were the cry</l>
<l n="tr">if a besieging host should break the walls</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> or old <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, and wrathful flames</l>
<l n="tr">o'er towers of kings and worshipped altars roll.</l>
<l n="tr">Her sister heard. Half in a swoon, she ran</l>
<l n="tr">with trembling steps, where thickest was the throng,</l>
<l n="tr">beating her breast, while with a desperate hand</l>
<l n="tr">she tore at her own face, and called aloud</l>
<l n="tr">upon the dying Queen. “Was it for this</l>
<l n="tr">my own true sister used me with such guile?</l>
<l n="tr">O, was this horrid deed the dire intent</l>
<l n="tr">of altars, Iofty couch, and funeral fires?</l>
<l n="tr">What shall I tell for chiefest of my woes?</l>
<l n="tr">Lost that I am! Why, though in death, cast off</l>
<l n="tr">thy sister from thy heart? Why not invite</l>
<l n="tr">one mortal stroke for both, a single sword,</l>
<l n="tr">one agony together? But these hands</l>
<l n="tr">built up thy pyre; and my voice implored</l>
<l n="tr">the blessing of our gods, who granted me</l>
<l n="tr">that thou shouldst perish thus—and I not know!</l>
<l n="tr">In thy self-slaughter, sister, thou hast slain</l>
<l n="tr">myself, thy people, the grave counsellors</l>
<l n="tr">of <placeName key="tgn,7002861" authname="tgn,7002861">Sidon</placeName>, and yon city thou didst build</l>
<l n="tr">to be thy throne!—Go, fetch me water, there!</l>
<l n="tr">That I may bathe those gashes! If there be</l>
<l n="tr">one hovering breath that stays, let my fond lips</l>
<l n="tr">discover and receive!” So saying, she sprang up</l>
<l n="tr">from stair to stair, and, clasping to her breast</l>
<l n="tr">her sister's dying form, moaned grievously,</l>
<l n="tr">and staunched the dark blood with her garment's fold.</l>
<l n="tr">Vainly would Dido lift her sinking eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">but backward fell, while at her heart the wound</l>
<l n="tr">opened afresh; three times with straining arm</l>
<l n="tr">she rose; three times dropped helpless, her dimmed eyes</l>
<l n="tr">turned skyward, seeking the sweet light of day, —</l>
<l n="tr">which when she saw, she groaned. <milestone ed="p" n="693" unit="card" />Great Juno then</l>
<l n="tr">looked down in mercy on that lingering pain</l>
<l n="tr">and labor to depart: from realms divine</l>
<l n="tr">she sent the goddess of the rainbow wing,</l>
<l n="tr">Iris, to set the struggling spirit free</l>
<l n="tr">and loose its fleshly coil. For since the end</l>
<l n="tr">came not by destiny, nor was the doom</l>
<l n="tr">of guilty deed, but of a hapless wight</l>
<l n="tr">to sudden madness stung, ere ripe to die,</l>
<l n="tr">therefore the Queen of Hades had not shorn</l>
<l n="tr">the fair tress from her forehead, nor assigned</l>
<l n="tr">that soul to Stygian dark. So Iris came</l>
<l n="tr">on dewy, saffron pinions down from heaven,</l>
<l n="tr">a thousand colors on her radiant way,</l>
<l n="tr">from the opposing sun. She stayed her flight</l>
<l n="tr">above that pallid brow: “I come with power</l>
<l n="tr">to make this gift to Death. I set thee free</l>
<l n="tr">from thy frail body's bound.” With her right hand</l>
<l n="tr">she cut the tress: then through its every limb</l>
<l n="tr">the sinking form grew cold; the vital breath</l>
<l n="tr">fled forth, departing on the viewless air.</l></div1>
</body></text></TEI.2>
